<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ruby | Brandon Hilkert]]></title>
  <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/categories/ruby/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-04T06:15:48-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brandon Hilkert]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[brandonhilkert@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using Rails Fixtures To Seed a Database]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/using-rails-fixtures-to-seed-a-database/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-04T06:13:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/using-rails-fixtures-to-seed-a-database</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s no mystery that <a href="/blog/7-reasons-why-im-sticking-with-minitest-and-fixtures-in-rails/">I’ve grown to love Rails fixtures</a>. And I tend to mostly use relational databases in my applications, <a href="/blog/rails-gemfile-teardown-2014/">specifically PostgreSQL</a>.</p>

<p>Most applications have ancillary data that’s required to support the main function of the application — think drop-downs with states for shipping or credit card type.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>This data is almost always never interesting, but completely necessary for the application to work as expected. So when it comes to time send your little baby to production, only to find your users can’t pay because they can’t pick their credit card type, your world comes crashing down.</p>

<p>If you have those credit card types in fixtures from the start, loading them in to your development of production database is just a <code>rake</code> task away.</p>

<h2>The Problem</h2>

<p>Let’s assume our application requires us have a list of supported credit card types, and the user is required to pick from the list to pay for the awesome stuff we sell. A sample fixture might look like:</p>

<p>```
visa:
  name: Visa</p>

<p>mastercard:
  name: Mastercard</p>

<p>amex:
  name: American Express
```</p>

<p>This is a somewhat trivial example because the <code>name</code> matches what one might expect in a potential transaction record if we had a <code>credit_card_type</code> field or something similar if we denormalized.</p>

<p>Perhaps we have a field <code>credit_card_type_id</code> in a <code>transactions</code> table that references the foreign key of the related <code>CreditCardType</code> record.</p>

<p>So how do we get these records in to our development and production databases?</p>

<h2>The Solution</h2>

<p>Fortunately, Rails has our backs. The following rake test is available from a default Rails application:</p>

<p><code>
$ bin/rake -T
...
rake db:fixtures:load # Load fixtures into the current environment's database
</code></p>

<p>The <code>db:fixtures:load</code> task is an interesting start, but quickly we realize it might be a little heavy-handed. If this application has users, we probably wouldn&rsquo;t want to copy them to production. They might, however, be a great starting pointing for development.</p>

<p>So how do we handle getting trivial model data in to production for only specific models?</p>

<p>It turns out that we can specify <strong>ONLY</strong> the models we want to load by using the <code>FIXTURES</code> environment variable:</p>

<p><code>
rake db:fixtures:load FIXTURES=credit_card_types
</code></p>

<p><em>Note: The name of the fixture file (usually the database table name) should be used as the value for <code>FIXTURES</code>, not the model name.</em></p>

<p>With that single command, any environment we specify will immediately get the data for our 3 credit card types.</p>

<p>A word of warning, if we run this command multiple times, it will seed the table multiple times. It&rsquo;s not idempotent.</p>

<p>Additionally, if we wanted to load more than just a single fixture, we can specify the names of the files separated by commas:</p>

<p><code>
rake db:fixtures:load FIXTURES=credit_card_types,states,cities
</code></p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s take a quick look at how Rails implements this functionality, specifically the determination of single models:</p>

<p>```
fixtures_dir = if ENV[&lsquo;FIXTURES_DIR&rsquo;]</p>

<pre><code>             File.join base_dir, ENV['FIXTURES_DIR']
           else
             base_dir
           end
</code></pre>

<p>fixture_files = if ENV[&lsquo;FIXTURES&rsquo;]</p>

<pre><code>              ENV['FIXTURES'].split(',')
            else
              # The use of String#[] here is to support namespaced fixtures
              Dir["#{fixtures_dir}/**/*.yml"].map {|f| f[(fixtures_dir.size + 1)..-5] }
            end
</code></pre>

<p>ActiveRecord::FixtureSet.create_fixtures(fixtures_dir, fixture_files)
```</p>

<p>If the <code>FIXTURES</code> variable is present, code teases appart the model names and looks in the fixtures directory and loads the YAML fixture file for that table name.</p>

<p>An interesting side note, it&rsquo;s possible to specify alternate directories for fixture using the <code>FIXTURES_DIR</code> variable. I personally haven taken advantage of this, but could be useful if you want to keep specific fixture files for production that might be different than those that reside in <code>test/fixtures/*</code>.</p>

<p>I wouldn&rsquo;t suggesting using this approach for anything that needs to reference other foreign keys. When you&rsquo;re transferring to a different database, foreign keys will not match and your application will likely not work as expected.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>This approach has saved me quite a bit of time in my last few applications. Build it once, use it everywhere. As mentioned above, using this approach to seed database records  with a foreign key should be avoided.</p>

<p>Most applications have a number of tasks needed for a developer to get up and running. Combining fixture data with additional seed data placed in <code>db/seeds.rb</code> can give you the best of both worlds, while still ensuring you have robust data to test against.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2014 In Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/2014-in-review/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-29T14:57:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/2014-in-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For the past 2 years, I’ve committed myself to <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/be-ambitious/">specific
goals</a> for the year to come. Most
people call them New Year’s Resolutions. Heck, I probably even referred to them
as “resolutions” too. But the more I thought about it, the more it dawned on me
that a “resolution” felt more like a fix for something — something that didn&rsquo;t
go well in the previous year. Think weight loss (everyone makes this resolution at least once in their life) or a dedication to be more focused.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Mine have been more of the bucket list variety. The first was <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/loyalty/">completing an Ironman</a>. The second, <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/be-ambitious/">writing a book</a>.</p>

<p>Both felt almost too big initially, but ultimately led to opportunities and
lifestyle changes I would’ve never expected once finished. So naturally, with
2014 winding down, the question becomes <strong>&ldquo;what’s the goal for 2015?&rdquo;</strong>.</p>

<p>And the answer is&hellip;<em>I don’t know</em>.</p>

<p>It doesn’t mean I’m not going to do anything. In fact, it probably means the
opposite. I’m just not going to set out with a specific goal in mind. If
halfway through something, I want to stop and do something else, so be it.</p>

<p>I remember during my training for the Ironman (9 months total), I constantly thought about what I would do with my free time when it was over. Every time my alarm went off at 5am, I thought about what it would feel like to get another 2 hours of sleep. It was endless. Nine months was a long time to have those thoughts and, perhaps, why I was so well positioned to write and launch the book (I had 9 months to think about what was next and how to accomplish it).</p>

<p>Always having your sights set on the future can wear on you though.</p>

<p>Without those feelings now, I’m going to let 2015 take me wherever it does. I don’t have any expectations financially or professionally. I’m going to do my best to make the most out of every moment and appreciate more of the small things. It’s so easy to skip over the small things and in many cases, the small things are actually the best things. And we don’t realize it until they’re gone.</p>

<p>2014 was a great year in all. Here are a few of the events that stand out the most:</p>

<ul>
<li>my wife and I <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/about/">welcomed our son, Cruz</a></li>
<li>my wife and I celebrated our 4 year anniversary</li>
<li>wrote a book, <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/books/build-a-ruby-gem/">Build a Ruby Gem</a></li>
<li>provided a <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/courses/build-a-ruby-gem/">free email course on building a Ruby gem</a> to 1,218 people</li>
<li>connected with 2,645 people through my <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/newsletter/">newsletter</a></li>
<li>built a <a href="https://www.funneloptimizer.io/">funnel optimization service for bloggers selling products</a></li>
<li>published 24 <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/archives/">articles</a></li>
<li>saw <a href="https://github.com/brandonhilkert/sucker_punch">Sucker Punch</a> <a href="https://rubygems.org/gems/sucker_punch">downloaded over 225k times</a></li>
<li>celebrated <a href="https://github.com/brandonhilkert/sucker_punch">Sucker Punch</a> being <a href="http://guides.rubyonrails.org/active_job_basics.html">integrated in to Rails</a></li>
<li>made my <a href="https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/16898">first commit to Rails</a> (even if it was small!)</li>
<li>traveled to Jackson Hole, WY</li>
<li>built a <a href="https://vuier.com/">pay-to-view video platform</a> with a few friends</li>
<li>built a <a href="https://perform.io/">performance management system</a></li>
<li>renovated my
  <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/images/2014/bathroom-before.jpg">kids'</a>
  <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/images/2014/bathroom-after.jpg">bathroom</a></li>
<li>built a deployment system for <a href="https://www.pipelinedeals.com/">PipelineDeals</a> and supporting services that I’m very proud of</li>
<li>built a staging server management application</li>
<li>built <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/how-to-win-friends-and-in/cbmeigkjdnilgodhnhagokhoehbpkdcc?hl=en-US">3</a> <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/pipelinedeals-crm-contact/ieaafnaonfabpgpkkeglkeodkpiijjdd?hl=en-US">chrome</a> <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/pipelinedeals-gmail/fdfifknmbmalmgdjmnhkcfholdgacikl?hl=en-US">extensions</a>, the latter being my first <a href="http://facebook.github.io/react/">React</a> app</li>
<li>started a <a href="http://walnutstlabs.com/event/walnut-st-labs-night-owls/">weekly tech gathering</a> at a <a href="http://walnutstlabs.com">local co-working space</a></li>
<li>stopped push email notifications on all my devices (strongly recommended)</li>
<li>saw <a href="http://defriendnotifierapp.com/">Defriend Notifier</a> be used by 30,128 people</li>
<li>started exploring other programming languages, specifically <a href="https://golang.org/">Go</a> and <a href="http://elixir-lang.org/">Elixir</a></li>
</ul>


<p>I’m excited for 2015!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Ruby Refactor: Dependency Injection Options]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/a-ruby-refactor-exploring-dependency-injection-options/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-17T07:07:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/a-ruby-refactor-exploring-dependency-injection-options</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently wrote some code to interface with Stripe’s webhooks. After looking at the code and tests, I decided I needed to do something to make it easier to test <em>all</em> pricing tiers— something I wasn’t able to easily do from the start.</p>

<p><a href="http://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dependency_injection">Dependency injection</a> was a necessary piece of that puzzle. I’ve always been curious about the various forms of dependency injection and the effects each would have on the code. Below I explore 2 options (constructor injection and setter injection).</p>

<!--more-->


<p>In the end, setter injection felt for more natural for this case and it didn’t interfere with the classes argument list and felt ancillary to the responsibility of the code. While the change in code was small, it has a huge impact on my confidence in the code and associated tests.</p>

<h2>The Code</h2>

<p>The class below is responsible for handling Stripe’s <code>invoice.created</code> webhook. Prior to a customer being billed monthly subscription, Stripe will ping your application (if configured) — giving you the opportunity to add additional line items (think metered billing…). It could be additional services, or perhaps the entire bill itself (this use case). Nevertheless, the responsibility of the class is to create an invoice item based on the customer’s usage during the previous period.</p>

<p>```
module StripeEvent
  class InvoiceCreated</p>

<pre><code>attr_reader :payload

def initialize(payload)
  @payload = payload
end

def perform
  Stripe::InvoiceItem.create(
    customer: user.stripe_id,
    amount: additional_charges_in_cents,
    currency: "usd",
    description: "Usage charges"
  )
end

private

def additional_charges_in_cents
  Billing::Tier.new(usage).additional_charges_in_cents
end

def usage
  Billing::Usage.new(user).last_30_days
end

def user
  @user ||= User.find_by(stripe_id: payload["data"]["object"]["customer"])
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>I wrote this code pretty quickly and felt pretty good about it. The responsibility of determining the pricing tier had been broken out in to a separate class, as well as determining the customer’s actual usage. At least I thought they were…</p>

<p>So what about the tests?</p>

<p>```
require &lsquo;test_helper&rsquo;</p>

<p>class InvoiceCreatedTest &lt; ActiveSupport::TestCase
  def setup</p>

<pre><code>@payload = {
  "data" =&gt; {
    "object" =&gt; {
      "customer" =&gt; "stripe_brandon"
    }
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  test &lsquo;adds invoice item based on usage&rsquo; do</p>

<pre><code>Stripe::InvoiceItem.expects(:create).with(
  customer: "stripe_brandon",
  amount: 1900,
  currency: "usd",
  description: "Usage charges"
).returns(true)
StripeEvent::InvoiceCreated.new(@payload).perform
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  test &lsquo;adds next level charge for usage&rsquo; do</p>

<pre><code>Stat.create!(user: users(:brandon), step: steps(:nav_one), impressions: 3_000, date: 5.days.ago)

Stripe::InvoiceItem.expects(:create).with(
  customer: "stripe_brandon",
  amount: 4900,
  currency: "usd",
  description: "Usage charges"
).returns(true)
StripeEvent::InvoiceCreated.new(@payload).perform
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>The first thing I noticed with this setup was the detailed usage of <code>Stripe::InvoiceItem.expects</code>. I wasn’t sure if this was necessarily a bad thing because it was a third-party service and it seemed like reasonable boundary of the application.</p>

<p>Aside from the mock, another thing that bothered me was the difficulty simulating different pricing tiers and customer usage. You probably noticed the <code>Stat.create!…</code> in the last test. I could’ve duplicated <code>Stat</code> entries until I reached some arbitrary level of usage that bumped this user to the next pricing tier. But that felt risky and very dependent on knowing the actual value of the subsequent tier.</p>

<p>What if I wanted to change the ceiling of that tier next month? I’d have to come in here and adjust the stats being created until it totaled something above the adjustment. It just felt weird…</p>

<p>What if we had a way to easily swap in implementations of the <code>Billing::Usage</code>? It would then allow me to concoct any combination of usage and mock the expected values sent to Stripe.</p>

<h2>Setter Injection</h2>

<p>In a few other articles, I’ve heard this termed “accessors as collaborators”. Whatever the name, it was surprising how such a little a change could produce so much flexibility in my tests. And with that additional flexibility came confidence because it allowed me to test the edge cases with minimal overhead.</p>

<p>```
module StripeEvent
  class InvoiceCreated</p>

<pre><code>attr_writer :usage_service
attr_reader :payload

def initialize(payload)
  @payload = payload
end

def perform
  if user.created_at &lt; 14.days.ago
    Stripe::InvoiceItem.create(
      customer: user.stripe_id,
      amount: additional_charges_in_cents,
      currency: "usd",
      description: "Usage charges"
    )
  end
end

private

def additional_charges_in_cents
  Billing::Tier.new(usage).additional_charges_in_cents
end

def usage
  usage_service.last_30_days
end

def usage_service
  @usage_service ||= Billing::Usage.new(user)
end

def user
  @user ||= User.find_by(stripe_id: payload["data"]["object"]["customer"])
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>A couple things changed:</p>

<ol>
<li><p><code>usage_service</code> was created to extract the code to calculate customer usage</p></li>
<li><p>The <code>usage</code> method now calls the <code>last_30_days</code> method on <code>usage_service</code></p>

<p> This is interesting because you’ll notice now that the only important idea about <code>usage_service</code> is the   fact that is has a <code>last_30_days</code> method. We can now take comfort in the idea that <code>usage_service</code> could    be anything really, as long as it implements the <code>last_30_days</code> method.</p></li>
<li><p><code>attr_writer :usage_service</code> was added to allow for other implementations of the usage class</p></li>
</ol>


<p>This allows us to inject other forms of the <code>usage_service</code> to simulate more or less customer usage:</p>

<p>```
require &lsquo;test_helper&rsquo;</p>

<p>class InvoiceCreatedTest &lt; ActiveSupport::TestCase
  def setup</p>

<pre><code>@payload = {
  "data" =&gt; {
    "object" =&gt; {
      "customer" =&gt; "stripe_brandon"
    }
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  test &lsquo;adds invoice item based on usage&rsquo; do</p>

<pre><code>Stripe::InvoiceItem.expects(:create).with(
  customer: "stripe_brandon",
  amount: 1900,
  currency: "usd",
  description: "Usage charges"
)
StripeEvent::InvoiceCreated.new(@payload).perform
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  test &lsquo;adds next level charge for usage&rsquo; do</p>

<pre><code>Stat.create!(user: users(:brandon), step: steps(:nav_one), impressions: 3_000, date: 5.days.ago)

Stripe::InvoiceItem.expects(:create).with(
  customer: "stripe_brandon",
  amount: 4900,
  currency: "usd",
  description: "Usage charges"
)
StripeEvent::InvoiceCreated.new(@payload).perform
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  test &lsquo;adds highest tier&rsquo; do</p>

<pre><code>Stripe::InvoiceItem.expects(:create).with(
  customer: "stripe_brandon",
  amount: 49900,
  currency: "usd",
  description: "Usage charges"
)
inv = StripeEvent::InvoiceCreated.new(@payload)
inv.usage_service = Level5Usage.new
inv.perform
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  test &lsquo;adds 2nd highest tier&rsquo; do</p>

<pre><code>Stripe::InvoiceItem.expects(:create).with(
  customer: "stripe_brandon",
  amount: 24900,
  currency: "usd",
  description: "Usage charges"
)
inv = StripeEvent::InvoiceCreated.new(@payload)
inv.usage_service = Level4Usage.new
inv.perform
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  test &lsquo;adds middle tier&rsquo; do</p>

<pre><code>Stripe::InvoiceItem.expects(:create).with(
  customer: "stripe_brandon",
  amount: 12900,
  currency: "usd",
  description: "Usage charges"
)
inv = StripeEvent::InvoiceCreated.new(@payload)
inv.usage_service = Level3Usage.new
inv.perform
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  test &lsquo;adds 2nd tier&rsquo; do</p>

<pre><code>Stripe::InvoiceItem.expects(:create).with(
  customer: "stripe_brandon",
  amount: 4900,
  currency: "usd",
  description: "Usage charges"
)
inv = StripeEvent::InvoiceCreated.new(@payload)
inv.usage_service = Level2Usage.new
inv.perform
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  test &lsquo;adds 1st tier&rsquo; do</p>

<pre><code>Stripe::InvoiceItem.expects(:create).with(
  customer: "stripe_brandon",
  amount: 1900,
  currency: "usd",
  description: "Usage charges"
)
inv = StripeEvent::InvoiceCreated.new(@payload)
inv.usage_service = Level1Usage.new
inv.perform
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  private</p>

<p>  Level5Usage = Class.new { def last_30_days; 2_000_000; end }
  Level4Usage = Class.new { def last_30_days; 900_000; end }
  Level3Usage = Class.new { def last_30_days; 190_000; end }
  Level2Usage = Class.new { def last_30_days; 19_000; end }
  Level1Usage = Class.new { def last_30_days; 1_900; end }
```</p>

<p>I’ve created classes for each usage tier that implement the <code>last_30_days</code> method. In real life, this usage service is more complex, but we can test the complexity of it alone through unit tests. The responsibility of this class is to ensure invoice items are added to Stripe correctly, so removing the complexity of <code>Billing::Usage</code> form this test allows us to maximize this test’s value and keep us isolated from the implementation of <code>Billing::Usage</code> — assuming it implements the <code>last_30_days</code> method.</p>

<h2>Constructor Injection</h2>

<p>Most dependency injection posts focus on constructor injection. The idea being that an implementation can be supplied. If not, a reasonable default will be provided. How might that change this scenario?</p>

<p>```
module StripeEvent
  class InvoiceCreated</p>

<pre><code>attr_reader :payload

def initialize(payload, usage_service = Billing::Usage)
  @payload = payload
  @usage_service = usage_service
end

def perform
  if user.created_at &lt; 14.days.ago
    Stripe::InvoiceItem.create(
      customer: user.stripe_id,
      amount: additional_charges_in_cents,
      currency: "usd",
      description: "Usage charges"
    )
  end
end

private

def additional_charges_in_cents
  Billing::Tier.new(usage).additional_charges_in_cents
end

def usage
  @usage_service.new(user).last_30_days
end

def user
  @user ||= User.find_by(stripe_id: payload["data"]["object"]["customer"])
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>Because the <code>usage</code> method requires instantiation from within the class, I had to update the fake test Usage classes to accept <code>user</code> as an argument during instantiation:</p>

<p>```
require &lsquo;test_helper&rsquo;</p>

<p>class InvoiceCreatedTest &lt; ActiveSupport::TestCase
  def setup</p>

<pre><code>@payload = {
  "data" =&gt; {
    "object" =&gt; {
      "customer" =&gt; "stripe_brandon"
    }
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  test &lsquo;adds invoice item based on usage&rsquo; do</p>

<pre><code>Stripe::InvoiceItem.expects(:create).with(
  customer: "stripe_brandon",
  amount: 1900,
  currency: "usd",
  description: "Usage charges"
)
StripeEvent::InvoiceCreated.new(@payload).perform
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  test &lsquo;adds next level charge for usage&rsquo; do</p>

<pre><code>Stat.create!(user: users(:brandon), step: steps(:nav_one), impressions: 3_000, date: 5.days.ago)

Stripe::InvoiceItem.expects(:create).with(
  customer: "stripe_brandon",
  amount: 4900,
  currency: "usd",
  description: "Usage charges"
)
StripeEvent::InvoiceCreated.new(@payload).perform
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  test &lsquo;adds highest tier&rsquo; do</p>

<pre><code>Stripe::InvoiceItem.expects(:create).with(
  customer: "stripe_brandon",
  amount: 49900,
  currency: "usd",
  description: "Usage charges"
)
inv = StripeEvent::InvoiceCreated.new(@payload, Level5Usage)
inv.perform
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  test &lsquo;adds 2nd highest tier&rsquo; do</p>

<pre><code>Stripe::InvoiceItem.expects(:create).with(
  customer: "stripe_brandon",
  amount: 24900,
  currency: "usd",
  description: "Usage charges"
)
inv = StripeEvent::InvoiceCreated.new(@payload, Level4Usage)
inv.perform
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  test &lsquo;adds middle tier&rsquo; do</p>

<pre><code>Stripe::InvoiceItem.expects(:create).with(
  customer: "stripe_brandon",
  amount: 12900,
  currency: "usd",
  description: "Usage charges"
)
inv = StripeEvent::InvoiceCreated.new(@payload, Level3Usage)
inv.perform
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  test &lsquo;adds 2nd tier&rsquo; do</p>

<pre><code>Stripe::InvoiceItem.expects(:create).with(
  customer: "stripe_brandon",
  amount: 4900,
  currency: "usd",
  description: "Usage charges"
)
inv = StripeEvent::InvoiceCreated.new(@payload, Level2Usage)
inv.perform
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  test &lsquo;adds 1st tier&rsquo; do</p>

<pre><code>Stripe::InvoiceItem.expects(:create).with(
  customer: "stripe_brandon",
  amount: 1900,
  currency: "usd",
  description: "Usage charges"
)
inv = StripeEvent::InvoiceCreated.new(@payload, Level1Usage)
inv.perform
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  private</p>

<p>  Level5Usage = Struct.new(:user) { def last_30_days; 2_000_000; end }
  Level4Usage = Struct.new(:user) { def last_30_days; 900_000; end }
  Level3Usage = Struct.new(:user) { def last_30_days; 190_000; end }
  Level2Usage = Struct.new(:user) { def last_30_days; 19_000; end }
  Level1Usage = Struct.new(:user) { def last_30_days; 1_900; end }
```</p>

<p>The resulting test classes seem overly complex and sprinkled with details that aren’t particularly relevant to its responsibility. If we were to pass in an already instantiated usage class as an argument, it means we would have to already know the user before-hand, which means we’d have to parse <code>@user ||= User.find_by(stripe_id: payload["data"]["object"]["customer”])</code> outside of this class. I don’t love that solution — the parent that calls this <code>InvoiceCreated</code> class is pretty minimal and I wanted to keep it that way.</p>

<p>Another option would be to provide <code>user</code> as an argument to the to the <code>last_30_days</code> method:</p>

<p><code>
def usage
  @usage_service.new.last_30_days(user)
end
</code></p>

<p>We could then change our fake test usage classes back to:</p>

<p><code>
Level1Usage = Class.new { def last_30_days; 1_900; end }
</code></p>

<p>Notice the lack of <code>Struct</code> with an argument…</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>Of the two options, I prefer the setter injector in this case. There’s something about changing the signature of a class just for tests that didn’t feel natural.</p>

<p>An accessor (or writer…), in this case, provided the same flexibility without changing the signature. I like being able to quickly look at the argument list of <code>initialize</code> and clearly understand its roles and responsibilities within the system.</p>

<p>Which do you prefer?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rails Gemfile Teardown - 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/rails-gemfile-teardown-2014/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-03T13:14:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/rails-gemfile-teardown-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What’s the first thing you look at when you see the source code of a Rails project?</p>

<p>For me, it’s the <code>Gemfile</code>. Think about it&hellip;there&rsquo;s very few other files that contain so much information. It describes the building blocks of the application. And at times, you can even see specific features of the application.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>A <code>Gemfile</code> also includes hints about preference and style. And style is something most Ruby developers are very passionate about. It doesn’t take long to find the story of a Rubyist describing their “love at first sight” experience with the language. It’s hard to find another file in a Rails project that’s so telling.</p>

<p>A year ago, I wrote about the <a href="/blog/patterns-in-a-rails-gemfile/">Ruby gems I regularly use in my Rails applications</a>. Because technology and the tools we use change so fast, I thought it’d be interesting to take a look at one of my more recent Gemfiles to see what’s changed.</p>

<h2>Rails Templates</h2>

<p>As I mentioned in the last <a href="/blog/patterns-in-a-rails-gemfile/">Gemfile post</a>, I tend to write a bunch of small applications sprinkled around some larger ones. Despite the size of the project, I feel like I’ve honed in a set of Ruby gems that feel comfortable and productive for me and my workflow.</p>

<p>Knowing the act of bootstrapping a Rails project is sometimes tedious, I took some time to build a <a href="https://github.com/brandonhilkert/rails_templates">Rails template</a> around the gems and patterns I commonly use. I’ll definitely be writing about this experience in the future since there seems to be very little discussion about it.</p>

<p>In short, extracting my preferences to a template has been a HUGE time saver. It no longer feels like a burden to run <code>rails new</code>. I can jump right in and have a consistent set of tools that enable me to be productive within a few minutes.</p>

<h2>My 2014 Gemfile</h2>

<p>The <code>Gemfile</code> below is one of the larger projects I worked on this year. I thought it’d give a good sense of some of my more practical everyday preferences, along with some feature-specific choices for this particular application.</p>

<p>```
source &lsquo;<a href="https://rubygems.org">https://rubygems.org</a>&rsquo;</p>

<p>ruby &lsquo;2.1.4&rsquo;</p>

<p>gem &lsquo;rails&rsquo;, &lsquo;4.1.8&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;pg&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;sass-rails&rsquo;, &lsquo;~> 4.0.3&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;uglifier&rsquo;, &lsquo;>= 1.3.0&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;coffee-rails&rsquo;, &lsquo;~> 4.0.0&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;jquery-rails&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;turbolinks&rsquo;</p>

<p>gem &lsquo;bcrypt-ruby&rsquo;, &lsquo;~> 3.1.2&rsquo;</p>

<p>group :development, :test do
  gem &lsquo;pry&rsquo;
end</p>

<p>group :test do
  gem &lsquo;selenium-webdriver&rsquo;
  gem &lsquo;capybara&rsquo;
  gem &lsquo;timecop&rsquo;
  gem &lsquo;mocha&rsquo;
end</p>

<p>group :development do
  gem &lsquo;quiet_assets&rsquo;
  gem &lsquo;spring&rsquo;
  gem &lsquo;bullet&rsquo;
  gem &lsquo;stripe_tester&rsquo;, &lsquo;~> 0.1.0&rsquo;
end</p>

<p>group :production, :demo do
  gem &lsquo;rails_12factor&rsquo;
  gem &lsquo;heroku-deflater&rsquo;
end</p>

<p>gem &lsquo;font-awesome-rails&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;unicorn&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;bootstrap-sass&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;sidekiq&rsquo;, require: &lsquo;sidekiq/web&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;sinatra&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;local_time&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;gravatar_image_tag&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;so_meta&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;chronic&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;recurrence&rsquo;</p>

<p>gem &lsquo;premailer-rails&rsquo;</p>

<p>gem &lsquo;momentjs-rails&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;bootstrap3-datetimepicker-rails&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;bootstrap-switch-rails&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;bootstrap-wysihtml5-rails&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;bootstrap-select-rails&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;autosize-rails&rsquo;</p>

<p>gem &lsquo;aws-sdk&rsquo;</p>

<p>gem &lsquo;html-pipeline&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;rinku&rsquo;</p>

<p>gem &lsquo;newrelic_rpm&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;doc_raptor&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;stripe&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;jquery-ui-rails&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;active_model_serializers&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;rubyzip&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;render_anywhere&rsquo;, require: false
gem &lsquo;pusher&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;filepicker-rails&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;memcachier&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;dalli&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;intercom-rails&rsquo;
```</p>

<p>A few comments:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>I’ve standardized on <a href="http://www.postgresql.org/">Postgres</a> as the database for my apps, even in development. It’s reliable and allows me to be sure that the code I write will work the same way in production, since I tend to deploy most of my apps to <a href="https://www.heroku.com/">Heroku</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>I leave <code>turbolinks</code> on. Judging from recent posts and comments within the community, this will probably one of the more controversial decisions.</p>

<p>  If I’m being honest, my first experience with Turbolinks wasn’t great. And by “wasn’t great”, I mean — it broke <strong>EVERYTHING</strong>! But the good news was that it brought to light the fact that I sucked at javascript. At the time, I was capable of writing <em>just</em> enough to modify form behavior or fade in an DOM element.</p>

<p>  The time had come to level up on my javascript skills. I was able to improve my javascript and also do it in a way that can took full advantage of the benefits that Turbolinks offers. Since that time, I’ve left Turbolinks on and no longer had to worry that my client-side code will stop working after clicking through a few application links.</p></li>
<li><p>I’ve standardized on using <code>has_secure_password</code> for authentication. I previously used <a href="https://github.com/plataformatec/devise">devise</a>, but found the extra features are no longer worth the additional complexity. <code>has_secure_password</code> provides me reliable authentication patterns that are simple to understand and maintain. Hence the need for <code>bcrypt</code> in the <code>Gemfile</code> above.</p></li>
<li><p>As for my test environment, I’ve written about <a href="/blog/7-reasons-why-im-sticking-with-minitest-and-fixtures-in-rails/">my switch to Minitest and fixtures</a>. I’m still just as happy with that decision as the time I wrote about it. I’ve seen Rspec go through a variety of API changes since then, and thankful I no longer have to worry about updating my test suite every couple months. I continue to find value in <code>capybara</code> and include <code>mocha</code> for the times <code>Minitest</code>’s stubbing and mocking isn’t enough (I’ve been meaning to dig in to the places I use <code>mocha</code>. I’m guessing if the code was better, I probably wouldn’t need it at all).</p></li>
<li><p><code>bullet</code> is a killer gem for tracking down performances issues. It’s saved me countless hours of debugging.</p></li>
<li><p>The inclusion of <code>spring</code> in Rails 4.1 is great. I realize it’s a bandaid in some respects, but waiting for the environment to load on every test run is a drag. I’ve found that because my tests are so responsive when <code>spring</code> is working properly, it encourages me to run my tests more often. Once setup, it works well and only in rare cases has not reloaded when it should have.</p></li>
<li><p>I generally always include <code>bootstrap</code> and <code>font-awesome</code> in my projects. Being a non-designer, it helps me get something on the screen faster, even if it’s not the final design.</p></li>
<li><p>I continue to use <code>unicorn</code>. It’s been around for so long and continues to be competitive in benchmarks against other Ruby web servers. I tested Passenger in a few applications, but got scared off when it printed the entire environment to the screen in production on Heroku on an exception. I’m told there are ways around this with some non-trivial configuration, but I think it’s a bizarre default and isn’t conducive to my workflow.</p></li>
<li><p>For the apps that need background processing, <code>sidekiq</code> continues to be my goto when a separate worker is necessary. I generally mount Sidekiq’s web UI to provide insight to the state of the jobs, which is why <code>sinatra</code> is included.</p></li>
<li><p>I’ve written about putting together <a href="/blog/relative-timestamps-in-rails/">a gem to render relative timestamps</a> on the client side. While I’d love to sit here and tell you I use it, I don’t. Basecamp’s <a href="https://github.com/basecamp/local_time">local_time</a> gem is exceptional for that need and I’m pretty sure we can count on it being updated and maintained well going forward (one of the biggest changes in my mindset for including a new gem).</p></li>
<li><p>This particular app has some pretty hairy time calculations and scheduling. It’s not something I was very experienced with prior, but found value in the combination of <code>chronic</code> and <code>recurrence</code>. Both make the process of targeting a specific <code>datetime</code> and scheduling something in the future relatively simple.</p></li>
<li><p>I included a number of bootstrap related javascript gems (<code>bootstrap3-datetimepicker-rails</code>, <code>bootstrap-switch-rails</code>, <code>bootstrap-switch-rails</code>, <code>bootstrap-select-rails</code>). All are little more than a <a href="/blog/how-to-build-a-rails-engine/">Rails engine</a> that exposes the appropriate javascript and stylesheets to the asset pipeline. These are particularly dependent on the project. I’d normally not start by including anything like this. Side note &ndash; I could’ve copied the relevant assets to <code>vendor/assets</code> rather than requiring a gem that does the same. In a few cases, some added view helpers as well.</p></li>
<li><p>I’ve standardized on using New Relic to collect application metrics and exceptions.</p></li>
<li><p>It shouldn’t be a surprise that <code>stripe</code> is the payment processor I reach for when I’m in control. It’s super developer-friendly and, at this point, I’ve done enough that integration is not much more than a copy/paste from other apps. I recently started using <code>stripe_tester</code> in the test environment. It’s been great for stubbing out calls to Stripe so the test suite continues to be performant. It also allows me to setup some unique edge-case data coming from Stripe so I can protect users from ending up in a crappy state.</p></li>
<li><p>I generally reach for <code>active_model_serializers</code> anytime I need a <code>json</code> response that contains more than a simple hash (in which case I’d continue to render it in the controller response). I’ve used the view equivalent solutions a few times (<code>jbuilder</code>, etc.) and they worked ok too, but for whatever reason, <code>active_model_serializers</code> does it for me.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>The rest are very use case-specific. And in general, the defacto solution for each (<code>pusher</code> for real-time features, <code>dalli</code> for memcached, etc.).</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>I’m happy with my current toolkit. This doesn’t mean I’m not on the lookout for shiny new things, but I’m generally a little more cautious about replacing something reliable, even if it doesn’t do everything under the sun.</p>

<p>Even though Ruby makes it easy to include third party libraries, it doesn’t mean we always should. As developers, we inherit the stability of the dependencies we include. Even though a gem’s code might be locked away behind a separate git repository, it likely has the same holes and complexities that we’re worried about in our applications. And perhaps, even more…</p>

<p><a href="https://www.ruby-toolbox.com/">Ruby toolbox</a> is a great resource when searching for a gem. I generally consider the number of downloads, age of the project and development activity when deciding which one to go with.</p>

<p>What have your favorite gems been this year?</p>

<h2>Build a Ruby Gem</h2>

<p>Ruby gems are the building blocks of Ruby/Rails applications. If you haven’t built one yourself, there’s no better time to start. Github makes it extremely to contribute to existing gems and sometimes that’s <a href="/blog/3-ways-to-get-started-contributing-to-open-source/">the easiest way to get started contributing to open source</a>. My book, <em>Build a Ruby Gem</em>, includes <a href="/books/build-a-ruby-gem/">everything you to need to get started building a Ruby gem</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rails Active Record Validation Contexts with Inheritance]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/creating-rails-active-record-validation-contexts-with-inheritance/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-18T17:20:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/creating-rails-active-record-validation-contexts-with-inheritance</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you’ve used <code>validates</code> in a Rails Active Record model, you know they work great -- at least until the first bit of complexity arises. At that point, they can quickly morph in to a ball of conditional spaghetti convoluting the initial reason the validation was added in the first place.</p>




<p>I recently had an experience using <code>has_secure_password</code> where I wanted control the length of the user-supplied password. Adding a length validation to the password accessor invalidated existing records, so I was in a bit of a bind. In the end, I sub-classed the Active Record model to create a unique model made specifically for that context. This allowed me to inherit the core functionality from the model and sprinkle on existing validations for specific use cases. This was a new tactic for me and I’m still not sure how I feel about it. I like the fact that it removed complexity from the <code>User</code> model. This, in hopes, will keep the minimize the likelihood of it becoming a God object.</p>




<!--more-->




<h2>The Problem</h2>




<p>Using <code>has_secure_password</code> is a relatively easy way to add authentication to a Rails app. In order to disguise the plain text passwords, an <a href="https://github.com/rails/rails/blob/3bdf7b80a11dcb67b18553ff1fe0da82b0cffc20/activemodel/lib/active_model/secure_password.rb#L106">accessor for the plain <code>password</code></a> is added that encrypts it before saving.</p>




<p>The only true Active Record validation <code>has_secure_password</code> adds is a <a href="https://github.com/rails/rails/blob/3bdf7b80a11dcb67b18553ff1fe0da82b0cffc20/activemodel/lib/active_model/secure_password.rb#L68">confirmation of the password</a> — and only when the password is present. This allows us to create a user object without supplying a password, or maybe saving straight to the <code>password_digest</code> field, which is used to store the encrypted password in the database.</p>




<p>I wanted to enforce a minimum password length, because what good is a 1 character password (or 0 for that matter) ?!?!</p>




<p>The first thing I did was add this to the <code>User</code> model:</p>




<pre><code>validates :password, length: { minimum: 8 }
</code></pre>




<p>This works for new users, but not for those with a <code>password_digest</code> already. Attempting to updated an existing user produces the following error:</p>




<pre><code>ActiveRecord::RecordInvalid: Validation failed: Password is too short (minimum is 8 characters)
</code></pre>




<p>The next step was to conditionalize only on create:</p>




<pre><code>validates :password, length: { minimum: 8 }, on: :create
</code></pre>




<p>Except, that wasn’t right either because I’d definitely want to allow users to update their password, in which case, the length validation wouldn’t be enforced.</p>




<p>I found another <a href="http://quickleft.com/blog/rails-tip-validating-users-with-has_secure_password">post suggesting to allow <code>nil</code></a> using:</p>




<pre><code>validates :password, length: { minimum: 8 }, allow_nil: true
</code></pre>




<p>But, again, that felt weird and doesn’t read particularly well when you’re looking through the source trying to understand what condition would generate a <code>nil</code> password.</p>




<p>Other solutions included <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/6486345/2261909">mixing conditionals and checking model dirty state</a> and <a href="http://urgetopunt.com/rails/2012/11/12/validate-password-presence-has-secure-password.html">some combination of all of the above</a>.</p>




<p>I’m guessing some combination of the above would’ve worked, but something didn’t feel quite right. A quick glance over any of those solutions left me wanting something cleaner and more approachable. Because it’s a complex and tremendously important part of the app, I wanted to feel comfortable with the solution.</p>




<h2>The Solution</h2>




<p>I recently read <a href="https://leanpub.com/growing-rails"><em>Growing Rails Application in Practice</em></a>. The most interesting takeaway for me was the idea of sub-classing an Active Record object to exactly the problem described above.</p>




<p>Consider this…we have our <code>User</code> model with <code>has_secure_password</code>:</p>




<pre><code>class User &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
  has_secure_password
end
</code></pre>




<p>As we saw above, the variety of validation contexts made the standard ActiveModel validation awkward. What if we sub-class <code>User</code> and add the validation contexts for a specific use case? In our case, minimum length:</p>




<pre><code>class User::AsSignUp &lt; User
  validates :password, length: { minimum: 8 }
end
</code></pre>




<p>In this case, we’re create a separate model, for the purpose of signing up, and perhaps other user-related attribute management (profile, password reset, etc.).</p>




<p>Now, instead of passing the <code>User</code> model to the view from the controller, we pass an instantiated version of the new context-specific model class:</p>




<pre><code>def create
  @user = User::AsSignUp.find(current_user.id)
  …
end
</code></pre>




<p>Lastly, because the sub-class name is inferred within the form, we have to do one more thing to make the params are accessible on the <code>create</code> action using <code>params[:user]</code>. We’ll change the form from:</p>




<pre><code>&lt;%= form_for @user, url: user_confirm_path(@user.invitation_token) do |f| %&gt;
</code></pre>




<p>to:</p>




<pre><code>&lt;%= form_for @user, as: :user, url: user_confirm_path(@user.invitation_token) do |f| %&gt;
</code></pre>




<p>Because the remainder of the app operates fine without any need for the password validation, the <code>User</code> can be used where necessary and without worry of it becoming invalid because the password accessor isn’t present.</p>




<h2>Summary</h2>




<p>While sub-classing models in Rails is generally frowned upon, this use case is one of the few that felt reasonable. It feels relatively low cost and stays in isolation. I’d love to hear how you might have solved this problem. I looked and explored a handful of solutions. While others worked, none seems as expressive as the one above.</p>


<p>A form object using
<a href="http://api.rubyonrails.org/classes/ActiveModel/Model.html">ActiveModel</a> or
similar could&rsquo;ve been an alternative option. I didn&rsquo;t explore it for this
particular use case, mostly because I wanted to give this one a shot. However,
I have no doubt it would&rsquo;ve at least worked equally as well.</p>

<p>I should also point out that I&rsquo;m familiar with the built-in <a href="https://github.com/rails/rails/blob/master/activemodel/lib/active_model/validations.rb#L73">validation
contexts in ActiveModel</a>.
And for whatever reason, I&rsquo;ve not used them before. I&rsquo;ll probably give it a
shot on another occasion for comparison.</p>

<p>What are your thoughts on this technique?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
