<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: rails | Brandon Hilkert]]></title>
  <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/categories/rails/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-02T09:40:50-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brandon Hilkert]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[brandonhilkert@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rails Gemfile Teardown - 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/rails-gemfile-teardown-2014/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-03T13:14:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/rails-gemfile-teardown-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What’s the first thing you look at when you see the source code of a Rails project?</p>

<p>For me, it’s the <code>Gemfile</code>. Think about it&hellip;there&rsquo;s very few other files that contain so much information. It describes the building blocks of the application. And at times, you can even see specific features of the application.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>A <code>Gemfile</code> also includes hints about preference and style. And style is something most Ruby developers are very passionate about. It doesn’t take long to find the story of a Rubyist describing their “love at first sight” experience with the language. It’s hard to find another file in a Rails project that’s so telling.</p>

<p>A year ago, I wrote about the <a href="/blog/patterns-in-a-rails-gemfile/">Ruby gems I regularly use in my Rails applications</a>. Because technology and the tools we use change so fast, I thought it’d be interesting to take a look at one of my more recent Gemfiles to see what’s changed.</p>

<h2>Rails Templates</h2>

<p>As I mentioned in the last <a href="/blog/patterns-in-a-rails-gemfile/">Gemfile post</a>, I tend to write a bunch of small applications sprinkled around some larger ones. Despite the size of the project, I feel like I’ve honed in a set of Ruby gems that feel comfortable and productive for me and my workflow.</p>

<p>Knowing the act of bootstrapping a Rails project is sometimes tedious, I took some time to build a <a href="https://github.com/brandonhilkert/rails_templates">Rails template</a> around the gems and patterns I commonly use. I’ll definitely be writing about this experience in the future since there seems to be very little discussion about it.</p>

<p>In short, extracting my preferences to a template has been a HUGE time saver. It no longer feels like a burden to run <code>rails new</code>. I can jump right in and have a consistent set of tools that enable me to be productive within a few minutes.</p>

<h2>My 2014 Gemfile</h2>

<p>The <code>Gemfile</code> below is one of the larger projects I worked on this year. I thought it’d give a good sense of some of my more practical everyday preferences, along with some feature-specific choices for this particular application.</p>

<p>```
source &lsquo;<a href="https://rubygems.org">https://rubygems.org</a>&rsquo;</p>

<p>ruby &lsquo;2.1.4&rsquo;</p>

<p>gem &lsquo;rails&rsquo;, &lsquo;4.1.8&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;pg&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;sass-rails&rsquo;, &lsquo;~> 4.0.3&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;uglifier&rsquo;, &lsquo;>= 1.3.0&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;coffee-rails&rsquo;, &lsquo;~> 4.0.0&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;jquery-rails&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;turbolinks&rsquo;</p>

<p>gem &lsquo;bcrypt-ruby&rsquo;, &lsquo;~> 3.1.2&rsquo;</p>

<p>group :development, :test do
  gem &lsquo;pry&rsquo;
end</p>

<p>group :test do
  gem &lsquo;selenium-webdriver&rsquo;
  gem &lsquo;capybara&rsquo;
  gem &lsquo;timecop&rsquo;
  gem &lsquo;mocha&rsquo;
end</p>

<p>group :development do
  gem &lsquo;quiet_assets&rsquo;
  gem &lsquo;spring&rsquo;
  gem &lsquo;bullet&rsquo;
  gem &lsquo;stripe_tester&rsquo;, &lsquo;~> 0.1.0&rsquo;
end</p>

<p>group :production, :demo do
  gem &lsquo;rails_12factor&rsquo;
  gem &lsquo;heroku-deflater&rsquo;
end</p>

<p>gem &lsquo;font-awesome-rails&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;unicorn&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;bootstrap-sass&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;sidekiq&rsquo;, require: &lsquo;sidekiq/web&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;sinatra&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;local_time&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;gravatar_image_tag&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;so_meta&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;chronic&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;recurrence&rsquo;</p>

<p>gem &lsquo;premailer-rails&rsquo;</p>

<p>gem &lsquo;momentjs-rails&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;bootstrap3-datetimepicker-rails&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;bootstrap-switch-rails&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;bootstrap-wysihtml5-rails&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;bootstrap-select-rails&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;autosize-rails&rsquo;</p>

<p>gem &lsquo;aws-sdk&rsquo;</p>

<p>gem &lsquo;html-pipeline&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;rinku&rsquo;</p>

<p>gem &lsquo;newrelic_rpm&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;doc_raptor&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;stripe&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;jquery-ui-rails&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;active_model_serializers&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;rubyzip&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;render_anywhere&rsquo;, require: false
gem &lsquo;pusher&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;filepicker-rails&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;memcachier&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;dalli&rsquo;
gem &lsquo;intercom-rails&rsquo;
```</p>

<p>A few comments:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>I’ve standardized on <a href="http://www.postgresql.org/">Postgres</a> as the database for my apps, even in development. It’s reliable and allows me to be sure that the code I write will work the same way in production, since I tend to deploy most of my apps to <a href="https://www.heroku.com/">Heroku</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>I leave <code>turbolinks</code> on. Judging from recent posts and comments within the community, this will probably one of the more controversial decisions.</p>

<p>  If I’m being honest, my first experience with Turbolinks wasn’t great. And by “wasn’t great”, I mean — it broke <strong>EVERYTHING</strong>! But the good news was that it brought to light the fact that I sucked at javascript. At the time, I was capable of writing <em>just</em> enough to modify form behavior or fade in an DOM element.</p>

<p>  The time had come to level up on my javascript skills. I was able to improve my javascript and also do it in a way that can took full advantage of the benefits that Turbolinks offers. Since that time, I’ve left Turbolinks on and no longer had to worry that my client-side code will stop working after clicking through a few application links.</p></li>
<li><p>I’ve standardized on using <code>has_secure_password</code> for authentication. I previously used <a href="https://github.com/plataformatec/devise">devise</a>, but found the extra features are no longer worth the additional complexity. <code>has_secure_password</code> provides me reliable authentication patterns that are simple to understand and maintain. Hence the need for <code>bcrypt</code> in the <code>Gemfile</code> above.</p></li>
<li><p>As for my test environment, I’ve written about <a href="/blog/7-reasons-why-im-sticking-with-minitest-and-fixtures-in-rails/">my switch to Minitest and fixtures</a>. I’m still just as happy with that decision as the time I wrote about it. I’ve seen Rspec go through a variety of API changes since then, and thankful I no longer have to worry about updating my test suite every couple months. I continue to find value in <code>capybara</code> and include <code>mocha</code> for the times <code>Minitest</code>’s stubbing and mocking isn’t enough (I’ve been meaning to dig in to the places I use <code>mocha</code>. I’m guessing if the code was better, I probably wouldn’t need it at all).</p></li>
<li><p><code>bullet</code> is a killer gem for tracking down performances issues. It’s saved me countless hours of debugging.</p></li>
<li><p>The inclusion of <code>spring</code> in Rails 4.1 is great. I realize it’s a bandaid in some respects, but waiting for the environment to load on every test run is a drag. I’ve found that because my tests are so responsive when <code>spring</code> is working properly, it encourages me to run my tests more often. Once setup, it works well and only in rare cases has not reloaded when it should have.</p></li>
<li><p>I generally always include <code>bootstrap</code> and <code>font-awesome</code> in my projects. Being a non-designer, it helps me get something on the screen faster, even if it’s not the final design.</p></li>
<li><p>I continue to use <code>unicorn</code>. It’s been around for so long and continues to be competitive in benchmarks against other Ruby web servers. I tested Passenger in a few applications, but got scared off when it printed the entire environment to the screen in production on Heroku on an exception. I’m told there are ways around this with some non-trivial configuration, but I think it’s a bizarre default and isn’t conducive to my workflow.</p></li>
<li><p>For the apps that need background processing, <code>sidekiq</code> continues to be my goto when a separate worker is necessary. I generally mount Sidekiq’s web UI to provide insight to the state of the jobs, which is why <code>sinatra</code> is included.</p></li>
<li><p>I’ve written about putting together <a href="/blog/relative-timestamps-in-rails/">a gem to render relative timestamps</a> on the client side. While I’d love to sit here and tell you I use it, I don’t. Basecamp’s <a href="https://github.com/basecamp/local_time">local_time</a> gem is exceptional for that need and I’m pretty sure we can count on it being updated and maintained well going forward (one of the biggest changes in my mindset for including a new gem).</p></li>
<li><p>This particular app has some pretty hairy time calculations and scheduling. It’s not something I was very experienced with prior, but found value in the combination of <code>chronic</code> and <code>recurrence</code>. Both make the process of targeting a specific <code>datetime</code> and scheduling something in the future relatively simple.</p></li>
<li><p>I included a number of bootstrap related javascript gems (<code>bootstrap3-datetimepicker-rails</code>, <code>bootstrap-switch-rails</code>, <code>bootstrap-switch-rails</code>, <code>bootstrap-select-rails</code>). All are little more than a <a href="/blog/how-to-build-a-rails-engine/">Rails engine</a> that exposes the appropriate javascript and stylesheets to the asset pipeline. These are particularly dependent on the project. I’d normally not start by including anything like this. Side note &ndash; I could’ve copied the relevant assets to <code>vendor/assets</code> rather than requiring a gem that does the same. In a few cases, some added view helpers as well.</p></li>
<li><p>I’ve standardized on using New Relic to collect application metrics and exceptions.</p></li>
<li><p>It shouldn’t be a surprise that <code>stripe</code> is the payment processor I reach for when I’m in control. It’s super developer-friendly and, at this point, I’ve done enough that integration is not much more than a copy/paste from other apps. I recently started using <code>stripe_tester</code> in the test environment. It’s been great for stubbing out calls to Stripe so the test suite continues to be performant. It also allows me to setup some unique edge-case data coming from Stripe so I can protect users from ending up in a crappy state.</p></li>
<li><p>I generally reach for <code>active_model_serializers</code> anytime I need a <code>json</code> response that contains more than a simple hash (in which case I’d continue to render it in the controller response). I’ve used the view equivalent solutions a few times (<code>jbuilder</code>, etc.) and they worked ok too, but for whatever reason, <code>active_model_serializers</code> does it for me.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>The rest are very use case-specific. And in general, the defacto solution for each (<code>pusher</code> for real-time features, <code>dalli</code> for memcached, etc.).</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>I’m happy with my current toolkit. This doesn’t mean I’m not on the lookout for shiny new things, but I’m generally a little more cautious about replacing something reliable, even if it doesn’t do everything under the sun.</p>

<p>Even though Ruby makes it easy to include third party libraries, it doesn’t mean we always should. As developers, we inherit the stability of the dependencies we include. Even though a gem’s code might be locked away behind a separate git repository, it likely has the same holes and complexities that we’re worried about in our applications. And perhaps, even more…</p>

<p><a href="https://www.ruby-toolbox.com/">Ruby toolbox</a> is a great resource when searching for a gem. I generally consider the number of downloads, age of the project and development activity when deciding which one to go with.</p>

<p>What have your favorite gems been this year?</p>

<h2>Build a Ruby Gem</h2>

<p>Ruby gems are the building blocks of Ruby/Rails applications. If you haven’t built one yourself, there’s no better time to start. Github makes it extremely to contribute to existing gems and sometimes that’s <a href="/blog/3-ways-to-get-started-contributing-to-open-source/">the easiest way to get started contributing to open source</a>. My book, <em>Build a Ruby Gem</em>, includes <a href="/books/build-a-ruby-gem/">everything you to need to get started building a Ruby gem</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creating Rails Active Record Validation Contexts with Inheritance]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/creating-rails-active-record-validation-contexts-with-inheritance/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-18T17:20:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/creating-rails-active-record-validation-contexts-with-inheritance</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you’ve used <code>validates</code> in a Rails Active Record model, you know they work great -- at least until the first bit of complexity arises. At that point, they can quickly morph in to a ball of conditional spaghetti convoluting the initial reason the validation was added in the first place.</p>




<p>I recently had an experience using <code>has_secure_password</code> where I wanted control the length of the user-supplied password. Adding a length validation to the password accessor invalidated existing records, so I was in a bit of a bind. In the end, I sub-classed the Active Record model to create a unique model made specifically for that context. This allowed me to inherit the core functionality from the model and sprinkle on existing validations for specific use cases. This was a new tactic for me and I’m still now sure how I feel about it. I like the fact that it removed complexity from the <code>User</code> model. This, in hopes, will keep the minimize the likelihood of it becoming a God object.</p>




<!--more-->




<h2>The Problem</h2>




<p>Using <code>has_secure_password</code> is a relatively easy way to add authentication to a Rails app. In order to disguise the plain text passwords, an <a href="https://github.com/rails/rails/blob/3bdf7b80a11dcb67b18553ff1fe0da82b0cffc20/activemodel/lib/active_model/secure_password.rb#L106">accessor for the plain <code>password</code></a> is added that encrypts it before saving.</p>




<p>The only true Active Record validation <code>has_secure_password</code> adds is a <a href="https://github.com/rails/rails/blob/3bdf7b80a11dcb67b18553ff1fe0da82b0cffc20/activemodel/lib/active_model/secure_password.rb#L68">confirmation of the password</a> — and only when the password is present. This allows us to create a user object without supplying a password, or maybe saving straight to the <code>password_digest</code> field, which is used to store the encrypted password in the database.</p>




<p>I wanted to enforce a minimum password length, because what good is a 1 character password (or 0 for that matter) ?!?!</p>




<p>The first thing I did was add this to the <code>User</code> model:</p>




<pre><code>validates :password, length: { minimum: 8 }
</code></pre>




<p>This works for new users, but not for those with a <code>password_digest</code> already. Attempting to updated an existing user produces the following error:</p>




<pre><code>ActiveRecord::RecordInvalid: Validation failed: Password is too short (minimum is 8 characters)
</code></pre>




<p>The next step was to conditionalize only on create:</p>




<pre><code>validates :password, length: { minimum: 8 }, on: :create
</code></pre>




<p>Except, that wasn’t right either because I’d definitely want to allow users to update their password, in which case, the length validation wouldn’t be enforced.</p>




<p>I found another <a href="http://quickleft.com/blog/rails-tip-validating-users-with-has_secure_password">post suggesting to allow <code>nil</code></a> using:</p>




<pre><code>validates :password, length: { minimum: 8 }, allow_nil: true
</code></pre>




<p>But, again, that felt weird and doesn’t read particularly well when you’re looking through the source trying to understand what condition would generate a <code>nil</code> password.</p>




<p>Other solutions included <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/6486345/2261909">mixing conditionals and checking model dirty state</a> and <a href="http://urgetopunt.com/rails/2012/11/12/validate-password-presence-has-secure-password.html">some combination of all of the above</a>.</p>




<p>I’m guessing some combination of the above would’ve worked, but something didn’t feel quite right. A quick glance over any of those solutions left me wanting something cleaner and more approachable. Because it’s a complex and tremendously important part of the app, I wanted to feel comfortable with the solution.</p>




<h2>The Solution</h2>




<p>I recently read <a href="https://leanpub.com/growing-rails"><em>Growing Rails Application in Practice</em></a>. The most interesting takeaway for me was the idea of sub-classing an Active Record object to exactly the problem described above.</p>




<p>Consider this…we have our <code>User</code> model with <code>has_secure_password</code>:</p>




<pre><code>class User &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
  has_secure_password
end
</code></pre>




<p>As we saw above, the variety of validation contexts made the standard ActiveModel validation awkward. What if we sub-class <code>User</code> and add the validation contexts for a specific use case? In our case, minimum length:</p>




<pre><code>class User::AsSignUp &lt; User
  validates :password, length: { minimum: 8 }
end
</code></pre>




<p>In this case, we’re create a separate model, for the purpose of signing up, and perhaps other user-related attribute management (profile, password reset, etc.).</p>




<p>Now, instead of passing the <code>User</code> model to the view from the controller, we pass an instantiated version of the new context-specific model class:</p>




<pre><code>def create
  @user = User::AsSignUp.find(current_user.id)
  …
end
</code></pre>




<p>Lastly, because the sub-class name is inferred within the form, we have to do one more thing to make the params are accessible on the <code>create</code> action using <code>params[:user]</code>. We’ll change the form from:</p>




<pre><code>&lt;%= form_for @user, url: user_confirm_path(@user.invitation_token) do |f| %&gt;
</code></pre>




<p>to:</p>




<pre><code>&lt;%= form_for @user, as: :user, url: user_confirm_path(@user.invitation_token) do |f| %&gt;
</code></pre>




<p>Because the remainder of the app operates fine without any need for the password validation, the <code>User</code> can be used where necessary and without worry of it becoming invalid because the password accessor isn’t present.</p>




<h2>Summary</h2>




<p>While sub-classing models in Rails is generally frowned upon, this use case is one of the few that felt reasonable. It feels relatively low cost and stays in isolation. I’d love to hear how you might have solved this problem. I looked and explored a handful of solutions. While others worked, none seems as expressive as the one above.</p>


<p>A form object using
<a href="http://api.rubyonrails.org/classes/ActiveModel/Model.html">ActiveModel</a> or
similar could&rsquo;ve been an alternative option. I didn&rsquo;t explore it for this
particular use case, mostly because I wanted to give this one a shot. However,
I have no doubt it would&rsquo;ve at least worked equally as well.</p>

<p>I should also point out that I&rsquo;m familiar with the built-in <a href="https://github.com/rails/rails/blob/master/activemodel/lib/active_model/validations.rb#L73">validation
contexts in ActiveModel</a>.
And for whatever reason, I&rsquo;ve not used them before. I&rsquo;ll probably give it a
shot on another occasion for comparison.</p>

<p>What are your thoughts on this technique?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Refactoring Logic from a Rails View]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/refactoring-logic-from-a-rails-view/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-30T06:03:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/refactoring-logic-from-a-rails-view</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s generally known that leaving any kind of logic in a Rails view is bad news, both for debugging and your own sanity. Rails views can be cumbersome to test and leave a lot to be desired when it comes to debugging.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I recently went through the process of refactoring a Rails view that included logic. The end result was an isolated <a href="http://blog.jayfields.com/2007/10/ruby-poro.html">PORO</a> that was easily integrated with the controller/view.</p>

<h2>Background</h2>

<p>The app I’m currently working on is a greenfield app with vague specs, at best. I don’t mention this to fault anyone, but more to illustrate a point. Not all greenfield projects have well-defined specs.</p>

<p>In this particular case, the stakeholders were somewhat unsure of what the interface should look like. Together, we tossed around a number of ideas, ultimately leading to a few options. Only once an iteration of the UI was available, would we have a clear picture of whether it <em>felt right</em>.</p>

<h2>The Problem</h2>

<p>I implemented the first option in the most crude way I could think of. Unfortunately, that way involved putting logic in the view. I know, I know — I can hear it now, <em>”C’mon Brandon, everyone knows you shouldn’t do this!”</em>. Here’s the thing — I knew it too.</p>

<p>Here’s what I ended up with:</p>

<p>```</p>

<h1>controller</h1>

<p>def people
  @week_of = params[:week_of] || Checkin::Week.recent(current_company).first.beginning
  @people = current_user.reports
end</p>

<h1>view</h1>

<p>&lt;% @people.each do |person| %>
  &lt;% checkin = person.checkin_for(@week_of) %>
  <tr></p>

<pre><code>&lt;td&gt;
  &lt;%= profile_picture person %&gt;
  &lt;%= person %&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;

&lt;td&gt;
  &lt;%= checkin_status(checkin) %&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>  </tr>
&lt;% end %>
```</p>

<p>For each iteration of <code>@people</code>, I looked up the check-in for that particular week from the model:</p>

<p><code>
def checkin_for(week_of)
  Checkin.find_by(user_id: id, week_of: week_of)
end
</code></p>

<p>This crosses concerns, blurs responsibility — all the things that bad Rails app are made of. But I was doing this knowing it would either be entirely ripped out (we’d change the UI altogether), or refactored to something better.</p>

<p><em>Note: I could’ve just saved myself one step and never made the method in the model. For some reason, that made me feel better about it at the time. *shrugs*</em></p>

<p>So I added a Github issue and went on my way…</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/view-refactor/gh-issue.png" title="&ldquo;Github issue to refactor Rails view&rdquo;" ></p>

<h2>The Solution</h2>

<p>With a few minor tweaks, this implementation of the functionality and UI was adequate. So as time allowed, I jumped back in to untangling the mess I created.</p>

<p>The biggest variable in the display of a <code>Checkin</code> was the week (a date field corresponding to the beginning of that particular week). Once the date was known, I could look for a <code>Checkin</code> for each user in my visibility, see if it existed, and if not, return a stand-in object to represent a non-completed check-in.</p>

<p>I removed the model method:</p>

<p><code>
def checkin_for(week_of)
  Checkin.find_by(user_id: id, week_of: week_of)
end
</code></p>

<p>and the line in the view largely responsible for the mess:</p>

<p><code>
&lt;% checkin = person.checkin_for(@week_of) %&gt;
</code></p>

<p>I went back to the controller and initialized a new object that would allow me to iterate over a list of check-ins:</p>

<p><code>
def people
  @week_of = params[:week_of] || Checkin::Week.recent(current_company).first.beginning
  @reports = Checkin::Reports.new(current_user, @week_of)
end
</code></p>

<p>Let’s dig in to the new <code>Checkin::Reports</code> class…</p>

<p>```
class Checkin
  class Reports</p>

<pre><code>def initialize(user, week_of)
  @user, @week_of = user, week_of
end

def checkins
  reports.map { |person|
    Checkin.find_or_initialize_by(user_id: person.id, week_of: week_of)
  }
end

private

attr_reader :user, :week_of

def reports
  user.reports
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>I instantiate with the user and week, similar to what the <code>checkin_for</code> model method did above.</p>

<p>The only relatively interesting part of this class is that it’s using <code>find_or_intialize_by</code>. It turns out that the view didn’t care if the object was <code>nil</code>, or just a non-persisted <code>Checkin</code> object. All it did was interrogate certain attributes of the object, and guard against the argument being <code>nil</code>. From that perspective, we’ve improved our code even more because now instead of supplying nil to the helper, we are actually supplying it with a newly instantiated <code>Checkin</code> with some default attributes.</p>

<p>This means that our <code>checkin_status</code> helper, went from:</p>

<p>```
def checkin_status(checkin)
  if checkin &amp;&amp; checkin.completed_at?</p>

<pre><code>fa_icon("check-square-o", class: "green") + " Submitted #{local_time checkin.completed_at, format: :short_month_day }".html_safe
</code></pre>

<p>  else</p>

<pre><code>fa_icon("warning", class: "yellow") + " Not completed"
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>to:</p>

<p>```
def checkin_status(checkin)
  if checkin.completed_at?</p>

<pre><code>fa_icon("check-square-o", class: "green") + " Submitted #{local_time checkin.completed_at, format: :short_month_day }".html_safe
</code></pre>

<p>  else</p>

<pre><code>fa_icon("warning", class: "yellow") + " Not completed"
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>It’s a subtle change (removing the check <code>if checkin</code> from the first conditional), but one that’s less susceptible to bizarre edge cases. And clearer — It’s reasonable to expect that by calling the first argument <code>checkin</code>, <strong>the variable should be a <code>Checkin</code></strong>, and not sometimes <code>nil</code>.</p>

<p>Returning back to the view…using the new <code>@reports</code> variable, we no longer have to query during each iteration:</p>

<p>```
&lt;% @reports.checkins.each do |checkin| %>
  <tr></p>

<pre><code>&lt;td&gt;
  &lt;%= profile_picture checkin.user %&gt;
  &lt;%= checkin.user %&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;

&lt;td&gt;
  &lt;%= checkin_status(checkin) %&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>  </tr>
&lt;% end %>
```</p>

<p>Tests pass, and we’re in a much better place than we were before.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>I’ve seen a lot of people make notes for themselves to improve areas of their application and either never get the opportunity to go back and do so, or get so far removed from the mess, they forget about how bad it was in the first place. The approach I took above by making a note for myself worked because <strong>I knew</strong> I would go back to it. It’s possible this may not work for everyone.</p>

<p>If it takes more than just making a Github issue for your and your team, find what works. The important part is that the refactor takes place, in whatever way convenient for you.</p>

<p>The idea of not putting logic in a Rails view is well regarded as a best practice. Don’t think that just because I did it above, I’m advocating that it’s ok. To me, it’s only acceptable if you go back at a later time (soonish…) and clean it up.</p>

<p>Leaving little bits of bad practice sprinkled all of your app is heading of for a bad time. As <a href="http://sandimetz.com/">Sandi Metz</a> says, <a href="http://www.confreaks.com/presenters/211-sandi-metz">“go ahead, make a mess”</a>. Just be sure to come back and clean it up.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Minitest Helper Includes and Rails Fixtures]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/managing-login-passwords-for-capybara-with-minitest-and-rails-fixtures/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-25T06:10:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/managing-login-passwords-for-capybara-with-minitest-and-rails-fixtures</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Contuining my <a href="/blog/7-reasons-why-im-sticking-with-minitest-and-fixtures-in-rails/">love affair with Minitest and fixtures</a>, I wanted to dive in to something deeper this time. Switching tools takes time to get used to and managing passwords was one of the bigger headaches I encountered.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>The Problem</h2>

<p>I wanted to use <a href="https://github.com/jnicklas/capybara">Capybara</a> for integration testing. The application uses the standard email/password combo to authenticate users via <a href="http://api.rubyonrails.org/classes/ActiveModel/SecurePassword/ClassMethods.html#method-i-has_secure_password"><code>has_secure_password</code></a>.</p>

<p>Because plain text passwords are not stored in the database, but rather a <a href="https://github.com/rails/rails/blob/3bdf7b80a11dcb67b18553ff1fe0da82b0cffc20/activemodel/lib/active_model/secure_password.rb#L112"><code>password_digest</code></a>, I didn’t have a good way to fill in the login forms using Capybara to test against pages that require authentication.</p>

<h2>The Solution</h2>

<p>I started with a simple <code>users.yml</code> fixture that looked like this:</p>

<p><code>
fred:
  first_name: Fred
  last_name: Flintstone
  email: fred@flintstone.com
  title: CEO
  company: flintstone
  admin: true
</code></p>

<h3>Bcrypt</h3>

<p>As mentioned above, <code>has_secure_password</code> uses <code>Bcrypt</code> to encrypt the plain text passwords provided. The specific implementation to create the password digest is:</p>

<p><code>
BCrypt::Password.create("password", cost: 4)
</code></p>

<p>This method takes the plain text password (“password”) and encrypts it with what it calls the “cost”. It’s not terribly important for this article, but to save some speed, I’ve specified a cost of 4 — <a href="https://github.com/codahale/bcrypt-ruby/blob/master/lib/bcrypt/engine.rb#L7">the minimum cost support by the <code>Bcrypt</code> algorithm</a>. The default is 10, which will make your production applications safer. However, for testing, we don’t care.</p>

<p>The result of the method above looks like this:</p>

<p><code>
irb(main):001:0&gt; require "bcrypt"
=&gt; true
irb(main):002:0&gt; BCrypt::Password.create("password", cost: 4)
=&gt; "$2a$04$gw09FM67MDnzduXmlK46BOsdVTtzWKaSIkAdmnF/sJSLgcQhJBAUe"
</code></p>

<p>That output value is what’s being stored in our database when a user inputs and saves a password. From the application’s standpoint, we could print a value like this in to our fixtures, but what’s the fun in that?!?!</p>

<h3>ERB in Fixtures</h3>

<p>Since fixtures allow us to use ERB in them, we could provide the <code>Bcrypt</code> method above to produce the password digest like so:</p>

<p><code>
fred:
  first_name: Fred
  last_name: Flintstone
  email: fred@flintstone.com
  password_digest: &lt;%= BCrypt::Password.create("password", cost: 4) %&gt;
  title: CEO
  company: flintstone
  admin: true
</code></p>

<p>The downside is that the actual password (“password”) is here in plain text. To fill in our login form using Capybara, we don’t have a variable to access to the get the password — we literally have to type “password”. So this isn’t the most DRY thing in the world. While it would certainly work, I think we can do better…</p>

<h3>Capybara</h3>

<p>Let’s say I have a test that looks like this:</p>

<p><code>
visit signin_path
fill_in "email", with: user.email
fill_in "password", with: "password"
click_on "Sign in"
</code></p>

<h3>Extract a Module</h3>

<p>Our goal was to not sprinkle these plan text passwords all over the place. So let’s extract a module call <code>TestPasswordHelper</code> and put the plain text password in there:</p>

<p>```
require &ldquo;bcrypt&rdquo;</p>

<p>module TestPasswordHelper
  def default_password_digest</p>

<pre><code>BCrypt::Password.create(default_password, cost: 4)
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def default_password</p>

<pre><code>"password"
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>We’ll have our default password accessible via a method named…get this, <code>default_password</code>! The module also contains a method (<code>default_password_digest</code>) that will allow us to send the password digest to the fixture using the Bcrypt algorithm we explored above.</p>

<p>Now that we have a helper module ready all set up, we add the following to our <code>test/test_helper.rb</code> to make these methods accessible in our tests:</p>

<p>```
require &ldquo;support/test_password_helper&rdquo;</p>

<p>class ActiveSupport::TestCase
  include TestPasswordHelper
end
```</p>

<p>With these methods mixed in, we can update our Capybara test to use the <code>default_password</code> method:</p>

<p><code>
visit signin_path
fill_in "email", with: user.email
fill_in "password", with: default_password
click_on "Sign in"
</code></p>

<h3>Helpers in Fixtures</h3>

<p>Unfortunately, those helpers aren’t available in the fixtures.</p>

<p><code>ActiveRecord::FixtureSet</code> is the class that gives our fixtures life. We can use Ruby to include functionality from our test helper, that will give us access to to the <code>default_password_digest</code> method, which reads our <code>default_password</code> so we don’t have to type it out.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://api.rubyonrails.org/classes/ActiveRecord/FixtureSet.html#method-c-context_class">Rails API guide for fixtures</a> states that helper methods should be added to <code>ActiveRecord::FixtureSet.context_class</code>.</p>

<p>So back in our <code>test_helper.rb</code>, we can mix in our test helpers methods like so:</p>

<p><code>
ActiveRecord::FixtureSet.context_class.send :include, TestPasswordHelper
</code></p>

<p>Now, back in our <code>users.yml</code> fixture, we can use the new <code>default_password_digest</code> method:</p>

<p><code>
fred:
  first_name: Fred
  last_name: Flintstone
  email: fred@flintstone.com
  password_digest: &lt;%= default_password_digest %&gt;
  title: CEO
  company: flintstone
  admin: true
</code></p>

<p>We can now run our tests and verify the fixtures properly insert the digest using the default password and the Capybara tests reference that same default password.</p>

<p>Now, if in the future we wanted use a different password for some reason, we’d only have one place to change it, and the rest of the system would follow along.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>One of the things I’m constantly reminding myself during this process is whenever I have a problem, to step back and think about ways the Ruby language can help solve it rather than looking for some special sauce or gem to get me through the turmoil. Minitest is just Ruby — as most other gems are. Minitest generally provides enough utility to get us through the bigger use cases, but when it comes to special cases, it’s not there to hold our hand. That’s when we put our big boy pants on and make use of the language we’ve all come to know and love — Ruby!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using Rails 4.1 Secrets for Configuration]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/using-rails-4-dot-1-secrets-for-configuration/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-10T20:03:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/using-rails-4-dot-1-secrets-for-configuration</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I previously wrote about how I handle <a href="/blog/flexible-rails-environment-configuration/">environment configuration in Rails</a>. Along with solutions like the <a href="https://github.com/bkeepers/dotenv">dotenv gem</a>, it relies on entirely on environment variables.</p>

<p>One of the highlighted features of Rails 4.1 was the <a href="http://guides.rubyonrails.org/4_1_release_notes.html#config-secrets-yml"><code>config/secrets.yml</code></a> file. By default, this file contains the <code>secret_key_base</code> and defers to the ENV variable of the same name in the production environment. Even though <code>secret_key_base</code> isn’t typically referenced explicitly in an application, I was curious if I could use the <code>config/secrets.yml</code> file in place of previously documented configuration solution.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>After a little digging, it turns out that it works perfectly. A valid question is whether the variables are better referenced through the <code>Rails.application</code> hash, but that’s probably more a preference and use-case dependent decision. Either way, we’ll explore the solution below.</p>

<h2>The Question</h2>

<p>Below is a default <code>config/secrets.yml</code> file generated from a Rails 4.1 app. As you can see, both the development and test environments rely on statically set values, where the production environment relies on environment variables being set on the system. The latter is perfect for platforms like <a href="https://www.heroku.com">Heroku</a>, and just as easy if you manage your own systems on EC2 or similar infrastructure.</p>

<p>```
development:
  secret_key_base: 9ac2d0ad8ebcc312090e99d745006d3cf8</p>

<p>test:
  secret_key_base: a1580ad61ccb6ac60f9f256948cf63d6e20</p>

<h1>Do not keep production secrets in the repository,</h1>

<h1>instead read values from the environment.</h1>

<p>production:
  secret_key_base: &lt;%= ENV[&ldquo;SECRET_KEY_BASE&rdquo;] %>
```</p>

<p>Notice how ERB is processed in the file. This gives us the opportunity to use Ruby to generate random strings, dates, or anything else that can be expressed through code.</p>

<p>So can we use it for other configuration values in the application?</p>

<h2>The Solution</h2>

<p>In order to figure out where the output of the parsed secrets file was stored, I pulled the latest Rails changes and went code diving.</p>

<p>The first thing I did was search “secrets”. The first group of results were mostly comments related to the processing of <code>secret_key_base</code> and where it could be found. After combing through a few more results, I came across the <code>Rails::Application</code> class.</p>

<p>A static array at the top of the file seemed to hold some values for the application as shown below:</p>

<p>```
INITIAL_VARIABLES = [:config, :railties, :routes_reloader, :reloaders,</p>

<pre><code>                    :routes, :helpers, :app_env_config, :secrets] # :nodoc:
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Looks like we’re on the right track. Going further down the file leads us to the getter:</p>

<p>```
def secrets #:nodoc:
  @secrets ||= begin</p>

<pre><code>secrets = ActiveSupport::OrderedOptions.new
yaml = config.paths["config/secrets"].first

if File.exist?(yaml)
  require "erb"
  all_secrets = YAML.load(ERB.new(IO.read(yaml)).result) || {}
  env_secrets = all_secrets[Rails.env]
  secrets.merge!(env_secrets.symbolize_keys) if env_secrets
end

# Fallback to config.secret_key_base if secrets.secret_key_base isn't set
secrets.secret_key_base ||= config.secret_key_base

secrets
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>As you can see, the file path <code>config/secrets</code> is referenced as the <code>yaml</code> source:</p>

<p><code>
yaml = config.paths["config/secrets"].first
</code></p>

<p>and the result of reading the file is sent through ERB and YAML:</p>

<p><code>
all_secrets = YAML.load(ERB.new(IO.read(yaml)).result) || {}
</code></p>

<p>The environment group is parsed:</p>

<p><code>
env_secrets = all_secrets[Rails.env]
</code></p>

<p>The result of the output is returned, leaving us with a hash of options based on the environment group. With a little luck we should be able to query the application from the console and get the configuration values.</p>

<p><code>
irb(main):001:0&gt; Rails.application.secrets.class
=&gt; ActiveSupport::OrderedOptions
irb(main):002:0&gt; Rails.application.secrets
=&gt; {:secret_key_base=&gt;"9ac2d0ad8ebcc312090e99d745006d3cf8"}
irb(main):003:0&gt; Rails.application.secrets.secret_key_base
=&gt; "a1580ad61ccb6ac60f9f256948cf63d6e20"
</code></p>

<p>That’s great news because it means we can put other values in this file and reference them throughout our application using the parent hash <code>Rails.application.secrets</code>.</p>

<p>For example, let’s assume we need to configuration Pusher URL again. We could add it to the <code>secrets.yml</code> file like so:</p>

<p>```
development:
  secret_key_base: 9ac2d0ad8ebcc312090e99d745006d3cf8
  pusher_url: <a href="http://asdfa@api.pusherapp.com">http://asdfa@api.pusherapp.com</a></p>

<p>test:
  secret_key_base: a1580ad61ccb6ac60f9f256948cf63d6e20</p>

<h1>Do not keep production secrets in the repository,</h1>

<h1>instead read values from the environment.</h1>

<p>production:
  secret_key_base: &lt;%= ENV[&ldquo;SECRET_KEY_BASE&rdquo;] %>
  pusher_url: &lt;%= ENV[&ldquo;PUSHER_URL&rdquo;] %>
```</p>

<p>Now within our application we can set the Pusher URL within the initializer using the secret value:</p>

<p>```</p>

<h1>config/initializers/pusher.rb</h1>

<p>Pusher.url = Rails.application.secrets.pusher_url
```</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>I feel like my previous solution has the potential to be replaced with the secrets file. I plan to try it out in an upcoming application and see if it’s as easy to manage as it seems.</p>

<p>Note that by default, the <code>secrets.yml</code> file is NOT ignored by git. If you plan to include passwords or other sensitive data in the file, be sure to add it to your <code>.gitignore</code>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
