<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ironman | Brandon Hilkert]]></title>
  <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/categories/ironman/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-12-03T16:29:05-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brandon Hilkert]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[brandonhilkert@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Be Ambitious]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/be-ambitious/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-31T13:04:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/be-ambitious</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>2013</h2>

<p>On Dec. 31, 2012, I sat around a dinner table with my wife and 4 of our
friends.  Discussing the upcoming New Year, we went around the table and shared
our resolutions. My turn came and I said, &ldquo;<em>I&rsquo;m going to finish an
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ironman_Triathlon">Ironman</a></em>&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Up until that point, my longest race of any kind was a half marathon &ndash;
certainly no triathlons. So for me, this was biiiiiiig time. I honestly don&rsquo;t
know if anyone believed what I said that night. I&rsquo;m not even sure I did. But
nonetheless, I had said it out loud in the presence of friends. The same
friends I&rsquo;d later have to explain why I bailed &ndash; <em>if I bailed</em>.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>But I didn&rsquo;t bail. On Sept. 21, I finished the
<a href="http://www.tricolumbia.org/events/?eid=5">ChesapeakeMan</a> in 12 hours and 54
minutes. I spent 3 hours/day, 6 days/week for the prior 30 weeks preparing for
that day. It was easily the longest 30 weeks of my life.</p>

<h2>Accountability</h2>

<p>During the training, there were a few times I seriously considered quitting. In
every one of those moments, I thought back to the scene around that dinner
table on New Year&rsquo;s Eve. I had confidently told 5 other people I was going to
finish an Ironman and I didn&rsquo;t want to have to explain that I quit.</p>

<p>This is accountability&hellip;had I not mentioned by goal that night, the only
person I would&rsquo;ve let down is myself &ndash; that&rsquo;s easy to stomach. But knowing
others had expectations made it close to impossible for me to quit.</p>

<h2>2014</h2>

<p>With an Ironman crossed off my list, here we are, one year later. And rather
than rely on another dinner party resolution sharing session, I&rsquo;m documenting my resolution
here. So here goes&hellip;</p>

<h2>This year I&rsquo;m going to write to <a href="/books/build-a-ruby-gem/">write a book</a>.</h2>

<p>I never would&rsquo;ve thought a book would be in my future, but that&rsquo;s what
resolutions are for, right?!?! I also never would&rsquo;ve guessed I&rsquo;d finish an
Ironman, so why not keep the ball rollin'.</p>

<h2>In Summary</h2>

<p>Do something <strong>ambitious</strong> this year. Don&rsquo;t be the person that plan to lose 20
lbs. and quits going to the gym a week in to it. After my experience this year,
I believe <strong>everyone</strong> is capable of far more than they think.</p>

<p>This could be the year you take that next big step. Whether it&rsquo;s learning a new
language, launching a new product, or finding your dream job. <strong>Tell someone
about it</strong>. I promise you&rsquo;ll second guess quitting.</p>

<p><em>Leave a comment with your ambitious goals for 2014.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Loyalty]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/loyalty/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-30T08:34:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/loyalty</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last weekend, I finished an
<a href="http://www.tricolumbia.org/events/?eid=5">Ironman</a>.
The training consumed valuable time with both family and friends that I&rsquo;ll
never get back. However, the support and love that I received on the days
surrounding the race have given me an increased appreciation for the people
that are in my life and the unwavering support they offer.</p>

<p>Finishing the race was an incredible experience. The day of the race had its
share of extreme ups and downs, both of which I&rsquo;ve come to value now that it&rsquo;s
over. Since I no longer have to worry about waking up at 5 a.m. to get to gym,
I&rsquo;ve spent a fair amount of time replaying the past 30 weeks and the sacrifices
involved.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>The people pictured below were with me at every possible step of the race. They
spent almost 13 hours watching 154 people swim, bike and run 140.6 miles back
and forth through sunburn, darkness, and rain.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/ironman.jpg" title="&ldquo;My family at the Ironman&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>I feel so tremendously lucky to have them in my life and I&rsquo;m pretty sure I
don&rsquo;t always make that apparent. I don&rsquo;t think they have any idea how much
having them there meant to me. The thought of them standing around the next
corner got me those small wins that kept me upright.</p>

<p>To me, the most telling part is that I didn&rsquo;t specifically ask any of them to
come. All of them were there because they wanted to be. And that, meant the
most.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve spent the last week thinking about what I could say or do to show my
appreciation. The best I could come up with is to simply say &ldquo;Thank You&rdquo;.</p>

<p>This is loyalty.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
