<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: saas | Brandon Hilkert]]></title>
  <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/categories/saas/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-18T20:38:31-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brandon Hilkert]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[brandonhilkert@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2014 In Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/2014-in-review/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-29T14:57:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/2014-in-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For the past 2 years, I’ve committed myself to <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/be-ambitious/">specific
goals</a> for the year to come. Most
people call them New Year’s Resolutions. Heck, I probably even referred to them
as “resolutions” too. But the more I thought about it, the more it dawned on me
that a “resolution” felt more like a fix for something — something that didn&rsquo;t
go well in the previous year. Think weight loss (everyone makes this resolution at least once in their life) or a dedication to be more focused.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Mine have been more of the bucket list variety. The first was <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/loyalty/">completing an Ironman</a>. The second, <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/be-ambitious/">writing a book</a>.</p>

<p>Both felt almost too big initially, but ultimately led to opportunities and
lifestyle changes I would’ve never expected once finished. So naturally, with
2014 winding down, the question becomes <strong>&ldquo;what’s the goal for 2015?&rdquo;</strong>.</p>

<p>And the answer is&hellip;<em>I don’t know</em>.</p>

<p>It doesn’t mean I’m not going to do anything. In fact, it probably means the
opposite. I’m just not going to set out with a specific goal in mind. If
halfway through something, I want to stop and do something else, so be it.</p>

<p>I remember during my training for the Ironman (9 months total), I constantly thought about what I would do with my free time when it was over. Every time my alarm went off at 5am, I thought about what it would feel like to get another 2 hours of sleep. It was endless. Nine months was a long time to have those thoughts and, perhaps, why I was so well positioned to write and launch the book (I had 9 months to think about what was next and how to accomplish it).</p>

<p>Always having your sights set on the future can wear on you though.</p>

<p>Without those feelings now, I’m going to let 2015 take me wherever it does. I don’t have any expectations financially or professionally. I’m going to do my best to make the most out of every moment and appreciate more of the small things. It’s so easy to skip over the small things and in many cases, the small things are actually the best things. And we don’t realize it until they’re gone.</p>

<p>2014 was a great year in all. Here are a few of the events that stand out the most:</p>

<ul>
<li>my wife and I <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/about/">welcomed our son, Cruz</a></li>
<li>my wife and I celebrated our 4 year anniversary</li>
<li>wrote a book, <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/books/build-a-ruby-gem/">Build a Ruby Gem</a></li>
<li>provided a <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/courses/build-a-ruby-gem/">free email course on building a Ruby gem</a> to 1,218 people</li>
<li>connected with 2,645 people through my <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/newsletter/">newsletter</a></li>
<li>built a <a href="https://funneloptimizer.herokuapp.com/">funnel optimization service for bloggers selling
  products</a></li>
<li>published 24 <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/archives/">articles</a></li>
<li>saw <a href="https://github.com/brandonhilkert/sucker_punch">Sucker Punch</a> <a href="https://rubygems.org/gems/sucker_punch">downloaded over 225k times</a></li>
<li>celebrated <a href="https://github.com/brandonhilkert/sucker_punch">Sucker Punch</a> being <a href="http://guides.rubyonrails.org/active_job_basics.html">integrated in to Rails</a></li>
<li>made my <a href="https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/16898">first commit to Rails</a> (even if it was small!)</li>
<li>traveled to Jackson Hole, WY</li>
<li>built a <a href="https://vuier.com/">pay-to-view video platform</a> with a few friends</li>
<li>built a <a href="https://perform.io/">performance management system</a></li>
<li>renovated my
  <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/images/2014/bathroom-before.jpg">kids'</a>
  <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/images/2014/bathroom-after.jpg">bathroom</a></li>
<li>built a deployment system for <a href="https://www.pipelinedeals.com/">PipelineDeals</a> and supporting services that I’m very proud of</li>
<li>built a staging server management application</li>
<li>built <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/how-to-win-friends-and-in/cbmeigkjdnilgodhnhagokhoehbpkdcc?hl=en-US">3</a> <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/pipelinedeals-crm-contact/ieaafnaonfabpgpkkeglkeodkpiijjdd?hl=en-US">chrome</a> <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/pipelinedeals-gmail/fdfifknmbmalmgdjmnhkcfholdgacikl?hl=en-US">extensions</a>, the latter being my first <a href="http://facebook.github.io/react/">React</a> app</li>
<li>started a <a href="http://walnutstlabs.com/event/walnut-st-labs-night-owls/">weekly tech gathering</a> at a <a href="http://walnutstlabs.com">local co-working space</a></li>
<li>stopped push email notifications on all my devices (strongly recommended)</li>
<li>saw <a href="http://defriendnotifierapp.com/">Defriend Notifier</a> be used by 30,128 people</li>
<li>started exploring other programming languages, specifically <a href="https://golang.org/">Go</a> and <a href="http://elixir-lang.org/">Elixir</a></li>
</ul>


<p>I’m excited for 2015!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing FunnelOptimizer.io]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/introducing-funneloptimizer-dot-io/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-06T21:21:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/introducing-funneloptimizer-dot-io</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last month marks the 6 month anniversary of the release of <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/books/build-a-ruby-gem/">Build a Ruby Gem</a>. Thinking back to this time last year, I would’ve never guessed that I would launch a product to the tune of $16k+ sales in 6 months. Thanks to the help of expert teachers, I was able to quickly get over my fear of marketing and put my technical knowledge to good use.</p>

<p>The weeks leading up to the launch seem like a blur now. At the time, I had a perfectly crafted schedule of marketing material and approaches that, as far as I can tell, were the difference between no sales and quite a few.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>One of the biggest lessons learned was capturing emails on my <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com">blog posts</a>. Newsletter opt-ins are fantastic way to gather interest and offer subscribers additional incentives like discounts or other non-public postings. I, like many, made use of related blog posts to capture emails with a form like this:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/funnel_optimizer/newsletter-form.png" title="&ldquo;BrandonHilkert.com newsletter form&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>One of the benefits of serving a niche like Ruby programmers is there are quite a few repeat visitors. Around the new year, I was posting twice a month, and then every week leading up to the launch. The posts were naturally related to the content of building a Ruby gem and gave some teasers to what readers could expect in the <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/books/build-a-ruby-gem/">book</a>.</p>

<p>But one of the things that always bummed me out was how previously subscribed readers to my newsletter <strong>STILL saw the same newsletter opt-in form shown above</strong>. <em>Why on Earth would that be helpful to the them???</em></p>

<p>They can’t sign up twice, so why would I show them the form again? It turns out there’s no good answer for this. In general, the quickest way to solve this problem is to purchase a fancy marketing automation system and pay potentially 4 figures a month. There was no room for this with my little budget.</p>

<p>Ideally, what I wanted was to show my first visitor the opt-in form above, and then if they signed up, promote my book. Regardless of what I show, I could be using the real estate to show something that was more beneficial to the reader. And that’s the thing, it’s all about them. Anything I showed them beyond the form they already subscribed with would be more beneficial.</p>

<h2>I’m excited to tell you about [Funnel</h2>

<p>Optimizer](<a href="https://funneloptimizer.herokuapp.com/">https://funneloptimizer.herokuapp.com/</a>)!</p>

<p>I built Funnel Optimizer for people like me, and you. I want to help you sell more products, and provide even more value than you’re already providing. Funnel Optimizer offers you the opportunity to tailor your CTAs based on actions your audience have previously taken.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/funnel_optimizer/screenshots.png" title="&ldquo;Screenshots of FunnelOptimizer.io&rdquo;" ></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
