<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: sale | Brandon Hilkert]]></title>
  <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/categories/sale/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-08-10T08:11:38-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brandon Hilkert]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[brandonhilkert@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Ruby Book Bundle Is Live]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/the-ruby-book-bundle-is-live/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-06T07:01:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/the-ruby-book-bundle-is-live</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few fellow authors and friends of mine have put together the <a href="http://rubybookbundle.com/?c=bh">Ruby Book Bundle</a> including some of the best Ruby/Rails books out there. The <a href="http://rubybookbundle.com/?c=bh">bundle went on sale this morning</a>! It'll <strong>only be available for a week</strong>, so be sure to pick it up soon if you&rsquo;re interested.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><img class="center" src="/images/ruby-book-bundle.png" title="&ldquo;The Ruby Book Bundle&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a quick rundown of the details:</p>

<p><strong>Is this bundle right for me?</strong></p>

<p>The books in the Ruby Book Bundle span a range from beginner to advanced developers. <strong>As long as you understand the Ruby basics, though, you’ll learn a lot from these books.</strong></p>

<p>You’ll probably get the <em>most</em> out of the bundle if you’re an intermediate Ruby dev, focused on building more specific development skills. But if you’re interested in mastering the most important and most challenging parts of Rails, like testing, refactoring, gem-building, metaprogramming/DSL-writing, and app-building, this bundle will be perfect for you.</p>

<h2>What will I get?</h2>

<p>When you buy the bundle, you’ll immediately get the following to download:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Build a Ruby Gem</strong> (pdf, epub, mobi) with source code and screencasts</li>
<li><strong>Minitest Cookbook</strong> (pdf, epub, mobi) and source code examples</li>
<li><strong>Practicing Rails</strong> (pdf, epub, mobi)</li>
<li><strong>Fearless Refactoring</strong> (pdf)</li>
<li><strong>Ruby DSL Handbook</strong> (pdf, epub, mobi) with cheat sheets, sample code and screencasts</li>
<li><strong>Rebuilding Rails</strong> (pdf)</li>
</ul>


<h2>How long will the sale run?</h2>

<p>The bundle will be <strong>available for 1 week only</strong> &ndash; ending <strong>July 10th, 11:59PM PDT</strong>.</p>

<h2>What if I’m not happy with the bundle?</h2>

<p>We want you to be happy with what you’ve bought! <strong>So if you’re not 100% satisfied with the value you got from the bundle, shoot me an email at <a href="mailto:brandonhilkert%2Bbundle@gmail.com">brandonhilkert+bundle@gmail.com</a> within 30 days, and I’ll refund your money.</strong></p>

<p>I feel fortunate to be part of such a great group of developers. They&rsquo;ve
provided a ton of value to the community and their books continue to impress
me.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
