<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: sidekiq | Brandon Hilkert]]></title>
  <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/categories/sidekiq/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-10-25T20:02:01-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brandon Hilkert]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[brandonhilkert@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reducing Sidekiq Memory Usage with Jemalloc]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/reducing-sidekiq-memory-usage-with-jemalloc/"/>
    <updated>2018-04-28T14:42:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/reducing-sidekiq-memory-usage-with-jemalloc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ruby and Rails don&rsquo;t have a reputation of being memory-friendly. This comes with a trade-off of being a higher level language that tends to be more developer-friendly. For me, it works. I&rsquo;m content knowing I might have to pay more to scale a large application knowing I can write it in a language I enjoy.</p>

<p>Turns out&hellip;Ruby’s not the memory hog I&rsquo;d previously thought. After some research and experimentation, I&rsquo;ve found <code>jemalloc</code> to offer significant memory savings while at least preserving performance, if not improving it as well.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>The Problem</h2>

<p>At <a href="https://www.bark.us">Bark</a>, we poll external APIs for millions of monitored social media, text, and emails. This is all done through <a href="http://sidekiq.org/">Sidekiq</a> background jobs. Even though Ruby doesn&rsquo;t truly allow parallelism, we see great benefit with Sidekiq concurrency as the jobs wait for external APIs to respond. The API responses can often be large, not to mention any media they might include. As a result, we see the memory usage of our Sidekiq workers increase until they&rsquo;re ultimately killed and restarted by <a href="https://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/Software/systemd/"><code>systemd</code></a>.</p>

<p>The following shows a common memory usage pattern for our queue servers:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/jemalloc/sidekiq-memory-usage-before.png" title="&ldquo;Sidekiq servers memory usage before using jemalloc&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>Two things to notice:</p>

<ol>
<li><p><strong>Memory increased quickly</strong> - The rise of memory happens immediately after the processes are restarted. We deploy multiple times a day, but this was especially problematic on the weekends when deploys are happening less frequently</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Memory wasn&rsquo;t reused until restarted</strong> - The jaggedness of graph towards the center is the result of the memory limits we imposed on the <code>systemd</code> processes, causing them to be killed and ultimately restarted until they later reach the configured max memory setting again. Because the processes didn&rsquo;t appear to be reusing memory, we saw this happen just a few minutes after being restarted.</p></li>
</ol>


<h2>The Solution</h2>

<p>As the <a href="https://brandonhilkert.com/blog/why-i-wrote-the-sucker-punch-gem/">author of a multi-threaded background processing library</a>, I frequently see reports of memory leaks in Rails applications. As a Sidekiq user, <a href="https://github.com/mperham/sidekiq/issues/3824">this one caught my attention</a>. It starts as a classic memory leak report, but later turns towards deeper issues in the underlying operating system, not in the application. With <a href="https://www.speedshop.co/2017/12/04/malloc-doubles-ruby-memory.html">Nate Berkopec&rsquo;s post on Ruby memory usage in multi-threaded applications</a> referenced, the reporter found switching to <code>jemalloc</code> to fix their issue.</p>

<p><code>jemalloc</code> describes itself as:</p>

<blockquote><p>a general purpose malloc(3) implementation that emphasizes fragmentation avoidance and scalable concurrency support</p></blockquote>

<p>The description targets our use-case and issues with the current memory allocator. We were seeing terrible fragmentation when using Sidekiq (concurrent workers).</p>

<h3>How to use jemalloc</h3>

<p>Ruby can use <code>jemalloc</code> a few different ways. It can be compiled with <code>jemalloc</code>, but we already had Ruby installed and were interested in trying it with the least amount of infrastructure changes.</p>

<p>It turns out Ruby will attempt to use <code>jemalloc</code> if the <a href="https://github.com/jemalloc/jemalloc/wiki/Getting-Started">well-document environment variable <code>LD_PRELOAD</code></a> is set.</p>

<p>Our Sidekiq servers use Ubuntu 16.04, so we started by installing <code>jemalloc</code>:</p>

<p><figure class="code"><pre><code class="bash">sudo apt-get install libjemalloc-dev</code></pre></figure></p>

<p>From there, we configured the <code>LD_PRELOAD</code> environment variable by adding the following to <code>/etc/environment</code>:</p>

<p><figure class="code"><pre><code class="bash">LD_PRELOAD=/usr/lib/x86_64-linux-gnu/libjemalloc.so.1</code></pre></figure></p>

<p><em>Note: The location of <code>jemalloc</code> may vary depending on version and/or Linux distribution.</em></p>

<h3>Benchmark</h3>

<p>We benchmarked <code>jemalloc</code> on just one of the queue servers. This would allow us to do a true comparison against similar activity.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/jemalloc/sidekiq-memory-usage-comparison.png" title="&ldquo;Sidekiq server memory usage with one server using jemalloc&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>As we can see, the difference is drastic &ndash; <strong>over 4x decrease in memory usage</strong>!</p>

<p>The more impressive detail was the consistency. Total memory usage doesn&rsquo;t waver much. Processing large payloads and media, I assumed we&rsquo;d continue to see the peaks and valleys common to processing social media content. The sidekiq processes using <code>jemalloc</code> show a better ability to use previously allocated memory.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/jemalloc/sidekiq-memory-usage-with-jemalloc-details.png" title="&ldquo;Sidekiq server memory usage details with one server using jemalloc&rdquo;" ></p>

<h3>Roll it in to production</h3>

<p>With similar behavior over a 3 day period, we concluded to roll it out to the remaining queue servers.</p>

<p>The reduced memory usage continues to be impressive, all without any noticeable negative trade-offs.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/jemalloc/sidekiq-memory-usage-after.png" title="&ldquo;Sidekiq server memory usage after using jemalloc&rdquo;" ></p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>We were surprised by the significant decrease in memory usage by switching to <code>jemalloc</code>. Based on the other reports, we assumed it be reasonable, but not a 4x decrease.</p>

<p>Even after looking at these graphs for the last couple days, the differences seem too good to be true. But all is well and it&rsquo;s hard to imagine NOT doing this for any Ruby server we deploy in the future.</p>

<p>Give it a shot. I&rsquo;d love to see your results.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Monitoring Sidekiq using AWS Lambda and CloudWatch]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/monitoring-sidekiq-using-aws-lambda-and-cloudwatch/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-27T13:58:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/monitoring-sidekiq-using-aws-lambda-and-cloudwatch</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few articles ago, I wrote about <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/monitoring-sidekiq-using-aws-lambda-and-slack/">how to monitor Sidekiq retries using AWS Lambda</a>. Retries are often the first indication of an issue if your application does a lot of background work.</p>

<p>As <a href="https://www.bark.us">Bark</a> continues to grow, we became interested in how the number of jobs enqueued and retrying trended over time. Using AWS Lambda to post this data to CloudWatch, we were able to visualize this data over time.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>The Problem</h2>

<p><a href="http://sidekiq.org/">Sidekiq</a> offers a way to visual the jobs processed over time when on the dashboard. In fact, <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/3-ways-to-get-started-contributing-to-open-source/">this graph was one of my first open source contributions</a>.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/sidekiq-cloudwatch/sidekiq-dashboard.png" title="&ldquo;Sidekiq Dashboard&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>Unfortunately, these graph don&rsquo;t show the number of retries from 2 am last night, or how long it took to exhaust the queues when 2 million jobs were created.</p>

<p>Historical queue data is important if our application does a lot of background work and number of users is growing. Seeing these performance characteristics over time can help us be more prepared to add more background workers or scale our infrastructure in a way to stay ahead when our application is growing quickly.</p>

<h2>The Solution</h2>

<p>Because Bark is on AWS, we naturally looked to their tools for assistance. We already use CloudWatch to store data about memory, disk, and CPU usage for each server. This has served us well and allows us to set alarms for certain thresholds and graph this data over time:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/sidekiq-cloudwatch/cloudwatch-memory.png" title="&ldquo;Monitoring memory usage on AWS CloudWatch&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>Knowing we&rsquo;d have similar data for queue usage, we figured we could do the same with Sidekiq.</p>

<h3>Sidekiq Queue Data Endpoint</h3>

<p>If you remember from the last article on <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/monitoring-sidekiq-using-aws-lambda-and-slack/">monitoring Sidekiq retries using AWS Lambda</a>, we setup an endpoint in our application to return Sidekiq stats:</p>

<pre><code>require 'sidekiq/api'

class SidekiqQueuesController &lt; ApplicationController
  skip_before_action :require_authentication

  def index
    base_stats = Sidekiq::Stats.new
    stats = {
       enqueued: base_stats.enqueued,
       queues: base_stats.queues,
       busy: Sidekiq::Workers.new.size,
       retries: base_stats.retry_size
    }

    render json: stats
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>along with the route:</p>

<pre><code>resources :sidekiq_queues, only: [:index]
</code></pre>

<p>Using this resource, we need to poll at some regular interval and store the results.</p>

<h3>AWS Lambda Function</h3>

<p>AWS Lambda functions are perfect for one-off functions that feel like a burden to maintain in our application.</p>

<p>For the trigger, we&rsquo;ll use &ldquo;CloudWatch Events - Schedule&rdquo;:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/sidekiq-monitor/lambda-trigger.png" title="&ldquo;AWS Lambda trigger&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>From here, we&rsquo;ll enter a name and description for our rule and define its rate (I chose every 5 minutes). Enable the trigger and we&rsquo;ll move to defining our code. Next, we&rsquo;ll give the function a name and choose the latest NodeJS as the runtime. Within the inline editor, we&rsquo;ll use the following code:</p>

<pre><code>var AWS = require('aws-sdk');
var url = require('url');
var https = require('https');

if (typeof Promise === 'undefined') {
  AWS.config.setPromisesDependency(require('bluebird'));
}

var cloudwatch = new AWS.CloudWatch();

sidekiqUrl = '[Sidekiq stat URL]'

var logMetric = function(attr, value) {
    var params = {
        MetricData: [
            {
                MetricName: attr,
                Dimensions: [
                    {
                        Name: "App",
                        Value: "www"
                    }
                ],
                Timestamp: new Date(),
                Unit: "Count",
                Value: value
            }
        ],
        Namespace: "Queues"
    };

    return cloudwatch.putMetricData(params).promise();
}

var getQueueStats = function(statsUrl) {
    return new Promise(function(resolve, reject) {
        var options = url.parse(statsUrl);
        options.headers = {
            'Accept': 'application/json',
        };
        var req = https.request(options, function(res){
            var body = '';

            res.setEncoding('utf8');

            //another chunk of data has been recieved, so append it to `str`
            res.on('data', function (chunk) {
                body += chunk;
            });

            //the whole response has been recieved
            res.on('end', function () {
                resolve(JSON.parse(body));
            });
        });

        req.on('error', function(e) {
           reject(e);
        });

        req.end();
    });
}

exports.handler = function(event, context) {
    getQueueStats(sidekiqUrl).then(function(stats) {
        console.log('STATS: ', stats);

        var retryPromise = logMetric("Retries", stats.retries);
        var busyPromise = logMetric("Busy", stats.busy);
        var enqueuedPromise = logMetric("Enqueued", stats.enqueued);

        Promise.all([retryPromise, busyPromise, enqueuedPromise]).then(function(values) {
            console.log(values);
            context.succeed();
        }).catch(function(err){
            console.error(err);
            context.fail("Server error when processing message: " + err );
        });
    })
    .catch(function(err) {
        console.error(err);
        context.fail("Failed to get stats from HTTP request: " + err );
    });
};
</code></pre>

<p><em>Note: <code>sidekiqURL</code>  need to be defined with appropriate values for this to work.</em></p>

<p>Within CloudWatch, we&rsquo;re defining a new namespace (&ldquo;Queues&rdquo;) where our data will live. Within this namespace, we&rsquo;ll segregate these stats by the Dimension <code>App</code>. As we can see, we chose <code>www</code> for this value. If we wanted to monitor the queues of a few servers, each one could use a unique App name.</p>

<p>Review and save the Lambda function and we&rsquo;re all set!</p>

<h3>Graphing Sidekiq Queue Data</h3>

<p>Once the function has run a few times, under CloudWatch &ndash;> Metrics, we&rsquo;ll see the following custom namespace:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/sidekiq-cloudwatch/custom-namespace.png" title="&ldquo;AWS CloudWatch Custom Namespace&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>From here, we&rsquo;ll choose the name of our app (<code>www</code>) and graph the values of each of these values over whatever timespan we want:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/sidekiq-cloudwatch/sidekiq-queues.png" title="&ldquo;AWS CloudWatch Monitoring Sidekiq Queues&rdquo;" ></p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve found AWS lamba to be a great place for endpoints/functionality that feels cumbersome to include in my applications. Bringing deeper visibility to our Sidekiq queues has given us the ability to see usage trends we weren&rsquo;t aware of throughout the day. This will help us preemptively add infrastructure resources to keep up with our growth.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Monitoring Sidekiq Using AWS Lambda and Slack]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/monitoring-sidekiq-using-aws-lambda-and-slack/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-25T11:54:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/monitoring-sidekiq-using-aws-lambda-and-slack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s no mystery I&rsquo;m a <a href="http://sidekiq.org/">Sidekiq</a> fan &ndash; my background job processing library of choice for any non-trivial applications. My favorite feature of Sidekiq has to be retries. By default, failed jobs will retry 25 times over the course of 21 days.</p>

<p>As a remote company, we use Slack to stay in touch with everyone AND to manage/monitor our infrastructure (hello #chatops). We can deploy from Slack (we don&rsquo;t generally, we have full CI) and be notified of infrastructure and application errors.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>When Sidekiq retries accumulate, it&rsquo;s a good indication that something more severe might be wrong. Rather than get an email we won&rsquo;t see for 30 minutes, we decided to integrate these notifications in to Slack. In doing so, we found <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/lambda/">AWS Lambda</a> to be a lightweight solution to tie the monitoring of Sidekiq and notifications in Slack together.</p>

<h2>The Problem</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.bark.us/">Bark</a> is background job-heavy. The web application is a glorified CRUD app that sets up the data needed to poll a child&rsquo;s social media feed and monitor for potential issues. The best-case scenario for a parent is that they will never hear from us.</p>

<p>Because Bark&rsquo;s background jobs commonly interact with 3rd-party APIs, failures aren&rsquo;t a big surprise. APIs can be down, network connections can fail &ndash; Sidekiq&rsquo;s retry logic protects us from transient network errors. Under normal circumstances, jobs retry and ultimately run successfully after subsequent attempts. These are non-issues and something we don&rsquo;t need an engineer to investigate.</p>

<p>There are times when retries accumulate, giving us a strong indication that something more severe may be wrong. Initially, we setup New Relic to notify us of an increased error rate. This worked for simple cases, but was sometimes a false positive. As a result, we started to ignore them, which potentially masked more important issues.</p>

<p>We soon realized one of the gauges of application health was the number of retries in the Sidekiq queue. We have the Sidekiq Web UI mounted within our admin application, so we&rsquo;d browse there a few times a day to make sure the number of retries weren&rsquo;t outside our expectations (in this case &lt; 50 were acceptable).</p>

<p>This wasn&rsquo;t a great use of our time. Ideally, we wanted a Slack notification when the number of Sidekiq retries was > 50.</p>

<h2>The Solution</h2>

<p>Because Bark is on AWS, we naturally looked to their tools for assistance. In this case, we needed something that would poll Sidekiq, check the number of retries, and <code>POST</code> to Slack if the number of retries was > 50.</p>

<p>There were a few options:</p>

<ol>
<li>Add the Sidekiq polling and Slack notification logic to our main application and setup a Cron job</li>
<li>Create a new satellite application that ONLY does the above (microservices???)</li>
<li>Setup an AWS Lambda function to handle the above logic</li>
</ol>


<p>The first two options would&rsquo;ve worked, but I was hesistant to add complexity to our main application. I was also hesitant to have to manage another application (ie. updates, etc.) for something that seemed simple.</p>

<p>Option &ldquo;AWS Lambda&rdquo; won! Let&rsquo;s take a look at the implementation.</p>

<h3>Sidekiq Queue Data Endpoint</h3>

<p>First, we need to expose the number of Sideki retries somehow. As I mentioned above, the Sidekiq web UI is mounted in our admin application, but behind an authentication layer that would&rsquo;ve been non-trivial to publicly expose.</p>

<p>Instead, we created a new Rails route to respond with some basic details about the Sidekiq system.</p>

<pre><code>require 'sidekiq/api'

class SidekiqQueuesController &lt; ApplicationController
  skip_before_action :require_authentication

  def index
    base_stats = Sidekiq::Stats.new
    stats = {
       enqueued: base_stats.enqueued,
       queues: base_stats.queues,
       busy: Sidekiq::Workers.new.size,
       retries: base_stats.retry_size
    }

    render json: stats
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>along with the route:</p>

<pre><code>resources :sidekiq_queues, only: [:index]
</code></pre>

<p>As you can see, the endpoint is public (there&rsquo;s no job args or names exposed &ndash; just counts). The code digs in to the <a href="https://github.com/mperham/sidekiq/wiki/API">Sidekiq API</a> to interrogate the size of queues.</p>

<h3>Slack Incoming WebHook</h3>

<p>We want to be able to POST to Slack when the number of Sidekiq retries are > 50. To do this, we&rsquo;ll setup a custom incoming webhook integration in Slack.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;ll start by choose <code>Apps &amp; integrations</code> from within the main Slack options. From here, choose <code>Manage</code> in the top right, and then <code>Custom Integrations</code> on the left. You&rsquo;ll have 2 options:</p>

<ol>
<li>Incoming WebHooks</li>
<li>Slash Commands</li>
</ol>


<p>We&rsquo;ll choose <code>Incoming Webhooks</code> and choose <code>Add Configuration</code> to add a new one. From here, we&rsquo;ll supply the information needed to specify the channel where the notifications will appear and how they look.</p>

<p>The most important of this step is to get the <code>Webhook URL</code>. This will be the URL we <code>POST</code> to from within our Lambda function when retries are above our acceptable threshold.</p>

<h3>AWS Lambda Function</h3>

<p>Now that we have our endpoint to expose the number of retries (among other things) and the Slack webhook URL to <code>POST</code> to, we need to setup the AWS Lambda function to tie to the two together. We&rsquo;ll start by creating a new Lambda function with the defaults &ndash; using the latest Node.</p>

<p>For the trigger, we&rsquo;ll use &ldquo;CloudWatch Events - Schedule&rdquo;:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/sidekiq-monitor/lambda-trigger.png" title="&ldquo;AWS Lambda trigger&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>From here, we&rsquo;ll enter a name and description for our rule and define its rate (I chose every 5 minutes). Enable the trigger and we&rsquo;ll move to defining our code. Next, we&rsquo;ll give the function a name and choose the latest NodeJS as the runtime. Within the inline editor, we&rsquo;ll use the following code:</p>

<pre><code>var AWS = require('aws-sdk');
var url = require('url');
var https = require('https');
var sidekiqURL, hookUrl, slackChannel, retryThreshold;

sidekiqUrl = '[Sidekiq queue JSON endpoint]'
hookUrl = '[Slack Incoming WebHooks URL w/ token]';
slackChannel = '#operations';  // Enter the Slack channel to send a message to
retryThreshold = 50;

var postMessageToSlack = function(message, callback) {
    var body = JSON.stringify(message);
    var options = url.parse(hookUrl);
    options.method = 'POST';
    options.headers = {
        'Content-Type': 'application/json',
        'Content-Length': Buffer.byteLength(body),
    };

    var postReq = https.request(options, function(res) {
        var chunks = [];
        res.setEncoding('utf8');
        res.on('data', function(chunk) {
            return chunks.push(chunk);
        });
        res.on('end', function() {
            var body = chunks.join('');
            if (callback) {
                callback({
                    body: body,
                    statusCode: res.statusCode,
                    statusMessage: res.statusMessage
                });
            }
        });
        return res;
    });

    postReq.write(body);
    postReq.end();
};

var getQueueStats = function(callback) {
    var options = url.parse(sidekiqUrl);
    options.headers = {
        'Accept': 'application/json',
    };

    var getReq = https.request(options, function(res){
        var body = '';

        res.setEncoding('utf8');

        //another chunk of data has been recieved, so append it to `str`
        res.on('data', function (chunk) {
            body += chunk;
        });

        //the whole response has been recieved, so we just print it out here
        res.on('end', function () {
            if (callback) {
                callback({
                    body: JSON.parse(body),
                    statusCode: res.statusCode,
                    statusMessage: res.statusMessage
                });
            }
        });
    })

    getReq.end();
}

var processEvent = function(event, context) {
    getQueueStats(function(stats){
        console.log('STATS: ', stats.body);

        var retries = stats.body.retries;

        if (retries &gt; retryThreshold) {
            var slackMessage = {
                channel: slackChannel,
                text: "www Sidekiq retries - " + retries
            };

            postMessageToSlack(slackMessage, function(response) {
                if (response.statusCode &lt; 400) {
                    console.info('Message posted successfully');
                    context.succeed();
                } else if (response.statusCode &lt; 500) {
                    console.error("Error posting message to Slack API: " + response.statusCode + " - " + response.statusMessage);
                    context.succeed();  // Don't retry because the error is due to a problem with the request
                } else {
                    // Let Lambda retry
                    context.fail("Server error when processing message: " + response.statusCode + " - " + response.statusMessage);
                }
            });
        } else {
            console.info('Sidekiq retries were ' + retries + ' . Below threshold.');
            context.succeed();
        }
    })
};

exports.handler = function(event, context) {
    processEvent(event, context);
};
</code></pre>

<p><em>Note: <code>sidekiqURL</code> and <code>hookURL</code> need to be defined with appropriate values for this to work.</em></p>

<p>Review and save the Lambda function and we&rsquo;re all set!</p>

<h3>Review</h3>

<p>We can review the Lambda function logs on CloudWatch. Go to CloudWatch and choose &ldquo;Logs&rdquo; from the left menu. From here, we&rsquo;ll click the link to the name of our Lambda function:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/sidekiq-monitor/sidekiq-logs.png" title="&ldquo;AWS Cloudwatch logs&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>From here, logs for each invocation of the Lambda function will be grouped in to a log stream:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/sidekiq-monitor/log-streams.png" title="&ldquo;AWS Cloudwatch log streams&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>Grouped by time, each link will contain multiple invocations. A single execution is wrapped with a <code>START</code> and <code>END</code>, as shown in the logs. Messages in between will be calls to <code>console.log</code> from within our function. We logged the results of the Sidekiq queue poll for debugging purposes, so you can see that below:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/sidekiq-monitor/log.png" title="&ldquo;AWS Cloudwatch log&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>This was invocation where the number of retries were &lt; 50, and a result, didn&rsquo;t need to <code>POST</code> to Slack. Let&rsquo;s take a look at the opposite:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/sidekiq-monitor/log-post.png" title="&ldquo;AWS Cloudwatch log posting to Slack&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>We can see the <code>Message posted successfully</code> log indicating our message was successfully sent to Slack&rsquo;s incoming webhook.</p>

<p>Finally, here&rsquo;s what the resulting message looks like in Slack when the number of Sidekiq retries are above our threshold:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/sidekiq-monitor/slack.png" title="&ldquo;Slack notifications for Sidekiq retries&rdquo;" ></p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Using new tools is fun, but not when it brings operational complexity. I&rsquo;ve personally found AWS lamba to be a great place for endpoints/functionality that feels cumbersome to include in my applications. Bringing these notifications in to Slack has been a big win for our team. We took a previously untrustworthy notification (NewRelic error rate) and brought some clarity to the state and health of our applications.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lessons Learned from Building a Ruby Gem API]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/lessons-learned-from-building-a-ruby-gem-api/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-04T13:12:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/lessons-learned-from-building-a-ruby-gem-api</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sucker Punch was created because I had a <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/why-i-wrote-the-sucker-punch-gem/">need for background processing without a separate worker</a>. But I also figured others did too, given that adding a worker dyno on Heroku was $35. For hobby apps, this was a significant cost.</p>

<p>Having gotten familiar with Celluloid from my work on Sidekiq, I knew Celluloid had all the pieces to puzzle to make this easier. In fact, one of the earliest incarnations of Sucker Punch wasn&rsquo;t a gem at all, just some Ruby classes implementing the pieces of Celluloid necessary to put together a background processing queue.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>The resulting code was less than ideal. It worked, but didn&rsquo;t feel like an API that anyone would want to use. From a beginner&rsquo;s perspective, this would stop adoption in its tracks. This is a common challenge with any code we encounter. No doubt, the Ruby standard library has all the tools necessary to make just about anything we can dream of, but sometimes the result isn&rsquo;t ideal. It&rsquo;s the same reason libraries like Rspec and HTTParty can exist. Developers prefer to use simplistic <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domain-specific_language">DSLs</a> over convoluted, similarly-functioning code. Ruby has always been a language where developers consistently tout their ability to write code that reads well, feeding the levels of developer happiness.</p>

<h2>Why Rewrite Sucker Punch</h2>

<p>It started when <a href="https://github.com/brandonhilkert/sucker_punch/issues/122">a version of Celluloid was yanked from RubyGems.org</a>. This resulted in a flurry of tweets and GH issues detailing their inability to bundle their applications.</p>

<p>As of version <code>0.17</code>, methods in public API changed without supporting documentation. On top of that, the core <code>celluloid</code> gem was split in to a series of child gems causing navigation to be painful.</p>

<p>This made my life as the Sucker Punch maintainer difficult. There were some requests to upgrade Sucker Punch to use Celluloid <code>~&gt; 0.17</code> and I feared of what would happen if I did. This caused me to think about what the future of Sucker Punch looked like without Celluloid. I still use Sucker Punch and believe it&rsquo;s a valuable asset to the community. My goal was to find a way to move it forward productively without experiencing similar pains.</p>

<p>In the end, thanks to some <a href="https://github.com/brandonhilkert/sucker_punch/pull/126">communinity contributions</a>, <a href="https://github.com/brandonhilkert/sucker_punch/blob/master/CHANGES.md#160">Sucker Punch <code>1.6.0</code> was released with Celluloid <code>0.17.2</code> support</a>.</p>

<h2>Where to now?</h2>

<p>Around that same time, Mike Perham had been writing about his experiences <a href="http://www.mikeperham.com/2015/10/14/optimizing-sidekiq/">optimizing Sidekiq</a> and <a href="http://www.mikeperham.com/2015/10/14/should-you-use-celluloid/">whether continuing with Celluloid made sense for Sidekiq</a>. Having less experience with multi-threading, it didn&rsquo;t make sense for me to reinvent the wheel.</p>

<p>I had been hearing about <a href="https://github.com/ruby-concurrency/concurrent-ruby"><code>concurrent-ruby</code></a> through a variety of outlets, one of which was Rails <a href="https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/20866">replacing the existing concurrency latch with similar functionality from <code>concurrent-ruby</code></a>. After poking around <code>concurrent-ruby</code>, I realized it had all the tools necessary to build a background job processing library. Much like Celluloid in that respect, had the tools, but lacked the simple DSL for the use case.</p>

<p>What if Sucker Punch used <code>concurrent-ruby</code> in place of <code>celluloid</code>?</p>

<p>I can hear what you&rsquo;re thinking&hellip;&ldquo;What&rsquo;s the difference? You&rsquo;re swapping one dependency for another!&rdquo;. 100% true. The difference was that the little bit of communication I had with the maintainers of <code>concurrent-ruby</code> felt comfortable, easy, and welcoming. And with <code>concurrent-ruby</code> now a dependency of Rails, it&rsquo;s even more accessible for those using Sucker Punch within a Rails application (a common use case). But like before, there&rsquo;s no way to be sure that  <code>concurrent-ruby</code> won&rsquo;t cause similar pains/frustrations.</p>

<h2>Celluloid Basics</h2>

<p>A basic Sucker Punch job looks like:</p>

<pre><code>class LogJob
  include SuckerPunch::Job

  def perform(event)
    Log.new(event).track
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>To run the job asynchronously, we use the following syntax:</p>

<pre><code>LogJob.new.async.perform("new_user")
</code></pre>

<p>The most interesting part of this method chain is the <code>async</code>. Removing <code>async</code>, leaves us with a call to a regular instance method.</p>

<p>It so happens that <a href="https://github.com/celluloid/celluloid/wiki/Basic-usage"><code>async</code> is a method in Celluloid that causes the next method to execute asynchronously</a>. And this works because by including <code>SuckerPunch::Job</code>, we&rsquo;re including <code>Celluloid</code>, which gives us the <code>async</code> method on instances of the job class.</p>

<h2>Developing APIs</h2>

<p>If you&rsquo;re familiar with the basics of Celluloid, you&rsquo;ll notice there&rsquo;s not much to Sucker Punch. It adds the Celluloid functionality to job classes and does some things under the hood to ensure there&rsquo;s one queue for each job class.</p>

<p><strong>Early in my <code>concurrent-ruby</code> spike, I realized what a mistake to tie Sucker Punch&rsquo;s API to the API of Celluloid</strong>. Tinkering with the idea of removing Celluloid has left Sucker Punch with two options:</p>

<ol>
<li>Continue using the <code>async</code> method with the new dependency</li>
<li>Break the existing DSL and create a dependency-independent syntax and try my best to document and support the change through the backwards-incompatible change</li>
</ol>


<p>Option 1 is the easy way out. Option 2 is more work, far more scary, but the right thing to do.</p>

<p>I decided to abandon my thoughts about previous versions and write as if it were new today. This will be the basis for the next major release of Sucker Punch (<code>2.0.0</code>).</p>

<p>Settling on abandoning the existing API, the next question is, <strong>&ldquo;What should the new API look like?&rdquo;</strong>.</p>

<p>Being a fan of Sidekiq, it didn&rsquo;t take long for me to realize it could actually make developers lives easier if Sucker Punch&rsquo;s API was the same.</p>

<p>Switching between Sidekiq and Sucker Punch is not uncommon. I look at Sidekiq as Sucker Punch&rsquo;s big brother and often suggest people use it instead when the use case makes sense.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re familiar with Sidekiq, using the <code>perform_async</code> class method should look familiar:</p>

<pre><code>LogJob.peform_async("new_user")
</code></pre>

<p><strong>So why not use the same for Sucker Punch?</strong></p>

<p>If so, switching between Sidekiq and Sucker Punch would be no more than swapping <code>include Sidekiq::Worker</code> for <code>include SuckerPunch::Job</code> in the job class, aside from the gem installation itself. The result would be less context switching and more opportunity focus on the important parts of the application.</p>

<p>I can hear the same question again, &ldquo;What&rsquo;s the difference? You suggested isolating yourself from a dependency&rsquo;s API and now you&rsquo;re suggesting using another!&rdquo;. I look at this one a little differently&hellip;</p>

<p>Sidekiq is uniquely positioned in the community as a paid open source project. We&rsquo;re happy users of Sidekiq Pro and continue to do so for the support. You can certainly get support for the open source version, but one way to ensure Sidekiq is actively maintained is by paying for it. This financial support from us and others decreases the likelihood Mike will choose to abandon it. Mike&rsquo;s also been public about his long-term interest in maintaining Sidekiq. With all this in mind, I&rsquo;m willing to bank on its existence as the defacto way to enqueue jobs for background processing.</p>

<p>And if for some reason Sidekiq does disappear, there&rsquo;s nothing lost on Sucker Punch. There&rsquo;s no dependency. Just a similar syntax.</p>

<p>Sucker Punch <code>2.0.0</code> will have 2 class methods to enqueue jobs:</p>

<pre><code>LogJob.perform_async("new_user")
</code></pre>

<p>and</p>

<pre><code>LogJob.perform_in(5.minutes, "new_user")
</code></pre>

<p>The latter defining a delayed processing of the <code>perform</code> method 5 minutes from now.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>Settling on a library&rsquo;s API isn&rsquo;t easy. Isolating it from underlying dependencies is the best bet for long-term stability. Using the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adapter">adapter pattern</a> can help create a layer (adapter) between your code and the dependency&rsquo;s API. But like always, there are always exceptions.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m taking a leap of faith that doing what I believe is right won&rsquo;t leave existing users frustrated, ultimately abandoning Sucker Punch altogether.</p>

<p>Sucker Punch <code>v2.0</code> is shaping up to be the best release yet. I&rsquo;m looking forward to sharing it with you.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sidekiq As A Microservice Message Queue]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/sidekiq-as-a-microservice-message-queue/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-30T12:06:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/sidekiq-as-a-microservice-message-queue</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the recent series on transitioning to microservices, I detailed a path to move a large legacy Rails monolith to a cluster of a dozen microservices. But not everyone starts out with a legacy monolith. In fact, given Rails popularity amongst startups, <strong>it&rsquo;s likely most Rails applications don&rsquo;t live to see 4+ years in production</strong>. So what if we don&rsquo;t have a huge monolith on our hands? Are microservices still out of the question?</p>

<p>Sadly, the answer is, &ldquo;it depends&rdquo;. The &ldquo;depends&rdquo; part is specific to your context. While microservices may seem like the right move for you and your application, it&rsquo;s also possible it could cause a mess if not done carefully.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>This post will explore opportunities for splitting out unique microservices using <a href="http://sidekiq.org/">Sidekiq</a>, without introducing an enterprise message broker like <a href="https://www.rabbitmq.com/">RabbitMQ</a> or <a href="http://kafka.apache.org/">Apache Kafka</a>.</p>

<h2>When are Microservices right?</h2>

<p>Martin Fowler <a href="http://martinfowler.com/articles/microservice-trade-offs.html">wrote about trade-offs that come when introducing microservices</a>.</p>

<p>The article outlines 6 pros and cons introduced when you moved a microservices-based architecture. The strongest argument for microservices is the strengthening of module boundaries.</p>

<p>Module boundaries are naturally strengthened when we&rsquo;re forced to move code to another codebase. The result being, in most cases a group of microservices appears to be better constructed than the legacy monolith it was extracted from.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s no doubt Rails allows developers to get something up and running very quickly. Sadly, you can do so while making a big mess at the same time. It&rsquo;s worth noting there&rsquo;s nothing stopping a monolith from being well constructed. With some discipline, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KJVTM7mE1Cc">your monolith can be the bright and shiny beauty that DHH wants it to be</a>.</p>

<h2>Sidekiq Queues</h2>

<p>Ok, ok. You get it. Microservices can be awesome, but they can also make a big mess. I want to tell you about how I recently avoided a big mess without going &ldquo;all in&rdquo;.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s no hiding I&rsquo;m a huge <a href="http://sidekiq.org/">Sidekiq</a> fan. It&rsquo;s my goto solution for background processing.</p>

<p>Sidekiq has the notion of <a href="https://github.com/mperham/sidekiq/wiki/Advanced-Options#workers">named queues</a> for both <a href="https://github.com/mperham/sidekiq/wiki/Advanced-Options#workers">jobs</a> and <a href="https://github.com/mperham/sidekiq/wiki/Advanced-Options#queues">workers</a>. This is great from the standpoint that it allows you to put that unimportant long-running job in a different queue without delayed other important fast-running jobs.</p>

<p>A typical worker might look like:</p>

<pre><code>class ImportantWorker
  include Sidekiq::Worker

  def perform(id)
    # Do the important stuff
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>If we want to send this job to a different queue, we&rsquo;d add <code>sidekiq_options queue: :important</code> to the worker, resulting in:</p>

<pre><code>class ImportantWorker
  include Sidekiq::Worker
  sidekiq_options queue: :important

  def perform(id)
    # Do the important stuff
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>Now, we need to make sure the worker process that&rsquo;s running the jobs knows to process jobs off this queue. A typical worker might be invoked with:</p>

<pre><code>bin/sidekiq
</code></pre>

<p>Since new jobs going through this worker will end up on the <code>important</code> queue, we want to make sure the worker is processing jobs from the <code>important</code> queue too:</p>

<pre><code>bin/sidekiq -q important -q default
</code></pre>

<p><em>Note: Jobs that don&rsquo;t specify a queue will go to the <code>default</code> queue. We have to include the <code>default</code> queue when we using the <code>-q</code> option, otherwise the default queue will be ignored in favor of the queue passed to the <code>-q</code> option.</em></p>

<p>The best part, you don&rsquo;t even have to have multiple worker processes to process jobs from multiple queues. Furthermore, the <code>important</code> queue can be checked twice as often as the <code>default</code> queue:</p>

<pre><code>bin/sidekiq -q important,2 -q default
</code></pre>

<p>This flexibility of where jobs are enqueued and how they&rsquo;re processed gives us an incredible amount of freedom when building our applications.</p>

<h2>Extracting Worker to a Microservice</h2>

<p>Let&rsquo;s assume that we&rsquo;ve deployed your main application to Heroku. The application uses Sidekiq and we&rsquo;ve included a Redis add-on. With the addition of the add-on, our application now has a <code>REDIS_URL</code> environment variable that Sidekiq connects to on startup. We have a web process, and worker process. A pretty standard Rails stack:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/sidekiq/rails-web-worker.png" title="&ldquo;Rails with typical worker process&rdquo;" ></p>

<p><strong>What&rsquo;s stopping us from using that same <code>REDIS_URL</code> in another application?</strong></p>

<p>Nothing, actually. And if we consider what we know about the isolation of jobs in queue and workers working on specific queues, there&rsquo;s nothing stopping us from having workers for a specific queue in a different application altogether.</p>

<p>Remember <code>ImportantWorker</code>, imagine the logic for that job was better left for a different application. We&rsquo;ll leave that part a little hand-wavey because there still should be a really good reason to do so. But we&rsquo;ll assume you&rsquo;ve thought long and hard about this and decided the core application was not a great place for this job logic.</p>

<p>Extracting the worker a separate application might now look something like this:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/sidekiq/rails-with-microservice.png" title="&ldquo;Using Sidekiq as a Message Queue between two Rails microservices&rdquo;" ></p>

<h2>Enqueueing Jobs with the Sidekiq Client</h2>

<p>Typically, to enqueue the <code>ImportantWorker</code> above, we&rsquo;d call the following from our application:</p>

<pre><code>ImportantWorker.perform_async(1)
</code></pre>

<p>This works great when <code>ImportantWorker</code> is defined in our application. With the expanded stack above, <code>ImportantWorker</code> now lives in a new microservice, which means we don&rsquo;t have access to the <code>ImportantWorker</code> class from within the application. We <em>could</em> define it in the application just so we can enqueue it, with the intent that the application won&rsquo;t process jobs for that worker, but that feels funny to me.</p>

<p>Rather, we can turn to the underlying Sidekiq client API to enqueue the job instead:</p>

<pre><code>Sidekiq::Client.push(
  "class" =&gt; "ImportantWorker",
  "queue" =&gt; "important",
  "args" =&gt; [1]
)
</code></pre>

<p><em>Note: We have to be sure to define the <code>class</code> as a string <code>"ImportantWorker"</code>, otherwise we&rsquo;ll get an exception during enqueuing because the worker isn&rsquo;t defined in the application.</em></p>

<h2>Processing Sidekiq Jobs from a Microservice</h2>

<p>Now we&rsquo;re pushing jobs to the <code>important</code> queue, but have nothing in our application to process them. In fact, our worker process isn&rsquo;t even looking at that queue:</p>

<pre><code>bin/sidekiq -q default
</code></pre>

<p>From our microservice, we setup a worker process to <strong>ONLY</strong> look at the <code>important</code> queue:</p>

<pre><code>bin/sidekiq -q important
</code></pre>

<p>We define the <code>ImportantWorker</code> in our microservice:</p>

<pre><code>class ImportantWorker
  include Sidekiq::Worker
  sidekiq_options queue: :important

  def perform(id)
    # Do the important stuff
  end
end
</code></pre>

<p>And now when the worker picks jobs out of the <code>important</code> queue, it&rsquo;ll process them using the <code>ImportantWorker</code> defined above in our microservice.</p>

<p>If we wanted to go one step further, the microservice could then enqueue a job using the Sidekiq client API to a queue that only the core application is working on in order to send communication back the other direction.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>Any architectural decision has risks. Microservices are no exception. Microservices can be easier than an enterprise message broker, cluster of new servers and a handful of devops headaches.</p>

<p>I originally dubbed this the &ldquo;poor man&rsquo;s message bus&rdquo;. With more thought, there&rsquo;s nothing &ldquo;poor&rdquo; about this. Sidekiq has a been a reliable piece of our infrastructure and I have no reason to believe that&rsquo;ll change, even if we are using it for more than just simple background processing from a single application.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
