<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ambition | Brandon Hilkert]]></title>
  <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/categories/ambition/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-09T08:50:47-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brandon Hilkert]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[brandonhilkert@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Be Ambitious]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/be-ambitious/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-31T13:04:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/be-ambitious</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>2013</h2>

<p>On Dec. 31, 2012, I sat around a dinner table with my wife and 4 of our
friends.  Discussing the upcoming New Year, we went around the table and shared
our resolutions. My turn came and I said, &ldquo;<em>I&rsquo;m going to finish an
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ironman_Triathlon">Ironman</a></em>&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Up until that point, my longest race of any kind was a half marathon &ndash;
certainly no triathlons. So for me, this was biiiiiiig time. I honestly don&rsquo;t
know if anyone believed what I said that night. I&rsquo;m not even sure I did. But
nonetheless, I had said it out loud in the presence of friends. The same
friends I&rsquo;d later have to explain why I bailed &ndash; <em>if I bailed</em>.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>But I didn&rsquo;t bail. On Sept. 21, I finished the
<a href="http://www.tricolumbia.org/events/?eid=5">ChesapeakeMan</a> in 12 hours and 54
minutes. I spent 3 hours/day, 6 days/week for the prior 30 weeks preparing for
that day. It was easily the longest 30 weeks of my life.</p>

<h2>Accountability</h2>

<p>During the training, there were a few times I seriously considered quitting. In
every one of those moments, I thought back to the scene around that dinner
table on New Year&rsquo;s Eve. I had confidently told 5 other people I was going to
finish an Ironman and I didn&rsquo;t want to have to explain that I quit.</p>

<p>This is accountability&hellip;had I not mentioned by goal that night, the only
person I would&rsquo;ve let down is myself &ndash; that&rsquo;s easy to stomach. But knowing
others had expectations made it close to impossible for me to quit.</p>

<h2>2014</h2>

<p>With an Ironman crossed off my list, here we are, one year later. And rather
than rely on another dinner party resolution sharing session, I&rsquo;m documenting my resolution
here. So here goes&hellip;</p>

<h2>This year I&rsquo;m going to write to <a href="/books/build-a-ruby-gem/">write a book</a>.</h2>

<p>I never would&rsquo;ve thought a book would be in my future, but that&rsquo;s what
resolutions are for, right?!?! I also never would&rsquo;ve guessed I&rsquo;d finish an
Ironman, so why not keep the ball rollin'.</p>

<h2>In Summary</h2>

<p>Do something <strong>ambitious</strong> this year. Don&rsquo;t be the person that plan to lose 20
lbs. and quits going to the gym a week in to it. After my experience this year,
I believe <strong>everyone</strong> is capable of far more than they think.</p>

<p>This could be the year you take that next big step. Whether it&rsquo;s learning a new
language, launching a new product, or finding your dream job. <strong>Tell someone
about it</strong>. I promise you&rsquo;ll second guess quitting.</p>

<p><em>Leave a comment with your ambitious goals for 2014.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
