<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: decorators | Brandon Hilkert]]></title>
  <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/categories/decorators/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-01-09T15:22:25-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brandon Hilkert]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[brandonhilkert@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Adding Functionality to Ruby Classes with Decorators]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/adding-functionality-to-ruby-classes-with-decorators/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-09T15:37:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/adding-functionality-to-ruby-classes-with-decorators</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/using-the-sucker-punch-ruby-gem-to-cache-stripe-data-in-rails/">last article</a>, I presented some code that wrapped up accessing a customer&rsquo;s Stripe data and added a caching layer on top. I wanted to take some time to dig in to that code and see how we can make it better.</p>

<p>Decorators give us a tool to add additional functionality to a class while still keeping the public API consistent. From the perspective of the client, this is a win-win! Not only do they get the added behavior, but they don&rsquo;t need to call different methods to do so.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>The Problem</h2>

<p>Our original class accessed data from Stripe <strong>AND</strong> cached the response for some time period. I accentuated &ldquo;AND&rdquo; because it&rsquo;s generally the word to be on alert for when considering whether functionality can be teased apart in to separate responsibilities.</p>

<p>The question becomes, can we make one class that accesses Stripe data, and another that&rsquo;s only responsible for caching it?</p>

<p>Of course we can!</p>

<h2>The Solution</h2>

<p>Let&rsquo;s start with the most basic form of accessing our Stripe customer data with the <a href="https://github.com/stripe/stripe-ruby">Stripe gem</a>:</p>

<p>```
class AccountsController &lt; ApplicationController
  before_action :require_authentication</p>

<p>  def show</p>

<pre><code>@customer = Stripe::Customer.retrieve(current_user.stripe_id)
@invoices = @customer.invoices
@upcoming_invoice = @customer.upcoming_invoice
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<h2>Extract an Adapter</h2>

<p>Because we&rsquo;re interfacing with a third-party system (Stripe), it makes sense for to create a local adapter to access the Stripe methods. It&rsquo;s probably not likely we&rsquo;re going to switch out the official Stripe gem for another one that access the same data, but a better argument might be that we could switch billing systems entirely in the future. And if we make a more generic adapter to our third-party billing system, we would only need to update our adapter when that time comes.</p>

<p>While the adapter optimization may seem like overkill here, we&rsquo;ll see how that generic adapter helps us implement our caching layer shortly.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s start by removing the notion that it&rsquo;s Stripe and all and call it <code>Billing</code>. Here we can expose the methods needed from the  <code>AccountsController</code> above:</p>

<p>```
class Billing
  attr_reader :billing_id</p>

<p>  def initialize(billing_id)</p>

<pre><code>@billing_id = billing_id
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def customer</p>

<pre><code>Stripe::Customer.retrieve(billing_id)
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def invoices</p>

<pre><code>customer.invoices
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def upcoming_invoice</p>

<pre><code>customer.upcoming_invoice
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>There we have it. A simple <code>Billing</code> class that wraps the methods that we used in the first place &mdash; no change in functionality. But certainly more organized and isolated.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s now use this new class in the accounts controller from earlier:</p>

<p>```
class AccountsController &lt; ApplicationController
  before_action :require_authentication</p>

<p>  def show</p>

<pre><code>billing = Billing.new(current_user.stripe_id)

@customer = billing.customer
@invoices = billing.invoices
@upcoming_invoice = billing.upcoming_invoice
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>Not too bad! At this point we&rsquo;ve provide the exact same functionality we had before, but we have a class that sits in the middle between the controller and Stripe gem &ndash; an adapter if you will.</p>

<h2>Create a Decorator</h2>

<p>Now that we have our adapter set up, let&rsquo;s look at how we can add caching behavior to improve the performance of our accounts page.</p>

<p>The most of basic form of a decorator is to pass in the object we&rsquo;re decorating (<code>Billing</code>), and define the same methods of the billing, but add the additional functionality on top of them.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s create a base form of  <code>BillingWithCache</code> that <strong>does nothing more</strong> than call the host methods:</p>

<p>```
class BillingWithCache
  def initialize(billing_service)</p>

<pre><code>@billing_service = billing_service
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def customer</p>

<pre><code>billing_service.customer
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def invoices</p>

<pre><code>customer.invoices
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def upcoming_invoice</p>

<pre><code>customer.upcoming_invoice
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  private</p>

<p>  attr_reader :billing_service
end
```</p>

<p>So while we haven&rsquo;t added any additional functionality, we have created the ability for this class to be used in place of our existing <code>Billing</code> class because it responds to the same API (<code>#customer</code>, <code>#invoices</code>, <code>#upcoming_invoice</code>).</p>

<p>Integrating this new class with <code>AccountsController</code> looks like:</p>

<p>```
class AccountsController &lt; ApplicationController
  before_action :require_authentication</p>

<p>  def show</p>

<pre><code>billing = BillingWithCache.new(Billing.new(current_user.stripe_id))

@customer = billing.customer
@invoices = billing.invoices
@upcoming_invoice = billing.upcoming_invoice
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>As you can see, we only had to change one line &mdash; the line where we decorated the original billing class:</p>

<p><code>
BillingWithCache.new(Billing.new(current_user.stripe_id))
</code></p>

<p>I know what you&rsquo;re thinking, &ldquo;But it doesn&rsquo;t actually cache anything!&rdquo;. You&rsquo;re right! Let&rsquo;s dig in to the <code>BillingWithCache</code> class and add that.</p>

<h2>Adding Caching Functionality</h2>

<p>In order to cache data using <code>Rails.cache</code>, we&rsquo;re going to need a cache key of some kind. Fortunately, the original <code>Billing</code> class provides a reader for <code>billing_id</code> that will allow us to make this unique to that user.</p>

<p><code>
def cache_key(item)
  "user/#{billing_id}/billing/#{item}"
end
</code></p>

<p>In this case, <code>item</code> can refer to things like <code>"customer"</code>, <code>"invoices"</code>, or <code>"upcoming_invoice"</code>. This gives us a method we can use internally with <code>BillingWithCache</code> to provide a cache key unique to the both the user and the type of data we&rsquo;re caching.</p>

<p>Adding in the calls to actually cache the data:</p>

<p>```
class BillingWithCache
  def initialize(billing_service)</p>

<pre><code>@billing_service = billing_service
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def customer</p>

<pre><code>key = cache_key("customer")

Rails.cache.fetch(key, expires: 15.minutes) do
  billing_service.customer
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def invoices</p>

<pre><code>key = cache_key("invoices")

Rails.cache.fetch(key, expires: 15.minutes) do
  customer.invoices
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def upcoming_invoice</p>

<pre><code>key = cache_key("upcoming_invoice")

Rails.cache.fetch(key, expires: 15.minutes) do
  customer.upcoming_invoice
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  private</p>

<p>  attr_reader :billing_service</p>

<p>  def cache_key(item)</p>

<pre><code>"user/#{billing_service.billing_id}/billing/#{item}"
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>The code above caches the call to each of these methods for 15 minutes. We could go further and move that to an argument with a default value, but I&rsquo;ll leave as an exercise for another time.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>Separating your application and third-party services helps keeps your applications flexible &mdash; offering the freedom to switch to another service when one no longer fits the bill.</p>

<p>Another benefit of an adapter is you have the freedom to name the class and methods whatever you like. The base gem for a service might not have the best names, or it may be that the names don&rsquo;t make sense when dragged in to your application&rsquo;s domain. This is a small but important point as applications get larger and its code more complex. The more variable/method names you need to think about when you poke around the code, the harder it&rsquo;ll be to remember what was going on. Not to mention the pain new developers will have if they acquire the code. Whether it&rsquo;s you or the next developer, the time you invest in creating great names will be greatly appreciated.</p>

<p>Using decorators in this way makes it easier for clients of the code to avoid change, but keep your applications flexible. The <code>Billing</code> class above was relatively simple &mdash; intentionally so. If the class being decorated has more than a few methods, it might be worth incorporating <code>SimpleDelegator</code> to ensure the methods that don&rsquo;t need additional functionality still continue to respond appropriately.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
