<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: book | Brandon Hilkert]]></title>
  <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/categories/book/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-01T13:20:21-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brandon Hilkert]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[brandonhilkert@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How I Launched an Email Course to 500+ People]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/how-i-launched-an-email-course/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-06T06:15:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/how-i-launched-an-email-course</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>About a month ago, I joined <a href="http://jfdi.bz/">JFDI.bz</a> &ndash; a community for
solo-founders launching their own thing. Once a month, the group engages in a
<em>Week of Hustle</em> &ndash; a week long sprint to launch something.
I chose to launch an email course on the topic of <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/courses/build-a-ruby-gem/?utm_source=bh-newsletter&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=woh-summary">building a Ruby
gem</a>.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Why <em>Build a Ruby Gem</em>?</h2>

<p>A few years ago, I was building my first Ruby gem and I was left pretty
confused with the process and conventions. After working through my
frustrations, I thought the information I learned could be useful to others.</p>

<p>Honestly, I thought to write an eBook at first, however, the last thing I
wanted was to invest a month or two of my time only to find out people
weren&rsquo;t interested.</p>

<p>An email course was a good medium &ndash; I could cover the basics well enough to get
people through their hangups, while also validating the need for an eBook. I
figured if I got <strong>100-200</strong> people to sign up for the course, I would move
forward with the book.</p>

<h2>Results</h2>

<p>It turns out my marketing efforts were more successful than I anticipated.</p>

<h3>Today, almost 600 people have taken the Build a Ruby Gem email course!</h3>

<h2>Email is King&hellip;still</h2>

<p>Prior to launching this email course, I&rsquo;d read about the value of building an
email list from people like <a href="http://nathanbarry.com/">Nathan Barry</a>, <a href="http://unicornfree.com/">Amy
Hoy</a> and <a href="http://justinjackson.ca/">Justin Jackson</a>.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d also read countless other posts describing the most common regrets when
launching a new product. Almost all of them included not building an email
list. With that said, it was one of the first things I setup.</p>

<p>I blogged each day about my progress. Each post had a
mailing list subscription form that sent them subsequent daily updates.  Subscriptions
were slow at first, but interest built.  By then end of the week <strong>232</strong> people had
subscribed. And the day the course went live, I was able to to convert <strong>115</strong>
(~50%) of them.</p>

<p>The people subscribed were <strong>EXACTLY</strong> my target audience so it&rsquo;s no surprise
conversion was high.</p>

<h2>Finding Your Target Audience</h2>

<p>Fortunately for me, my target audience was Ruby developers and they hang out
online (surprise, surprise). But where online&hellip;</p>

<p>Let me hit you with something that seems obvious in hindsight:</p>

<h3>Marketing is easy when you build a product for an audience you&rsquo;re already part of.</h3>

<p>This was something I&rsquo;d <a href="http://unicornfree.com/2013/how-do-you-create-a-product-people-want-to-buy">read over the past few
months</a>,
but not seen its value until now.</p>

<p>The email course is for <strong>Ruby developers</strong>, I&rsquo;m a <strong>Ruby Developer</strong>, so the
question becomes&hellip;.<em>where do I hang out online?</em></p>

<p>That question is <strong>easy</strong> to answer &ndash; <a href="http://rubyweekly.com/">Ruby weekly</a>,
<a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/ruby">Reddit</a> and
<a href="http://www.rubyflow.com/">RubyFlow</a>.</p>

<p>And don&rsquo;t you know&hellip;it turns out those 3 sources have been the highest
converting sources since the course launched:</p>

<ol>
<li>Ruby weekly &ndash; 131</li>
<li>RubyFlow &ndash; 65</li>
<li>Reddit &ndash; 62</li>
</ol>


<p>The remaining sources were a combination of direct links, social media and
other technology news aggregation sites (probably mostly stemming from the top
sources above).</p>

<p><em>Note: I&rsquo;ve been reading <a href="http://www.amazon.com/80-20-Sales-Marketing-Definitive/dp/1599185059">80/20 Sales and
Marketing</a>
and the numbers above coincide, almost exactly, to the 80/20 curve. That is,
80% of the conversion came from 20% of the sources.</em></p>

<h2>Twitter Tip</h2>

<p>The last day of the email course has a <em>Summary</em> section thanking people for
taking the course and attempting to get feedback. While I haven&rsquo;t received much
constructive criticism, I dropped this little doozie at the bottom:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/email-course/click-to-tweet.png" title="&ldquo;Build a Ruby Gem Email Course Click To Tweet&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>I&rsquo;d read a post about <a href="http://grinnick.com/posts/how-groove-s-email-copy-makes-their-posts-go-viral?ref=hn">GroveHQ&rsquo;s emails going
viral</a>
and this was something they did in their campaigns.</p>

<p>The link allows people to click and immediately be setup to Tweet the
following:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/email-course/course-tweet.png" title="&ldquo;Build a Ruby Gem Email Course Tweet&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s difficult to determine the value of those tweets, but over 10 people have
clicked and tweeted. To me, this was surprising, but valuable.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll probably look to make it stand out a bit more to hopefully improve the
click-through.</p>

<h2>In Summary</h2>

<p>I spent a total of <strong>16 hours</strong> creating the <em>Build a Ruby Gem</em> email
course, which has since <strong>validated the need for a book</strong>. While interest
in a free email course doesn&rsquo;t guarantee a book on the same subject will sell, it was
the closet thing I could think to do outside of taking pre-orders.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve started writing the <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/books/build-a-ruby-gem/?utm_source=bh-newsletter&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=woh-summary"><em>Build a Ruby Gem</em>
book</a>.
If you&rsquo;re interested in receiving updates on my progress, enter your email
below:</p>

<p><div class="inline-newsletter-form">
  <form action="http://brandonhilkert.us7.list-manage2.com/subscribe/post?u=34ccc3aa2135746d0231c9420&id=3c07d60ff7" method="post" target="_blank" novalidate>
    <input type="email" value="" name="EMAIL" class="email" id="mce-EMAIL" placeholder="email" required>
    <input type="hidden" name="LOCATION" id="LOCATION" value="Category: book" />
    <input type="hidden" name="PRODUCT" id="PRODUCT" value="book-gem" />
    <input type="submit" value="Subscribe" name="subscribe" id="mc-embedded-subscribe" class="button">
  </form>
</div>

</p>

<p>Members of this list will also receive a <strong>20% discount coupon</strong> when the book
launches!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Be Ambitious]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/be-ambitious/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-31T13:04:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/be-ambitious</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>2013</h2>

<p>On Dec. 31, 2012, I sat around a dinner table with my wife and 4 of our
friends.  Discussing the upcoming New Year, we went around the table and shared
our resolutions. My turn came and I said, &ldquo;<em>I&rsquo;m going to finish an
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ironman_Triathlon">Ironman</a></em>&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Up until that point, my longest race of any kind was a half marathon &ndash;
certainly no triathlons. So for me, this was biiiiiiig time. I honestly don&rsquo;t
know if anyone believed what I said that night. I&rsquo;m not even sure I did. But
nonetheless, I had said it out loud in the presence of friends. The same
friends I&rsquo;d later have to explain why I bailed &ndash; <em>if I bailed</em>.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>But I didn&rsquo;t bail. On Sept. 21, I finished the
<a href="http://www.tricolumbia.org/events/?eid=5">ChesapeakeMan</a> in 12 hours and 54
minutes. I spent 3 hours/day, 6 days/week for the prior 30 weeks preparing for
that day. It was easily the longest 30 weeks of my life.</p>

<h2>Accountability</h2>

<p>During the training, there were a few times I seriously considered quitting. In
every one of those moments, I thought back to the scene around that dinner
table on New Year&rsquo;s Eve. I had confidently told 5 other people I was going to
finish an Ironman and I didn&rsquo;t want to have to explain that I quit.</p>

<p>This is accountability&hellip;had I not mentioned by goal that night, the only
person I would&rsquo;ve let down is myself &ndash; that&rsquo;s easy to stomach. But knowing
others had expectations made it close to impossible for me to quit.</p>

<h2>2014</h2>

<p>With an Ironman crossed off my list, here we are, one year later. And rather
than rely on another dinner party resolution sharing session, I&rsquo;m documenting my resolution
here. So here goes&hellip;</p>

<h2>This year I&rsquo;m going to write to <a href="/books/build-a-ruby-gem/">write a book</a>.</h2>

<p>I never would&rsquo;ve thought a book would be in my future, but that&rsquo;s what
resolutions are for, right?!?! I also never would&rsquo;ve guessed I&rsquo;d finish an
Ironman, so why not keep the ball rollin'.</p>

<h2>In Summary</h2>

<p>Do something <strong>ambitious</strong> this year. Don&rsquo;t be the person that plan to lose 20
lbs. and quits going to the gym a week in to it. After my experience this year,
I believe <strong>everyone</strong> is capable of far more than they think.</p>

<p>This could be the year you take that next big step. Whether it&rsquo;s learning a new
language, launching a new product, or finding your dream job. <strong>Tell someone
about it</strong>. I promise you&rsquo;ll second guess quitting.</p>

<p><em>Leave a comment with your ambitious goals for 2014.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
