<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: week of hustle | Brandon Hilkert]]></title>
  <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/categories/week-of-hustle/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-27T12:53:46-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brandon Hilkert]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[brandonhilkert@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Build a Ruby Gem Email Course - Weekend Update]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-weekend-update/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-09T06:15:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-weekend-update</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><p>
  <em>I did an <strong>8-day sprint</strong> to launch my <a
  href="/courses/build-a-ruby-gem/" target="_blank"><strong>Build a Ruby Gem</strong> email course</a>
  and documented my progress through this series of blog posts.</em>
</p>

<p><a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-woh-day-1/">Day 1</a> |
<a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-2/">Day 2</a> |
<a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-3/">Day 3</a> |
<a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-4/">Day 4</a> |
<a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-5/">Day 5</a> |
<a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-6/">Day 6</a> |
<a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-weekend-update/">Weekend Update</a>
<a href="/blog/how-i-launched-an-email-course/">Summary</a>
</p>

<p>Hope you had a great weekend!</p>

<p>Aside from hibernating inside due to the 6 extra inches of snow that wasn&rsquo;t
predicted, I spent some time with the course content this weekend. In efforts
to do a final proofread, I noticed something wasn&rsquo;t quite right. My goal for
this course was to smooth over the conventions of a Ruby gem that go much less
talked about. However, because I naively chose a gem that included Rails
integration as the example, the content ended up being more about Rails than I
had planned.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I thought about it for a bit on Saturday and decided it was best to
rewrite the content around a simpler gem example. So that my Sunday!</p>

<p>I thought about how I ended up down this path and realized it&rsquo;s because I
didn&rsquo;t put enough planning in to the actual content. Early on, I sketched our a
very rough outline of the lessons in the course, but never thought about the
examples or which gem to use. I originally picked on of my recent written gems
for Rails and assumed it was simple enough that I could quickly gloss over the
Rails details. But the last thing I wanted was for the Rails topics to cloud
the steps need to build a basic Ruby Gem.</p>

<p>Examples are really hard. I ended up choosing a topic that is probably not
supremely useful in an everyday Ruby application, however, the conventions and
theories apply to any gem.</p>

<p>I do plan to cover Rails integration in a future publication. There are so many
hooks in to the framework when using a Railtie, it almost deserves a separate
course. I did save the removed content, so I&rsquo;ll have to figure out where it&rsquo;s
best presented.</p>

<h2>What I Accomplished This Weekend</h2>

<p>As mentioned above, I rewrote the course content around a simpler gem example.
It did simplify the course, so I hope it&rsquo;ll be easier to navigate for those
that are less familiar with Ruby.</p>

<p>I also designed a landing page for the course that I&rsquo;m really excited about.
Web design has always been one of the skills that I&rsquo;ve struggled with. I can generally
get it 70-80% there, but never have it look really polished. I&rsquo;ve spent
more time doing that lately and finally feel like I&rsquo;m hitting the mark.</p>

<p>The only thing left to do is proofread the course content and setup the course
drip campaign in Mailchimp.</p>

<h2>Launch Date</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m excited to announce the course will launch this <strong>Wednesday (12/11) at 7AM
EST</strong>. I&rsquo;ll send an announcement on Wednesday morning with the registration
URL.</p>

<h2>Marketing</h2>

<p>Signups continued to trickle in throughout the weekend and I added another 30
subscriptions to this update list:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/woh/mailchimp-weekend.png" title="&ldquo;Mailchimp Weekend results&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>The link in Ruby Weekly amounted to 117 newsletter subscription
(<strong>almost 25% of the total visits</strong>). There&rsquo;s been no other channel even close to
that level of conversion.</p>

<p>During the process of posting course updates, I&rsquo;ve come across a few other
channels that I thought would be valuable sources of traffic after launch. I
plan to post to those sites sometime Wednesday and am interested to see how
they do relative to the sources I&rsquo;ve been using.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Build a Ruby Gem Email Course - Week of Hustle - Day 6]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-6/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-06T06:15:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-6</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><p>
  <em>I did an <strong>8-day sprint</strong> to launch my <a
  href="/courses/build-a-ruby-gem/" target="_blank"><strong>Build a Ruby Gem</strong> email course</a>
  and documented my progress through this series of blog posts.</em>
</p>

<p><a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-woh-day-1/">Day 1</a> |
<a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-2/">Day 2</a> |
<a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-3/">Day 3</a> |
<a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-4/">Day 4</a> |
<a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-5/">Day 5</a> |
<a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-6/">Day 6</a> |
<a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-weekend-update/">Weekend Update</a>
<a href="/blog/how-i-launched-an-email-course/">Summary</a>
</p>

<p>Happy Friday!</p>

<p>This morning I&rsquo;m feeling well rested and finally on the home stretch. In the
middle of the week, the remaining work felt overwhelming at times and I have a
feeling that played in to me feeling exhausted.</p>

<p>Part of it was that each lesson has gotten substantially longer than I planned
for. I think once I get in to the flow of writing, I tend to document
everything for everyone. I don&rsquo;t think everyone will need this level of detail,
but I&rsquo;d hate to leave it out, only to find that some users were left confused
because of the lack thereof.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s how the word count of each lesson shakes out so far:</p>

<!--more-->


<ul>
<li>Day 1 &ndash; 941</li>
<li>Day 2 &ndash; 1067</li>
<li>Day 3 &ndash; 1738</li>
<li>Day 4 &ndash; 868</li>
<li>Day 5 &ndash; 1118</li>
</ul>


<p>Looking at this now, I&rsquo;ll probably go back and rework Day 3 to either split out
some of the content, or remove it during editing depending on its value.</p>

<h2>What I Accomplished Today</h2>

<p>This morning I finished Day 5 of the Build a Ruby Gem Email Course. I&rsquo;m happy
with where it left off and can now say there&rsquo;s only 1 (2 at most) more to
write. And even those will be more wrap-up. All the code is finished.</p>

<p>I got in to the flow of writing pretty quickly this morning. I naturally woke
up around 6am, so I was probably less in a daze when I started.</p>

<h2>Marketing</h2>

<p>I was looking forward to writing this section&hellip;Yesterday, I opened my inbox and saw this:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/woh/ruby-weekly-link.png" title="&ldquo;A link to my Build a Ruby Gem email course in Ruby Weekly.&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>That&rsquo;s my course link in the <a href="http://rubyweekly.com/">Ruby Weekly</a> newsletter.
This newsletter is a great weekly summary of the Ruby community and has several
thousand subscribers. I had a feeling this would yield a significant bump in
subscriptions and page views and boy was that true.</p>

<p>Page views were up <strong>153%</strong> from the previous day:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/woh/ga-day5.png" title="&ldquo;Google Analytics day 5 results&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>And subscriptions for course updates were up <strong>130%</strong>:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/woh/mailchimp-day5.png" title="&ldquo;Mailchimp day 5 results&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>Herein lies the power of reaching your target audience&hellip;</p>

<p>I track conversions to the newsletter in Google Analytics and Ruby Weekly is
kind enough to send a lot a campaign identifier with the link. Here are the
channels that have converted the best:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/woh/ga-conversions-day5.png" title="&ldquo;Google Analytics traffic conversions from day 5&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>30% of all newsletter clicks resulted in newsletter subscriptions&hellip;I&rsquo;ll take
it! Not far behind is the campaign I sent to my personal list announcing the
email course, and next is links from Twitter. However, what this doesn&rsquo;t show
is that only 7 visitors arrived from Twitter referral links, so while 14% is
pretty good, it&rsquo;s a sample size that&rsquo;s probably not worth trusting.</p>

<p>While I&rsquo;ve read plenty about the power of email, I&rsquo;ve not seen this effect in
person until now. With these quick marketing recaps, I feel like I&rsquo;ve only
scratched the surface. After the course launches, I plan to spend more time
with the numbers to get a better feel for what went well, and more so, what I
should avoid in future launches.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Build a Ruby Gem Email Course - Week of Hustle - Day 5]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-5/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-05T06:15:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><p>
  <em>I did an <strong>8-day sprint</strong> to launch my <a
  href="/courses/build-a-ruby-gem/" target="_blank"><strong>Build a Ruby Gem</strong> email course</a>
  and documented my progress through this series of blog posts.</em>
</p>

<p><a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-woh-day-1/">Day 1</a> |
<a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-2/">Day 2</a> |
<a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-3/">Day 3</a> |
<a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-4/">Day 4</a> |
<a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-5/">Day 5</a> |
<a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-6/">Day 6</a> |
<a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-weekend-update/">Weekend Update</a>
<a href="/blog/how-i-launched-an-email-course/">Summary</a>
</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m tired. Getting up around 5am all week has worn on me. Yesterday I felt like
zombie&hellip;and it was mostly my own fault because I didn&rsquo;t make it a priority to
get bed a decent hour.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not sure about you, but I function best with 7-8 hours of sleep. I
generally can&rsquo;t sleep longer than 8, and anything less than 7 is OK for a
day or two, otherwise, it catches up with me. I think that&rsquo;s what&rsquo;s going
on here&hellip;</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Having realized this, I got to sleep last night around 9:30pm. I figured I&rsquo;d
sleep in until 6am or so, but naturally woke up around 5:15am. So while I&rsquo;m
feeling better this morning, I&rsquo;m still feeling the side effects of not getting
enough sleep from the first few days of the week.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll be more cautious of this for the rest of the week and see if I can get
back to a normal (whatever that means!).</p>

<h2>What I Accomplished Today</h2>

<p>Like the previous days, I was able to write Day 4 of the Build a Ruby Gem Email
Course. I had a bit of trouble getting in to the flow of writing this morning.
I&rsquo;m not sure if it&rsquo;s due to the lack of sleep mentioned above, or just a little
speed bump in the normal creative process. It took 15 min. or so until I felt
like words were coming out naturally.</p>

<h2>Changes to the Email Course</h2>

<p>On Day 3, I realized I hadn&rsquo;t gotten to the meat of the Ruby gem and was still
writing about important, but somewhat theoretical topics. It occurred to me that
it&rsquo;s probably best not to cut the content, but rather, extend the course. So
instead of a 5-day course, it might be 6 or 7. My goal is write the best content possible and if after 7 days, I
feel like I&rsquo;ve covered the topic thoroughly, I&rsquo;ll wrap it up.</p>

<p>One thought that has crossed my mind is removing some of the content for an
ebook. I could make the course somewhat abbreviated, while offering the book as
an up-sell to those interested in the details. I&rsquo;ll think about this some more
and once the course content shakes out.</p>

<p>Additionally , I thinking about spreading the course out. So rather than
send 1 email a day, shoot for every 2-3 days, so that I can market the course as
a 14 or 21-day email course. I also feel like the people that will get the most
value out of the content  would benefit from extra time in between each lesson.</p>

<h2>Marketing</h2>

<p>Visits were slightly down yesterday, and I suspect the allure of the announcement has worn off.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/woh/ga-day4.png" title="&ldquo;Google Analytics day 4 results&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>Thinking more about it, I&rsquo;ve not been great at seeking out marketing channels
for people that might be a good fit for the course. I&rsquo;ve been posting to the
same channels, which has produced a decreasing level of interest over the past
4 days. Truthfully, I&rsquo;m pretty worn out by the time I finish the email course
lesson and this update post, so it&rsquo;s difficult to get worked up for that. But
I&rsquo;ll think more about it and report back.</p>

<p>The mailing list is up to 82 subscribers, so while the growth is slowing, it&rsquo;s
still a 10% lift over the previous day. This, too, probably reiterates my need
to find users elsewhere.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/woh/mailchimp-day4.png" title="&ldquo;Mailchimp day 4 results&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>I setup the subscription form to track what page the user was on when they
subscribed. Subscriptions are coming from all over the place. It appears that even after 4 days, people are
still landing on the first post of the series and converting.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/woh/mailchimp-conversion-sources-day4.png" title="&ldquo;Mailchimp conversion sources for day 4&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>Again, Reddit appears to be the best source for both traffic and conversions.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/woh/sources-day4.png" title="&ldquo;Google Analytics day 4 traffic sources&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>Once the email course is live, I&rsquo;ll make a better effort to market the landing
page elsewhere. I think these updates may be better suited for a different
target audience anyway.</p>

<p>The end is near!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Build a Ruby Gem Email Course - Week of Hustle - Day 4]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-4/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-04T06:15:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><p>
  <em>I did an <strong>8-day sprint</strong> to launch my <a
  href="/courses/build-a-ruby-gem/" target="_blank"><strong>Build a Ruby Gem</strong> email course</a>
  and documented my progress through this series of blog posts.</em>
</p>

<p><a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-woh-day-1/">Day 1</a> |
<a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-2/">Day 2</a> |
<a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-3/">Day 3</a> |
<a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-4/">Day 4</a> |
<a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-5/">Day 5</a> |
<a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-6/">Day 6</a> |
<a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-weekend-update/">Weekend Update</a>
<a href="/blog/how-i-launched-an-email-course/">Summary</a>
</p>

<p>I let myself sleep in until 5:30am this morning ;) I spent a few very
unsuccessful hours wrestling with Wordpress last night and didn&rsquo;t get to bed at
the time I wanted. However, all is well. I was able to push out Day 4 of the
Build a Ruby Gem Email Course without issue.</p>

<p>One of the things that I&rsquo;m noticing about putting the course posts together is
how much the content relies on outside resources. Whether it&rsquo;s an external URL,
the output of a command prompt, or a diff on Github&hellip;getting those together is
a non-trivial amount of time.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>A side effect of getting up early is that by 7:30am (when I&rsquo;ve typically finish
this post), I feel really productive. At this point, I&rsquo;ve worked for 2 straight
hours, all of which have been highly focused. So at 7:30am, I take a break, get
some breakfast and take a shower and &ldquo;start&rdquo; the rest of my day. It feels like
the day starts out on a better foot as a result.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve also found that I&rsquo;ve been able to focus better early in the morning vs.
later at night. I know this is personal thing, some people do their best work
in the wee hours of the night. Not me, I&rsquo;m a morning person and have embraced
it. My productivity in the morning is probably 2-3x that of my normal
productivity during the day. I&rsquo;m not sure if it&rsquo;s because I&rsquo;m refreshed or
fewer distractions (it&rsquo;s dark, no TV, no social media, no other windows
open&hellip;).</p>

<h2>What I Accomplished Today</h2>

<p>I pushed out the latest day of the email course. I feel like it&rsquo;s just starting
to get in to the thick of things. I&rsquo;ve been really sensitive to the fact that
not every person that takes the course will be a Ruby veteran. Hopefully the
detailed discussions on load paths and basic installations won&rsquo;t detract from
the value for those that are.</p>

<p>Yesterday I mentioned the non-optimal formatting of my email campaigns on
mobile devices. I spent some time with Mailchimp last night and applied a more
responsive template to the campaign. It&rsquo;s better, but still somewhat finicky in
the iOS Gmail app. I&rsquo;ve sent a support request and hopefully I&rsquo;ll have that
ironed out soon. But for those on every other platform, you should&rsquo;ve had a
much better reading experience!</p>

<h2>Marketing</h2>

<p>As I expected, the growth of both the mailing list and page views slowed down a bit.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/woh/ga-day3.png" title="&ldquo;Google Analytics day 3 results&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>I got a 15% bump in mailing list subscriptions, which is better than nothing!</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/woh/mailchimp-day3.png" title="&ldquo;Mailchimp day 3 results&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m sending the daily update campaigns at 8pm. I didn&rsquo;t put much thought in to
this time, other than the fact that I stumbled on an email marketing post that
suggested the hours between 8-12am get the best open rates. According to the
campaign report, the open rate is doing well, as compared with the average.
However, I have a tendency to believe it&rsquo;s more due to the nature of the
opted-in target audience. This is a very specific topic that people
specifically wanted to read about. So it makes sense to me that the open rate
would be pretty high.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/woh/campaign-day3.png" title="&ldquo;Mailchimp day 3 campaign report&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>Reddit continues to be a positive source of traffic. I had haphazardly posted
to Reddit in the past, but it&rsquo;s been driving more traffic than any other
source. Along with views, it&rsquo;s also yielded one of the highest conversion rates
for the mailing list. So I&rsquo;ll continue to post my updates there.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/woh/sources-day3.png" title="&ldquo;Google Analytics day 3 traffic sources&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>Until tomorrow&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Build a Ruby Gem Email Course - Week of Hustle - Day 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-3/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-03T06:15:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>I&rsquo;m doing an
<strong>8-day sprint</strong> where I&rsquo;m launching an email course on
how to <strong>Build a Ruby Gem</strong>.</em></p>

<p><a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-woh-day-1/">Day 1</a> |
<a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-2/">Day 2</a> |
Day 3 |
<a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-4/">Day 4</a> |
<a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-5/">Day 5</a> |
<a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-6/">Day 6</a> |
<a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-weekend-update/">Weekend Update</a></p>

<h2>Back at it</h2>

<p>I hit the 5:00am goal this morning! It&rsquo;s 6:15am and I&rsquo;ve wrapped up the 2nd day of
the Build a Ruby Gem Email Course.</p>

<p>Yesterday, I had some anxiety about the amount of writing involved in putting
this course together. I&rsquo;ve read a number of blog posts about building a Ruby
gem, but most seem to assume you have a pretty in depth knowledge of creating
gems, while others skip important details of the process. So I knew going in to
it that I wanted to write about it a little differently. I wanted to talk more
about theory of why things are being done vs. how the Ruby language works.</p>

<p>Thinking back to my first Ruby gem, I remember my frustration trying to
understand the conventions of naming and file structure. So I&rsquo;m writing the course I
wish I had when I started.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Flow</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s been 3 days since I started documenting this process and the writing
process has gotten significantly easier. Since I started my blog, I&rsquo;ve read a
number of posts recommending the value of writing every day, regardless of the
subject. I&rsquo;m beginning to see the benefit of this consistency. I&rsquo;ll report back
on this by the end of the week as it should be even more apparent by then.</p>

<h2>What I Accomplished today</h2>

<p>I wrote Day 2 of the Build a Ruby Gem Email Course. The content organization
that I did on the first day has proved to be valuable. Outside of moving a few
topics around, it&rsquo;s stayed largely in tact. So here&rsquo;s to organization!!!</p>

<p>I think I also solved my email list problems. Actually, it was less &ldquo;problems&rdquo;, and
more, I need to learn how to use <a href="http://mailchimp.com/">Mailchimp</a>. I was in touch with their support
over an issue around signing up for multiple lists. I originally had the
subscriptions to the Week of Hustle updates going to my personal newsletter
list. This caused a semi-alarming error message if you were already on the
list.</p>

<p>The solution was to create a separate list and manage it outside of the realm
of my newsletter. Despite seeming over-complicated at first, I now feel
comfortable with this solution and I think it actually fits my goals better.
I&rsquo;ve already started to think of the best way to manage the email course once
it&rsquo;s live.</p>

<h2>What I&rsquo;m working on today</h2>

<p>A few people have pointed out some oddities with the formatting of my email
updates and there are a few design changes I&rsquo;d like to make on the sign up
forms. However, because the email updates are going out daily, it&rsquo;s my first
priority.</p>

<p>There have been no changes to the timeline I posted yesterday, and still feel
like I&rsquo;m on schedule to finish by the end of the weekend!</p>

<h2>Marketing</h2>

<p>I was originally worried that the buzz surrounding the course and my updates
about the process would die off and I&rsquo;d get another couple people throughout
the week. This appears to not be the case. However, I&rsquo;m not convinced it&rsquo;ll
continue this way throughout the week.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/woh/ga-day2.png" title="&ldquo;Google Analytics day 2 results&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>As you can see, traffic to the blog was almost exactly the same as the previous
day (Sunday).</p>

<p>I screwed up the Google Analytics tracking code on the layouts, so I wasn&rsquo;t
tracking email list conversions until late last night. But the good news is
that according to Mailchimp, I signed up another 25 subscribers to the updates list.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/woh/mailchimp-day2.png" title="&ldquo;Mailchimp day 2 results&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>This is down from the previous day, but overall, I couldn&rsquo;t be happier. I did
get a little boost because I sent a campaign about the course and my updates to
my newsletter email list, which seemed to account for maybe 8-10 subscriptions.</p>

<p>See you tomorrow!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
