<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: jfdi | Brandon Hilkert]]></title>
  <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/categories/jfdi/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-02T16:35:46-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brandon Hilkert]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[brandonhilkert@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Build a ruby gem email course - week of hustle - day 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-2/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-02T07:02:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-email-course-week-of-hustle-day-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Alright, back at it! I didn&rsquo;t quite hit the
5:00am goal I had, but was early enough to accomplish
what I was shooting for. (Setting my alarm for
11:58pm because namecheap.com had hourly Cyber Monday
coupon codes didn&rsquo;t help&hellip;).</p>

<p>If you remember from the <a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-woh-day-1/">previous
post</a>, I&rsquo;m doing an
<strong>8-day sprint</strong> where I&rsquo;m launching an email course on
how to <strong>Build a Ruby Gem</strong>.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;d like to stay updated via email on my progress, subscribe below.</p>

<p><div class="inline-newsletter-form">
  <form action="http://brandonhilkert.us7.list-manage2.com/subscribe/post?u=34ccc3aa2135746d0231c9420&amp;id=5619d347df" method="post" id="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" name="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" class="validate" target="_blank" novalidate>
    <input type="email" value="" name="EMAIL" class="email" id="mce-EMAIL" placeholder="email" required>
    <input type="hidden" name="LOCATION" id="LOCATION" value="Category: jfdi" />
    <input type="hidden" name="PRODUCT" id="PRODUCT" value="woh1" />
    <input type="submit" value="Subscribe" name="subscribe" id="mc-embedded-subscribe" class="button">
    <br class="clear">
  </form>
</div>

</p>

<h3>What I Accomplished today</h3>

<p>Today I wrote the first post out of 5 and it went
relatively smooth. Yesterday I created a rough outline
for the course content using
<a href="http://evernote.com/">Evernote</a>. I&rsquo;ve used it mainly as
a place to spew out the ideas that are not necessarily
organized, but just general notes about things I want to
make sure get covered (imagine that, using Evernote for
notes?!?!).</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Writing my entry for the email course caused me to
realize that I had to make a few changes to my blog to
facilitate the course (ie. hide newsletter signup at the
end of each course). Those changes probably took 10-15
min. However, I got them out of the way so I won&rsquo;t have
to worry about it anymore for future courses (I know, fat
chance a web developer leaves something alone for very
long&hellip;).</p>

<h3>What I&rsquo;m working on</h3>

<p>There&rsquo;s been some weirdness with my Mailchimp sign up
form, mostly around signing up for multiple groups as an
existing recipient. I&rsquo;ve submitted a support request and
have been reaching out to people that are far more
knowledgable than I using email lists and hope to have it
resolved by the end of the day, at which point I&rsquo;ll notify my existing
email list of the course.</p>

<h3>My new timeline</h3>

<p>I made a few changes/additions to my project timeline as
you can see below:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><del>Day 1 &ndash; Overall topic and organize what content goes on which days, setup GH
project and ready tags, write WOH day blog, why gem discussion (ref. open
source blog &ndash; pics of GA)</del></p></li>
<li><p><del>Day 2 &ndash; Write content and WOH blog (notify subscribers)</del></p></li>
<li><p>Day 3 &ndash; Write content and WOH blog (notify subscribers)</p></li>
<li><p>Day 4 &ndash; Write content and WOH blog (notify subscribers)</p></li>
<li><p>Day 5 &ndash; Write content and WOH blog (notify subscribers)</p></li>
<li><p>Day 6 &ndash; Write content and WOH blog (notify subscribers)</p></li>
<li><p>Day 7 &ndash;  Setup auto responder and way to capture for the course, write emails for each day of sequence (depending on the content). Proofread all course posts.</p></li>
<li><p>Day 8 &ndash; Launch with new landing page and notify subscribers</p></li>
</ul>


<p>I realized I needed to separate out time to proofread previous email course
content posts. After writing for over an hour, I don&rsquo;t feel like I&rsquo;m in the
best position to be critical of my writing. I think editing after the fact will
also reveal some places where content can be removed due to wordiness.</p>

<h3>Marketing</h3>

<p>I wanted to add a marketing section to each of these updates because building
an audience is such a critical piece of this process. Yesterday, I posted my
<a href="/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-woh-day-1/">Day 1</a> post around the internet and got
overwhelmingly positive feedback.</p>

<p>The &ldquo;sign up for updates&rdquo; form yielded around 40 subscriptions. My wife and I
went to the movies yesterday and at one point I looked at my phone and saw
this:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/woh/mailbox.png" title="&ldquo;My mailbox showing Mailchimp subscriptions&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>Yesterday I mentioned part of my motivation for launching this <strong>Build a Ruby
Gem</strong> email course was to determine if there was enough interest in the topic
to warrant an ebook. So far, so good&hellip;</p>

<p>Total visits to the site was 337. I&rsquo;ll take a 10% conversion rate any day!</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/woh/ga-day1.png" title="&ldquo;Google Analytics from Day 1&rdquo;" ></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Build a Ruby Gem Email Course - Week of Hustle - Day 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-woh-day-1/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-01T05:37:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-woh-day-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>JFDI</h3>

<p>Living outside a major metropolitan area has made it hard to surround myself
with other entrepreneurs. Fortunately, the internet has made the world a
smaller place. Last week I joined <a href="http://jfdi.bz/">JFDI.bz</a>, a community for
solo-founders launching their own thing.</p>

<p>My goal for joining this community was to have access to other motivated
entrepreneurs that I could use as a sounding-board. I also figured it&rsquo;d be
great opportunity to peek in to other solo founders launch process and
motivation for a particular product.</p>

<h3>Week of Hustle</h3>

<p>Week of Hustle is an 8-day sprint to launch something. Anything really&hellip;could
be an existing product that you need to put the finishing touches on, or a
brand new idea. It was one of the things that attracted most to JFDI.</p>

<p>Launching any kind of product is time consuming. And with a family and other
full-time responsibilities, life can get in the way. I feel like I&rsquo;m pretty
good at managing my time efficiently, but when accountability is involved, it&rsquo;s
much harder to put it off.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>My Goal</h3>

<p>This week I will be launching a free <strong>5-day email course</strong> focused on
<strong>Building a Ruby Gem</strong>. My goal for the course is to build my newsletter
audience and work through the steps of building a smaller info product to
determine if there&rsquo;s enough interest in the subject to warrant writing an
ebook.</p>

<p>As part of 8-day process, I will be posting blog entries daily about my
progress and the challenges I&rsquo;m facing at each step. If you&rsquo;re interested in
receiving these updates via email, subscribe here:</p>

<p><div class="inline-newsletter-form">
  <form action="http://brandonhilkert.us7.list-manage2.com/subscribe/post?u=34ccc3aa2135746d0231c9420&amp;id=5619d347df" method="post" id="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" name="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" class="validate" target="_blank" novalidate>
    <input type="email" value="" name="EMAIL" class="email" id="mce-EMAIL" placeholder="email" required>
    <input type="hidden" name="LOCATION" id="LOCATION" value="Category: jfdi" />
    <input type="hidden" name="PRODUCT" id="PRODUCT" value="woh1" />
    <input type="submit" value="Subscribe" name="subscribe" id="mc-embedded-subscribe" class="button">
    <br class="clear">
  </form>
</div>

</p>

<h3>Why an email course on Building a Ruby Gem?</h3>

<p>One of the first blog posts I wrote was about <a href="/blog/3-ways-to-get-started-contributing-to-open-source/">how to get started contributing
to Open Source</a>. I
wrote it because I remember being somewhat unsure about the topic early in my
Ruby career. Additionally, it garnered far more attention than any of my other
posts, which tells me there&rsquo;s clearly a need for this kind of discussion.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/woh/ga.png" title="&ldquo;Google Analytics of my first few blog posts.&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>The Ruby gem ecosystem is really powerful, but equally confusing, in my
opinion. There are <em>strong</em> recommendations about how to structure the
internals of a gem, which can make writing your first gem pretty frustrating.</p>

<h3>My plan this week</h3>

<p>So getting down to business&hellip;here&rsquo;s my tentative plan this week:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Day 1 &ndash; Overall topic and organize what content goes on which days, setup GH
project and ready tags, write WOH day blog, why gem discussion (ref. open
source blog &ndash; pics of GA)</p></li>
<li><p>Day 2 &ndash; Write content and WOH blog (notify subscribers)</p></li>
<li><p>Day 3 &ndash; Write content and WOH blog (notify subscribers)</p></li>
<li><p>Day 4 &ndash; Write content and WOH blog (notify subscribers)</p></li>
<li><p>Day 5 &ndash; Write content and WOH blog (notify subscribers)</p></li>
<li><p>Day 6 &ndash; Write content and WOH blog (notify subscribers)</p></li>
<li><p>Day 7 &ndash;  Setup auto responder and way to capture for the course, write emails for each day of sequence</p></li>
<li><p>Day 8 &ndash; Launch with new landing page and notify subscribers</p></li>
</ul>


<h3>Time Management</h3>

<p>I do have a full-time job and will be working all week. Because I try to spend
as much time as possible with my daughter, my goal is to accomplish the steps
above early in the AM. This morning I set my alarm for 6am, but got up 4:30am
because I was excited to start the week. Today was a relatively easy day in
terms of time-consuming tasks, so I&rsquo;m guessing I&rsquo;ll shoot for 5am the remainder
of the week. We&rsquo;ll see!</p>

<h3>Today&rsquo;s Accomplishments</h3>

<ul>
<li>I created a <a href="https://github.com/brandonhilkert/so_meta_course">Github project to house the code I&rsquo;ll write</a></li>
<li>I wrote this post</li>
<li>I setup a mail chimp entry form for subscription to my WOH updates</li>
<li>I created the structure for the email course content</li>
<li>I searched through <a href="http://reddit.com">Reddit</a> and found a <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/ruby/comments/1qplmu/tutorial_build_a_gem_from_scratch/">few posts that
express</a>
a need to <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/ruby/comments/1qmb29/building_a_gem_from_scratch_google_hangout_today/">learn about about writing Ruby
gems</a>.
Those interested in these posts would be a great target audience.</li>
</ul>


<p>So having said all that&hellip;if you&rsquo;re interested in staying up to date on my
progress or hearing about the launch of my FREE <strong>Building a Ruby Gem email
course</strong>, subscribe below:</p>

<p><div class="inline-newsletter-form">
  <form action="http://brandonhilkert.us7.list-manage2.com/subscribe/post?u=34ccc3aa2135746d0231c9420&amp;id=5619d347df" method="post" id="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" name="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" class="validate" target="_blank" novalidate>
    <input type="email" value="" name="EMAIL" class="email" id="mce-EMAIL" placeholder="email" required>
    <input type="hidden" name="LOCATION" id="LOCATION" value="Category: jfdi" />
    <input type="hidden" name="PRODUCT" id="PRODUCT" value="woh1" />
    <input type="submit" value="Subscribe" name="subscribe" id="mc-embedded-subscribe" class="button">
    <br class="clear">
  </form>
</div>

</p>

<p>Until tomorrow!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
