<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: open source | Brandon Hilkert]]></title>
  <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/categories/open-source/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-16T13:56:34-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Brandon Hilkert]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[brandonhilkert@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Absolutes as an AntiPattern]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/absolutes-as-an-antipattern/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-28T22:35:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/absolutes-as-an-antipattern</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s been awhile since my last post — almost 2 months to be specific. A trip to Portugal, getting sick and a minor run-in with a table saw made it challenging to post anything for the last couple weeks. But I’d be lying if I said I was itching to write.</p>

<p>During that time, I didn’t have anything screaming to be talked about. I have a long list of “decent post” topics, but none of them got me particularly excited. Until today…</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I stumbled on a blog post related to Rails’s upcoming <a href="http://edgeguides.rubyonrails.org/active_job_basics.html">Active Job feature</a>. While demonstrating the syntax for specifying the adapter, there was comment in the code snippet that said <em>“inline and other worse options”</em>. This caught me by surprise and bummed me out at the same time. Not only because I’m the author of <a href="https://github.com/brandonhilkert/sucker_punch">one of them</a>, but because there are a handful of background processing libraries in Ruby that are really good.</p>

<p>So, naturally, I pinged the author and mentioned the comment might be sending the wrong message. He responded with “I consider sidekiq to be the best background processing tool available for Ruby.” And then later, <em>“sidekiq is significantly better that delayed_job and resque. You’re welcome to disagree”</em>.</p>

<p><em>Note: The responses above illustrate a general sentiment. By no means is this post focused on the individual that said them.</em></p>

<p>The thing is, I don’t completely disagree. As you probably already know, I’m a huge fan of of <a href="http://sidekiq.org/">Sidekiq</a>. I’ve contributed to the project and believe Sidekiq’s author, <a href="https://www.mikeperham.com/">Mike Perham</a> is not only a great leader in the Ruby community, but a great example of how to manage and lead open source projects well.</p>

<p>However, those responses reminded me how damaging absolutes can be. You’ve probably heard it before:</p>

<blockquote><p>“we can <strong>ABSOLUTELY NOT</strong> do x, y and z”</p></blockquote>

<p><em>Why not? Will the world end? How do I know?</em></p>

<p>or, what about:</p>

<blockquote><p>“this feature needs to go out tomorrow, no excuses”</p></blockquote>

<p><em>What if there is an excuse? What if it’s not ready? Will I be fired? Will our company go under?</em></p>

<p>There are trade-offs to every decision made. While some options may not be ideal, they may still work, perhaps just not as well.</p>

<p>Absolutes beg the toddler question, <em>”why?”</em>. <em>Why won’t that language X work?</em> <em>Why can’t we use Y?</em>. If you don’t know the answer to those questions, you’re doing yourself a disservice by not asking. Maybe the person has thoroughly researched the topic to come up with those conclusions. But, maybe, they haven’t.</p>

<p>I’ve noticed those who do exhaustive research on a topic tend to present the information in a different manner. They’re confident the facts they found will prove their case and seem to present their findings less defensively. No, <em>”it has to be done like this”</em>. More like, <em>“I found a few ways to fix the problem and here’s why I think option 1 might be the best solution. What do you think?”</em>.</p>

<p>Whether you follow agile or any other methodology, predictions and absolutes have no place in conversations. There are plenty of examples of failed software projects. I’m pretty sure all of them featured people promising the work would be done in time and under budget. Buuuuuuut, it wasn’t.</p>

<h2>Background Jobs for the Big Boys</h2>

<p>Delayed Job was the first Ruby background processing library I used. I remember feeling badass that I was doing all this complicated stuff in the background. But at some point, there we so many jobs and so much activity that pushing and pulling jobs out of the primary data store wasn’t efficient. Reads from the web UI would slow down (and ultimately stop) and users would bail. Unfortunately, I couldn’t pop up a message and say, <em>”hey, hope you don’t mind, but I’m doing some pretty crucial shit in the background here, so you’re experience is gonna be sucky for a bit! sorry :(”</em>.</p>

<p>So, at the time, Resque was the next logical transition. I migrated the previously written jobs from Delayed Job to Resque and experienced a new level of <em>bad ass</em>. Fast forward 4 years — I still work on projects using Resque. Needless to say, it’s a pretty awesome piece of open source software.</p>

<p>A few years ago, Sidekiq came along. While I didn’t know much about multi-threading code in Ruby, I tried it on a side project and was floored at the results. Those 6 Heroku workers that I’d been paying for could be compacted in to 1?!?! And on top of that, I only needed 1 worker that had 25 workers working against the queue?!?!</p>

<p>But then one day, I dropped it in to a project that was using MongoDB and MongoMapper as ORM and things didn’t go so well. In the end, MongoMapper wasn’t thread-safe, which is a requirement of Sidekiq worker code. So in that case, was Sidekiq the best tool for the job? While I would’ve loved to use Sidekiq on that project, it certainly (like the absolute there…) wasn’t the right tool for <em>that</em> job.</p>

<p>And what about when I first started with Delayed Job…we were a small startup with limited cash. While it seems silly to balk over an extra $35 Heorku dyno, it was $35 that could’ve gone towards something else. Not to mention the extra Redis instance, along with the expertise to make sure the thing didn’t fall over and die. Was Sidekiq (or Resque for that matter) the best tool for that job? Nope!</p>

<p>Fast forward a few years, I had the need for an in-process background processing library, so <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/why-i-wrote-the-sucker-punch-gem/">I wrote one</a>. That need was driven off the motivation above — needing to minimize cost and complexity. Would Sidekiq have worked for that project? Of course! In fact, it was using Sidekiq for a year or so before I transitioned the jobs to use Sucker Punch.</p>

<h2>Use Cases</h2>

<p>At this point, you should be noticing a trend, right? The examples above were unique use cases with a unique set of requirements and limitations. Sure, if every project I worked on had unlimited resources (both time and money), Sidekiq would be probably be my go-to the majority of time (even when writing that sentence I hesitated and almost wrote “all the time”).</p>

<p>But I hesitate now. Because I remember learning about the new cool things and thinking, <em>”This is the best! There’s no way I’ll never not use it”</em>. And when I would talk to other developers, I would rave about how <em>X</em> is the best for <em>Y</em>. And now I realize I was a dummy for doing that. There’s no way I could’ve made that judgement for someone else and their work. What I really should’ve said was, <em>”I tried [insert fancy new gem/technique] for the first time the other day. It worked really well for doing X in my project that does Y”</em>. That definitely doesn’t sound as exciting, but it was the truth.</p>

<p>I feel fortunate to get to write Ruby everyday. It’s incredibly expressive, which is why the debate over the countless ways to do something is great. Does the code express the right intent? For your method, it might. But for mine, it might express the complete opposite. The good news is, that’s OK. Both versions will work and the fact that we can have conversations like that is a praise for the language itself. I prefer to have the opportunity to have that conversation about style, rather than a language more black and white. Maybe it’s the creative in me, but it seems like no 2 Ruby solutions will be identical and that’s one of the things I love most about writing Ruby.</p>

<p>We often joke about the stack overflow post that starts with <em>“I’m thinking about learning Rails…is it better than PHP?”</em>. Or even more relevant today, <em>”Which javascript framework should I use?”</em>.</p>

<p>And then there’s the guy who comes along and is all like, <em>”Let’s back up, what are you doing and why do you absolutely need a FRAMEWORK????”</em>. While I used to ignore those types of comments, they’re the kind that I think about now and find myself typing. And that has me wondering…why the change?</p>

<h2>Experience, Experience, Experience</h2>

<p>I got to thinking about how I felt when I was first learning to program. When I started to feel comfortable with Rails, my confidence was through the roof. But at the same time, my naivety was at an all time high. I had had minimal experiences with software systems that were either critical or heavily-loaded. But having found Resque, I felt like I could solve the world’s problems. This is somewhat of an exaggeration, but not too far off. I realized that, as it relates to my technical career, my naivety is doing this related to time:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/absolutes/naivety-graph.png" title="&ldquo;Graph of Naivety over Time&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>The less naivety, the more options and, naturally, certainty takes a nose dive:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/absolutes/certainty-graph.png" title="&ldquo;Graph of Certainty over Time&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>The more I learn about programming in general, the more questions I have. Fortunately, experiences have brought me to a point where I can fairly weigh the use of Sucker Punch or Delayed Job for a particular use case. I’m not sure projecting absolutes from up high does anyone any good. Beginners will take it as the word and spread the message to others they come across.</p>

<p>Use cases are real. And the less we force our own biases on people, the faster they’ll realize experience is key and the random guy behind the cat avatar on Stack Overflow might actually be asking the right questions — even if they are convoluted.</p>

<p>Next time you hear an absolute, ask <em>”Why?”</em>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Build a Ruby Gem - Ruby Heroes]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-ruby-heroes/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-09T06:03:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-ruby-heroes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s been 3 months since the release of <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/books/build-a-ruby-gem/?utm_source=bh-newsletter&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=rubyheroes"><em>Build a Ruby Gem</em></a> and I’ve gotten tremendous feedback since the launch.</p>

<p>I’ve love to share some news and an opportunity to win a <strong>FREE</strong> copy of the book. If you’ve already purchased the book, don’t worry, we’ll find a way to make it worth it for you.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Feedback</h2>

<p>The two questions I’ve heard the most since the release of the <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/courses/build-a-ruby-gem/?utm_source=bh-newsletter&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=rubyheroes">email course</a> and <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/books/build-a-ruby-gem/?utm_source=bh-newsletter&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=rubyheroes">book</a> are:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Why should I get involved with open source software?</p></li>
<li><p>How do I get started contributing to an open source project?</p></li>
</ol>


<h2>Benefits of Getting Involved</h2>

<p>Participating in open source projects is an enlightening experience. The benefits are widespread and different for each developer. Speaking personally, I’ve learned a ton from the codebases I’ve gotten involved with. Learning was the primary reason I got involved in the first place.</p>

<p>Going beyond the learning aspect, my open source contributions have resulted in several <strong>jobs offers</strong>, among other things. It’s easy to think that getting involved is only just about doing good for the community — but it’s <strong>bigger than that</strong>.</p>

<p>I could go on and on, but it’s likely you’ve already heard me talk about this through my post on <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/3-ways-to-get-started-contributing-to-open-source/?utm_source=bh-newsletter&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=rubyheroes">ways to get started contributing to open source</a> or the <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/books/build-a-ruby-gem/?utm_source=bh-newsletter&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=rubyheroes">open source chapter in <em>Build a Ruby Gem</em></a>.</p>

<h2>Hear It From Others in the Community</h2>

<p>Hearing other people’s stories has always had a profound effect on my comfort-level when approaching things I’m unfamiliar with. So with that being said, I want you to hear the answers to the questions above from those YOU look up to in the Ruby community.</p>

<p>This person could be the author of your favorite gem or Matz himself (disclaimer: I may or may not be able to make this one happen…). Either way, I’ll do my best to have live interview chats with your favorite Rubyists and dig through their experience and thoughts on the community and software in general.</p>

<p><em>Entries have closed for the giveaway.</em></p>

<p>Submissions will be open until <strong>5:00pm EDT on Friday, July 11</strong>. I’ll announcement the winner shortly thereafter.</p>

<p>Even if you don’t win, I’ll send everyone that submits a response a <strong>20% discount code</strong> for any package of <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/books/build-a-ruby-gem/?utm_source=bh-newsletter&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=rubyheroes"><em>Build a Ruby Gem</em></a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rails Reloader: A Lesser Known Railtie Hook]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/rails-reloader-a-lesser-known-railtie-hook/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-21T19:48:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/rails-reloader-a-lesser-known-railtie-hook</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently wrote <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/books/build-a-ruby-gem/?utm_source=bh-come&amp;utm_medium=web&amp;utm_campaign=reloader">a book about integrating with Rails from a Ruby gem</a>, which specifically touched on using a <a href="http://api.rubyonrails.org/classes/Rails/Railtie.html">Railtie</a> to extend <code>ActiveRecord</code>, <code>ActionController</code> and <code>ActionView</code> . While these are the 3 more popular Rails libraries, there’s plenty others <a href="http://guides.rubyonrails.org/configuring.html">that are configurable</a>.</p>

<p>A <a href="https://github.com/brandonhilkert/sucker_punch/issues/49">recent issue</a> in <a href="https://github.com/brandonhilkert/sucker_punch">Sucker Punch</a> caused me to go digging through the Rails source code. Ultimately, the <code>to_prepare</code> method on <code>ActionDispatch::Reloader</code> resolved the issue, but I surprised was to find very little documentation about it.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>The Problem</h2>

<p><a href="https://github.com/brandonhilkert/sucker_punch">Sucker Punch</a> lazily creates the <a href="http://celluloid.io/">Celluloid</a> pools used for background job queues. For the purpose of keeping track of the queues already initialized, Sucker Punch makes use of the <a href="https://github.com/celluloid/celluloid/wiki/Registry">Celluloid Registry</a>. Think of it as a class-level hash.</p>

<p>This works swimmingly in production, but not so much in development. Rails makes our lives easier by reloading code in between requests while in development, due to this setting in <code>config/environments/development.rb</code>:</p>

<p><code>
  config.cache_classes = false
</code></p>

<p>Without it, we’d be forced to restart the server after almost every request. If that sounds like a giant PITA to you, I whole heartedly agree!</p>

<p>So now you make your awesome job class, do some background work (send an email for example) and reload the page and boom:</p>

<p><code>``
Celluloid::PoolManager: async call</code>perform` aborted!
ArgumentError: A copy of SendInvitationJob has been removed from the module tree but is still active!</p>

<pre><code>    gems/activesupport-4.0.3/lib/active_support/dependencies.rb:446:in `load_missing_constant'
    gems/activesupport-4.0.3/lib/active_support/dependencies.rb:184:in `const_missing'
    my-app/app/jobs/send_invitation_job.rb:6:in `block in perform'
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>The Celluloid registry still has reference to a the original <code>SendInvitationJob</code> class when it was initialized, however, reloading the code has caused the original reference to disappear and all hell breaks loose when the queue key is fetched to send another job to the class.</p>

<p>In my head, it made sense for the queues to be cleared out upon every request in development. In general, because Sucker Punch doesn’t have persistent queues, the best use case is for quick one-off jobs that aren’t extremely important — email and logging come to mind. Since both of these examples are typically pretty speedy, it’s unlikely there will be a huge job backup upon subsequent requests.</p>

<p>I knew what I wanted, but didn’t know how to accomplish it.</p>

<h2>The Solution</h2>

<p>Knowing the issue was related to the setting <code>config.cache_classes = false</code> in the development environment, I broke open the Rails source code and searched for <code>cache_classes</code>. The first result was the <a href="https://github.com/rails/rails/blob/master/actionpack/lib/action_dispatch/middleware/reloader.rb"><code>ActionDispatch</code> reloader middleware</a>. Fortunately, there’s a very descriptive comment at the top of the class:</p>

<p><code>
  # By default, ActionDispatch::Reloader is included in the middleware stack
  # only in the development environment; specifically, when +config.cache_classes+
  # is false. Callbacks may be registered even when it is not included in the
  # middleware stack, but are executed only when &lt;tt&gt;ActionDispatch::Reloader.prepare!&lt;/tt&gt;
  # or &lt;tt&gt;ActionDispatch::Reloader.cleanup!&lt;/tt&gt; are called manually.
</code></p>

<p>This functionality is exactly what I needed!. From here, I just needed to know what callbacks were valid. A few lines in to the class are the following methods:</p>

<p>```</p>

<pre><code># Add a prepare callback. Prepare callbacks are run before each request, prior
# to ActionDispatch::Callback's before callbacks.
def self.to_prepare(*args, &amp;block)
  unless block_given?
    warn "to_prepare without a block is deprecated. Please use a block"
  end
  set_callback(:prepare, *args, &amp;block)
end

# Add a cleanup callback. Cleanup callbacks are run after each request is
# complete (after #close is called on the response body).
def self.to_cleanup(*args, &amp;block)
  unless block_given?
    warn "to_cleanup without a block is deprecated. Please use a block"
  end
  set_callback(:cleanup, *args, &amp;block)
end
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p><code>to_prepare</code> and <code>to_cleanup</code>…and like the comments say, they do exactly what you’d expect. Given that I wanted to clear our the Celluloid registry BEFORE each request, <code>on_prepare</code> is the golden ticket. Now I just needed to figure out how to clear the registry.</p>

<p>A quick glade over the <a href="http://rubydoc.info/gems/celluloid/Celluloid/Registry"><code>Celluloid::Registry</code> class documentation</a> shows some methods that might be of value. It turns out that these are instance methods for an instance of the <code>Celluloid::Registry</code> class. Unfortunately, when Celluloid boots, it instantiates a registry to use internally, so we need a way to get at that particular instance and clear it out. Sure enough, <a href="http://rubydoc.info/gems/celluloid/Celluloid/Actor#clear_registry-class_method">a class method to do just that in <code>Celluloid::Actor</code></a> is available.</p>

<p>Now that we all the pieces of the puzzle, it was time to put together a Railtie to trigger the behavior. Prior to needing this functionality, the Railtie in Sucker Punch was pretty simple:</p>

<p>```
module SuckerPunch
  class Railtie &lt; ::Rails::Railtie</p>

<pre><code>initializer "sucker_punch.logger" do
  SuckerPunch.logger = Rails.logger
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>All it did was connect the logger to the existing Rails logger. Adding the callback to <code>ActionDispatch</code> looks like:</p>

<p>```
module SuckerPunch
  class Railtie &lt; ::Rails::Railtie</p>

<pre><code>initializer "sucker_punch.logger" do
  SuckerPunch.logger = Rails.logger
end

config.to_prepare do
  Celluloid::Actor.clear_registry
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>Now when the Railtie is loaded, the <code>Celluloid::Actor.clear_registry</code> method is triggered before the reloading of code in the development environment, clearing out the Celluloid registry and allowing Sucker Punch to instantiate new job queues for each request.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>I was unaware of any of these methods when the issue was submitted. Rather than throw my hands up and close the issue because it didn’t affect me, I thought through an approach that could work, and only then started to write code. And in fact, didn’t know what code to write!</p>

<p>Comments and well written code serve as great documentation. I probably wouldn’t have stumbled on <code>ActionDispatch::Reloader</code> without the detailed comments at the top of the class. Sure, I would’ve found the <code>cache_classes</code> line, but might not have given it more thought.</p>

<p>Next time you have a question about the syntax of a method or the order of its arguments, clone the repo (if it’s open source, of course) and do a search. I think you’ll be surprised at how quickly you can find what you’re looking for. My guess is you’ll also be pleasantly surprised at the other things you stumble upon in the process.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Build a Ruby Gem eBook is Live!]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-is-live/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-26T23:49:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/build-a-ruby-gem-is-live</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After several weeks of <strong>really</strong> early mornings, <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/books/build-a-ruby-gem?utm_source=bh-com&amp;utm_medium=web&amp;utm_campaign=launch"><em>Build a Ruby Gem</em></a> is finally live:</p>

<p><a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/books/build-a-ruby-gem?utm_source=bh-com&amp;utm_medium=web&amp;utm_campaign=launch">http://brandonhilkert.com/books/build-a-ruby-gem/</a></p>

<p>Thanks again for all the support and encouragement. I had a great time working
on it and really look forward to hearing your feedback.</p>

<!--more-->

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Build a Rails Engine]]></title>
    <link href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/how-to-build-a-rails-engine/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-24T17:26:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/how-to-build-a-rails-engine</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>_This is one of the final post leading up the the launch of the
[__Build a Ruby Gem Ebook__](/books/build-a-ruby-gem/?utm_source=bh-com&utm_medium=web&utm_campaign=launch),
which is now available for sale in [3 packages](/books/build-a-ruby-gem/?utm_source=bh-com&utm_medium=web&utm_campaign=launch),
including __14 chapters of code__ and over 2 hours of screencasts_.


</p>

<p>Rails engines range from simple plugins to powerful micro-applications. The discussions we’ve had so far about Railties are closely related to the function of a Rails engine. One interesting side note is that a Rails application is a Rails engine itself — so it’s easy to see how we can encapsulate just about any normal Rails functionality in an engine, to ultimately embed in a host application.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://guides.rubyonrails.org/engines.html?utm_source=bh-com&amp;utm_medium=web&amp;utm_campaign=rails-engines">Rails engine documentation</a> is well written and touches on the many ways to include functionality. I won’t cover every detail of Rails engines in this chapter, just enough to get you started making use of them. It’s possible to make full applications (routes, controllers, models, migrations, etc.) using Rails engines. However, we’re going to focus on some of the simpler the elements of a Rails engine that allow us to integrate functionality where a Railtie won’t suffice. Just know, there is far more you can do with Rails engines than what we’ll cover here. The documentation link above provides examples of many of those use cases.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Use Case</h2>

<p>I wrote a <a href="http://brandonhilkert.com/blog/relative-timestamps-in-rails/?utm_source=bh-com&amp;utm_medium=web&amp;utm_campaign=rails-engines">blog post about rendering relatives timestamps in Rails</a> on the client. Using a client-side solution like <a href="http://timeago.yarp.com/?utm_source=bh-com&amp;utm_medium=web&amp;utm_campaign=rails-engines">timeago.js</a> allows timestamps to update in real-time, so when we see “15 minutes ago”, we know the record <em>really</em> is 15 minutes old.</p>

<p>The other benefit to using a client-side library like <code>timeago.js</code> is timezone offsets are handled automatically. All we have to do is render the UTC time in the view and javascript will handle converting it to the relative timezone of the browser, along with keeping it updated as the page becomes stale.</p>

<p>For this example, we’ll make a gem that integrates <code>timeago.js</code> in to a Rails application and provides a simple way to render relative timestamps in a view.</p>

<h2>The Implementation</h2>

<p>The implementation of our gem will require:</p>

<ol>
<li>Adding the <code>timeago.js</code> javascript asset to the asset pipeline</li>
<li>Adding a javascript asset to invoke the <code>timeago()</code> plugin</li>
<li>Adding a view helper to render html in a format the javascript plugin expects</li>
</ol>


<p>The third requirement was covered in a previous chapter on view helpers, so we’ll cruise through that one quickly. However, including assets hasn’t been covered and it’s the perfect segue in to the benefits of using a Rails engine, rather than just a Railtie.</p>

<p>Rails engines allow us create the same directory structure of a Rails application, since a Rails application is just a Rails engine. By indicating our gem is an engine (we’ll see how to do this soon…), Rails will pick up the related files in the Rails-specific directories in our gem. So if we add a file in the <code>app/helpers/</code> directory of our gem, that same file will be available in the host Rails application. The same approach applies for controllers, models, migrations, assets and anything else we would add to a typical Rails application.</p>

<p>To start, let’s create our new gem:</p>

<p>```bash
$ bundle gem time_ago</p>

<pre><code>  create  time_ago/Gemfile
  create  time_ago/Rakefile
  create  time_ago/LICENSE.txt
  create  time_ago/README.md
  create  time_ago/.gitignore
  create  time_ago/time_ago.gemspec
  create  time_ago/lib/time_ago.rb
  create  time_ago/lib/time_ago/version.rb
</code></pre>

<p>Initializing git repo in /Users/bhilkert/Dropbox/code/time_ago
```</p>

<p>When we include javascript libraries from external sources, the <code>vender/</code> directory is the most appropriate place for them. Let’s create the directory <code>vendor/assets/javascripts/</code> and place the source for the <code>timeago.js</code> plugin there:</p>

<p>```bash
├── Gemfile
├── LICENSE.txt
├── Rakefile
├── lib
│   ├── time_ago
│   │   └── version.rb
│   └── time_ago.rb
├── time_ago.gemspec
└── vendor</p>

<pre><code>└── assets
    └── javascripts
        └── jquery.timeago.js
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>To create our view helper, we’ll add the <code>/app/helpers/</code> directory:</p>

<p>```bash
├── Gemfile
├── LICENSE.txt
├── Rakefile
├── app
│   └── helpers
│       └── time_ago_helper.rb
├── lib
│   ├── time_ago
│   │   └── version.rb
│   └── time_ago.rb
├── time_ago.gemspec
└── vendor</p>

<pre><code>└── assets
    └── javascripts
        └── jquery.timeago.js
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>The code for the view helper is shown below:</p>

<p>```ruby
module TimeAgoHelper
  def timeago(time, options = {})</p>

<pre><code>options[:class] ||= "timeago"
content_tag(
 :time,
 time.to_s,
 options.merge(datetime: time.getutc.iso8601)
) if time
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>Lastly, we want to include a javascript asset to invoke the <code>timeago.js</code> plugin on page change (this includes the initial page load). This is almost identical to the first step of including the vendored <code>timeago.js</code> asset, except we’re going to put it in the <code>app/assets/javascripts/</code> directory since it’s not an external library, but rather a javascript include that will invoke the javascript plugin.</p>

<p>Let’s create the directory <code>app/assets/javascripts/</code> and place the following file there:</p>

<p>```javascript
// app/assets/javascripts/timeago.js
//
// jQuery Timeago setup for timeago helper
//
//= require jquery.timeago</p>

<p>$(document).on(&lsquo;page:change&rsquo;, function() {
  $(&ldquo;time.timeago&rdquo;).timeago();
});
```</p>

<p>This file serves as both a manifest file for the <code>jquery.timeago.js</code> asset and a function to invoke the plugin whenever the page loads or changes.</p>

<p>Lastly, we need to designate our gem as an engine. The default entry file that was created when we used bundler to bootstrap our gem looked like this:</p>

<p>```ruby
require &ldquo;time_ago/version&rdquo;</p>

<p>module TimeAgo
end
```</p>

<p>All we need to do is add the <code>Engine</code> class and inherit from <code>Rails::Engine</code>, giving us:</p>

<p>```ruby
require &ldquo;time_ago/version&rdquo;</p>

<p>module TimeAgo
  class Engine &lt; ::Rails::Engine
  end
end
```</p>

<p>At this point, because our gem is so closely tied to Rails, we should add Rails as a dependency in our gemspec:</p>

<p>```ruby</p>

<h1>coding: utf-8</h1>

<p>lib = File.expand_path(&lsquo;../lib&rsquo;, <strong>FILE</strong>)
$LOAD_PATH.unshift(lib) unless $LOAD_PATH.include?(lib)
require &lsquo;time_ago/version&rsquo;</p>

<p>Gem::Specification.new do |spec|
  spec.name          = &ldquo;time_ago&rdquo;
  spec.version       = TimeAgo::VERSION
  spec.authors       = [&ldquo;Brandon Hilkert&rdquo;]
  spec.email         = [&ldquo;<a href="&#109;&#x61;&#105;&#108;&#116;&#x6f;&#58;&#x62;&#x72;&#x61;&#x6e;&#x64;&#111;&#110;&#104;&#105;&#108;&#107;&#x65;&#114;&#116;&#x40;&#103;&#x6d;&#x61;&#105;&#108;&#x2e;&#99;&#111;&#x6d;">&#98;&#x72;&#x61;&#110;&#x64;&#111;&#x6e;&#104;&#105;&#108;&#x6b;&#x65;&#114;&#116;&#x40;&#103;&#109;&#x61;&#105;&#x6c;&#46;&#x63;&#x6f;&#x6d;</a>&rdquo;]
  spec.summary       = %q{A gem to integrate the timeago.js}
  spec.description   = %q{A gem to integrate the timeago.js}
  spec.homepage      = &ldquo;&rdquo;
  spec.license       = &ldquo;MIT&rdquo;</p>

<p>  spec.files         = <code>git ls-files -z</code>.split(&ldquo;\x0&rdquo;)
  spec.executables   = spec.files.grep(%r{^bin/}) { |f| File.basename(f) }
  spec.test_files    = spec.files.grep(%r{^(test|spec|features)/})
  spec.require_paths = [&ldquo;lib&rdquo;]</p>

<p>  spec.add_dependency &ldquo;rails&rdquo;, &ldquo;>= 3.1&rdquo;</p>

<p>  spec.add_development_dependency &ldquo;bundler&rdquo;, &ldquo;~> 1.5&rdquo;
  spec.add_development_dependency &ldquo;rake&rdquo;
end
```</p>

<p><em>Note: In addition to adding Rails as a dependency, we’ve also specified that it’s only compatible with Rails version <code>3.1</code> or later because of the need for the asset pipeline.</em></p>

<p>Moving to a sample Rails application, we can include the gem in our host application by adding it to the <code>Gemfile</code> using the path option:</p>

<p><code>ruby
gem "time_ago", path: "../time_ago"
</code></p>

<p>Since we included an asset that needs to be included in the Rails asset pipeline, we have to take one more step and instruct the user to add the following to their <code>app/assets/javascripts/application.js</code> manifest file:</p>

<p><code>javascript
//= require timeago
</code></p>

<p>This directive actually refers to the <code>app/assets/javascripts/timeago.js</code> file we included in our gem to invoke the timeago.js plugin on page change.</p>

<p>Now when we load our Rails application, tags using the <code>timeago</code> view helper get rendered to UI as:</p>

<p>```html
<time class="timeago" datetime="2014-01-08T14:55:58Z"></p>

<pre><code>2014-01-08 14:55:58 UTC
</code></pre>

<p></time>
```</p>

<p>and are updated by the javascript plugin to:</p>

<p>```html
<time class="timeago" datetime="2014-01-08T15:04:10Z"
   title="2014-01-08 15:04:10 UTC"></p>

<pre><code> 18 days ago
</code></pre>

<p></time>
```</p>

<h2>Implementations in the Wild</h2>

<p>One of the greatest examples of making the most of a Rails engine is <a href="https://github.com/plataformatec/devise?utm_source=bh-com&amp;utm_medium=web&amp;utm_campaign=rails-engines">Devise</a>. Devise is one of the more popular options for adding authentication to a Rails application. Just looking at the <a href="https://github.com/plataformatec/devise/tree/master/app?utm_source=bh-com&amp;utm_medium=web&amp;utm_campaign=rails-engines">app directory of the gem</a>, we can see Devise adds functionality through controllers, helpers, mailers and views. The structure of Devise is fairly complicated because it is doing so much, but <a href="https://github.com/plataformatec/devise/blob/master/lib/devise/rails.rb?utm_source=bh-com&amp;utm_medium=web&amp;utm_campaign=rails-engines#L5">here is where the Rails engine is defined</a> allowing the elements in the <code>/app</code> directory (among other things) to be integrated in to a Rails application.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://github.com/basecamp/local_time?utm_source=bh-com&amp;utm_medium=web&amp;utm_campaign=rails-engines">local_time gem</a> from Basecamp is a simple example of using the asset includes of a Rails engine to render relative timestamps. It’s similar to the one we created above, but uses the <a href="http://momentjs.com/?utm_source=bh-com&amp;utm_medium=web&amp;utm_campaign=rails-engines">moment.js</a> javascript library instead. Because it’s well tested and likely to be supported long-term, I’d suggest using it instead of the gem we created above.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>The introduction of Rails engines created a new way to organize micro-applications and integrate them into a host application. Doing so keeps features and otherwise separate logic truly separate.</p>

<p>I’ve only scratched the surface on what a gem can provide through engines. It’s certainly more detailed than just asset and view helper integration, as shown above. If you’re interested in learning more about the other features Rails engine provide, <a href="http://guides.rubyonrails.org/engines.html?utm_source=bh-com&amp;utm_medium=web&amp;utm_campaign=rails-engines">the Rails guides</a> are a great place to start.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
